<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of the grounds or causes, which are said to induce the court of Boston in New-England to make that order or law of banishment upon pain of death against the Quakers; as also of the grounds and considerations by them produced to manifest the warrantableness and justness both of their making and executing the same, which they now stand deeply engaged to defend, having already thereupon put two of them to death. As also of some further grounds for justifying of the same, in an appendix to John Norton's book ... whereto he is said to be appointed by the General Court. And likewise of the arguments briefly hinted in that which is called, A true relation of the proceedings against the Quakers, &amp;c. Whereunto somewhat is added about the authority and government which Christ excluded out of his Church ... By Isaac Penington, the younger.</title>
            <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1020_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863202</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 151:E1020[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of the grounds or causes, which are said to induce the court of Boston in New-England to make that order or law of banishment upon pain of death against the Quakers; as also of the grounds and considerations by them produced to manifest the warrantableness and justness both of their making and executing the same, which they now stand deeply engaged to defend, having already thereupon put two of them to death. As also of some further grounds for justifying of the same, in an appendix to John Norton's book ... whereto he is said to be appointed by the General Court. And likewise of the arguments briefly hinted in that which is called, A true relation of the proceedings against the Quakers, &amp;c. Whereunto somewhat is added about the authority and government which Christ excluded out of his Church ... By Isaac Penington, the younger.</title>
                  <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for L. Lloyd, next to the sign of the Castle in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to the appendix in the 1660 edition of "The heart of N-England rent at the blasphemies of the present generation" by John Norton, and to "A true relation of the proceedings against certain Quakers, at the generall Court of the Massachusets holden at Boston in New-England October. 18. 1659".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norton, John, 1606-1663. --  Heart of N-England rent at the blasphemies of the present generation.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts. --  General Court. --  True relation of the proceedings against certain Quakers, at the generall Court of the Massachusets holden at Boston in New-England October. 18. 1659.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Massachusetts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF THE Grounds or Cauſes, Which are ſaid to induce the Court of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> to make that Order or Law of Baniſhment upon pain of Death againſt the <hi>Quakers;</hi> As alſo of the Grounds and Conſiderations by them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to manifeſt the warrantableneſs and juſtneſs both of their making and executing the ſame, which they now ſtand deeply engaged to defend, having already thereupon put two of them to death. As alſo of ſome further Grounds for juſtifying of the ſame, in an <hi>Appendix</hi> to <hi>John Norton's</hi> Book (which was Printed after the Book it ſelf, yet as part thereof) whereto he is ſaid to be appointed by the General Court. And likewiſe of the Arguments briefly hinted in that which is called, <hi>A true Relation of the Proceedings againſt the</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereunto ſomewhat is added about the Authority and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which Chriſt excluded out of his Church, which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth ſomewhat concerning the true Church-Government.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iſaac Penington,</hi> the Younger.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Stone the Builders refuſed, is become the head of the Corner. This is the Lords doing; it is marvellous in our eyes,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 118.22, 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes. Even ſo Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 11.25, 26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>L. Lloyd,</hi> next to the Sign of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115389:2"/>
            <head>To the Rulers, Teachers, and People of
<hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAny a weary ſtep hath my poor ſoul fetched, and many difficulties and hardſhips hath it met with in its pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit after truth. The immortal ſeed hath deeply ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in me through the miſts of darkneſs, and various ſtratagems and powers of the enemy, which have often encompaſſed me, and diſtreſſed my Spirit exceedingly. I have known many bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, received deep wounds, yea and have been in deaths and graves often, where the living ſeed hath languiſhed for want of the living ſpring. Yet this thing to the praiſe and glory of the preſerver of
<hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> may I ſpeak, the ſence of God and the ſavour of his Spirit was never wholly taken away from me, though many times I knew it not, but was too apt to diſtruſt it, being ignorant of the way of its appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in me. The Scriptures I alwayes exceedingly prized, and a deep knowledge of them (from an experimental ſence of the things they ſpake of) was beſtowedon me: but I knew not what it was which gave me the knowledge, nor how it ſprang, but went about ſtill to fix it in the letter, and ſo gave away the glory from the ſpirit, which ſhines above and beyond the letter, and ought ſo to be acknowledged. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this deſpiſed people appeared, I was even quite worn out, and ſaid, my hope is cut off from the Lord, there is no ſuch appearance of him to be looked for, as my poor diſtreſſed ſoul wants. Live without the preſence of his ſpirit I could not, where to meet with his ſpirit could I hear no news; and that pretious knowledge which I had had through the operation of God upon my heart from the living ſpring, the ſame hand which gave me, alſo brake in pieces, and pulled down that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward building which was reared up in my Spirit. What a man of ſorrows I became hereupon, how I mourned all the day long, and roared out after my God all the night ſeaſon, is not to be uttered. And if it might be the Lords pleaſure, O that my miſery might end with me, and that this might be the iſſue of all my ſufferings, to fit me to be a faithful inſtrument in the hand of the Lord for the preſerving of others there from! Now this was it which undid me, namely the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the fleſhly wiſdome and underſtanding, which though God had broken in me mightily ſeveral times, yet it ſtill had ſome ſecret device or other to creep in again unto me, and to twine about my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, undiſcerned by me: but this effect ſtill attended it, by degrees <pb facs="tcp:115389:3"/> (like a canker) it eat out the ſweetneſs and freſhneſs of my life and Spirit, and exalted that part in me which God hides the myſteries of his kingdome from. At my firſt acquaintance with this rejected Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that which was eternal of God in me opened, and I did immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately in my ſpirit own them as children of my Father, truly begotten of his life by his own ſpirit: but the wiſe reaſoning part preſently roſe up, contending againſt their uncouth way of appearance, and in that I did diſown them, and continued a ſtranger to them, and a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againſt them for above twelve months, and by weighing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering things in that part, was ſtill further and further off from diſcerning their leadings by the life and ſpirit of God into thoſe things. But at length it pleaſed the Lord to draw out his ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that part in me, turning the wiſdome and ſtrength thereof backward, and to open that eye in me again wherewith he had given me to ſee the things of his kingdome in ſome meaſure from a child; and then I ſaw and felt them grown in that life and ſpirit, which I through the treachery of the fleſhly-wiſe part had been eſtranged to, and had adulterated from. And now what bitter dayes of mourning and lamentation (even for ſome years ſince) I have had over this, the Lord alone fully knows. Oh I have known it to be a bitter thing to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this wiſdome in underſtanding of Scriptures, in remembring of experiences, and in many more inward wayes of workings, than many can bear to hear. The Lord hath judged me for that, and I have born the burthen and condemnation of that, which many at this day wear as their crown. And now what am I at length? A poor worm, whom can I warn effectually? whom can I help? whom can I ſtop from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the pit? But though I am nothing, I muſt ſpeak, for the Lord draweth and moveth me: and how unſerviceable ſoever my pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be, yet my bowels cannot but roul, both towards thoſe that are in miſery, and towards thoſe that are running into miſery. Read in the fear, and in the ſimplicity, what was ſo written; and the Lord open that eye in you which can ſee the way of life, and diſcover the paths of the myſtery of iniquity in its moſt hidden workings in the heart, that ye ſleep not the ſleep of eternal death, and ſo at laſt be awakned in the bowels of that wrath and fiery indignation, which that ſpirit which erreth from and tranſgreſſeth the life and light within, can neither bear nor eſcape.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115389:3"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION OF THE Grounds or Cauſes which are ſaid to induce the Court of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> to make that Order or Law of Baniſhment upon pain of death againſt the <hi>Quakers;</hi> As alſo of the Grounds and Conſiderations by them produced to manifeſt the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantableneſs and juſtneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat in <hi>New-England</hi> there hath been a Law made of Baniſhing the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) and of death in caſe of return, is well known in theſe parts; but what induced them hereunto, &amp; what juſt Grounds and Reaſons they had for it, many are not acquainted with, but are very much diſſatisfied concerning their proceedings therein, fearing that they have diſhonoured God, brought a reproach upon the Name of Chriſt and his Goſpel, exceeded the limits of their power, given an ill example of Perſecution, laid a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hardening their hearts againſt God, and of drawing his heavy wrath upon them, all which they cannot but be deeply guilty of, in caſe it ſhould be proved that they have been miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and that theſe People (upon a further ſearch) ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to them to be of God, as they already have to very many, who have been exceedingly prejudiced againſt them, till they came more meekly to hear and conſider their caſe. For there are many here in Old <hi>England,</hi> and in other parts, who once revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, reproached, and thought they could hardly do bad enough againſt them, who now (in the ſingleneſs of their hearts) can bleſs God for raiſing up ſuch a People, and that they themſelves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115389:4"/> were not cut off in their blind zeal againſt them, but in the rich mercy of God had a way made for the removing of their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices and hard thoughts, and for the opening of their eyes, whereby they came to ſee that theſe are indeed a pretious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, begotten, brought forth, and guided by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that it is his living truth, which they (in obedience to his living power) are drawn to bear witneſs to, and to hold forth unto the World. And one ſuch teſtimony for them, is of more weight and value in a true ballance, than thouſands of teſtimonies againſt them from ſuch who are prejudiced, and have not patience to conſider things in equity and uprightneſs of heart, and alſo whoſe intereſt lies another way.</p>
            <p>Now meeting of late with a paper beginning thus, <hi>At a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Ceurt held at</hi> Boſton, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 18th. October, 1659. (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by way of preface, there is firſt an account given of what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to make this law of baniſhment and death, and then grounds and conſiderations laid down to clear it to be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and juſt) it was upon my heart to conſider and examine theſe, to ſee whether they did ariſe from the ſeed of God, and from the true knowledge of the Scriptures by his ſpirit, and ſo were weighty to the conſcience which ſingly waits upon God for ſatisfaction about truth; or whether they did ariſe from the fleſhly part, and from fleſhly reaſonings upon Scriptures, and ſo were but chaffy, and not able to ſatisfie the weighty conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpirit, as in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>And this I was the more induced to do, becauſe I found bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els rowling in me towards them, and a ſenſe of what might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be their ſnare, which hath overtaken and intangled many, for many who have blamed others ſeverely, and really thought how well they themſelves would have amended things, if ever they came into place and power, yet have failed, and run into the very ſame errour, when they have come to the tryal. So theſe perſons, when they were formerly perſecuted in <hi>England,</hi> no doubt but thought and intended (if ever they came to be free from it) to lay a foundation againſt it: yet when they come to the point, and feel their condition changed, in ſo much as it was now in their hand to determine what was the way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Church-government, and order, there lay a great temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before them to ſet up what they judged to be right, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115389:4"/> to force all others to a conformity to it. Yea now was their great danger, and time to beware, leſt the ſame perſecuting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit did get up in them, which their being perſecuted was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means to keep down: And if ſo (if the ſame ſpirit which perſecuted them, got up in them) then they who were once perſecuted, could not poſſibly forbear perſecuting: for that ſpirit will perſecute, wherever it gets up. And having laid its foundation of perſecution under a plauſible cover, then by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees it more and more vails the eye, hardens the heart, and takes away the tenderneſs which was in the perſons before, while they themſelves were perſecuted. Now I cannot but pitty thoſe that fall into any ſnare of the enemy, eſpecially thoſe who are taken in ſo great a ſnare, and come to ſo great a loſs of their tenderneſs towards God, his truths and people, and run ſo great an hazard and danger of the loſs of their ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Grounds or Cauſes expreſſed of their making that Law of Baniſhment, are in ſubſtance theſe three.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The coming of the</hi> Quakers <hi>from forraign parts, and from other Colonies, at ſundry times, and in ſeveral companies and numbers, into the juriſdiction of the Maſſathuſets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This, of it ſelf is far from any warrant: for
<hi>the Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof:</hi> and though they laim a propriety in it, yet it is ſtill more the Lords than theirs; and he may ſend any of his ſervants into it at his pleaſure, upon what meſſage or ſervice it ſeemeth good unto him. So that the great queſtion to be determined here is this, <hi>Whether theſe perſons came from the Lord, in his will, and at his appointment: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they came of themſelves, and in their own wills?</hi> For if they came by commiſſion and appointment from the Lord of Heaven and Earth, their warrant was without doubt ſufficient: but if they came in their own wills, and upon their own deſigns, then they went out of the Lords counſel and protection, and muſt bear their own burthen. Now conſider, whether ye were tender in the due weighing of this, before your impriſoning, and dealing hardly with them: for if at their firſt coming ye impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned them, and engaged your ſelves againſt them, ye thereby made your ſelves unfit for an equal conſideration of the cauſe, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115389:5"/> and God might juſtly then leave your eyes to be cloſed, and your hearts hardned againſt his truths and people; for begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with them ſo harſhly and unrighteouſly, and not in his fear.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thoſe leſſer puniſhments of the houſe of correction, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment for a time having been inflicted on ſome of them, but not ſufficing to deter and keep them away.</hi> (Why do ye omit cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of ears? are ye aſhamed to mention that amongſt the reſt? indeed the remembrance of it ſtrikes upon the Spirits of people here, and perhaps in <hi>New-England</hi> alſo.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that are ſent by the Lord, and go in the guidance of his ſpirit, cannot be deterred from obedience to him in his ſervice and work, either by leſſer or greater puniſhments. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments deter the evil doer; but he that doth well, is not afraid of being puniſhed, but is taught, and made willing, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſuffer for righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. And ye will find your greater puniſhments as ineffectual to obtain your end, as your leſſer. For they whoſe lives (in the power of God) are ſacrificed up to the will of God, are no more afraid of death, then they are of whips, priſons, cruel uſage in priſons, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of ears. Surely it had been a ſweeter, a more chriſtian, and ſafer courſe, to have weighed the thing in Gods fear and dread, before ye had begun any of your puniſhments. But your own late relation confeſſeth, that ye began with them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reports from
<hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> (from good hands ye ſay, and ſo they of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> might have ſaid, if they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the letters from the High-Prieſt, or relations from zealous and devout Jews) and I have heard related from many hands (which having drunk in prejudices from reports, and begun with impriſoning of them, might eaſily follow) that they were never afforded a fair hearing, but at your Courts queſtions put to entrap them, and they not ſuffered to plead the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and innocency of their cauſe, but endeavours uſed to draw them to that (and a watching to catch that from them) which would bring them within the compaſs of ſome of your laws. Your conſciences know how true theſe things are, &amp; will one day give in a clear and true teſtimony, although ye ſhould be able to bribe them at preſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That their coming thither was upon no other grounds or <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115389:5"/> occaſion (for ought that could appear) then to ſcatter their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt opinions, and to draw others to their way, and ſo to make diſturbance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chriſt ſaith to his diſciples, <hi>ye are the ſalt of the earth, and the light of the world:</hi> and they are not to lie ſtill, and keep their light under a buſhel, but to lighten and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the world, as the Lord calleth and guideth them. And if the Lord doth ſee that <hi>New-England,</hi> notwithſtanding all its profeſſion and talk of the things of God, hath need of his ſalt to ſavour it with, and of his light to inlighten them, and ſo ſendeth his meſſengers and ſervants among them, they have no reaſon to be offended with the Lord for this, or with his people, or with the truths they bring. They have long had a form up, and it may have eaten out the power, and they may not be ſo ſavoury now in their eaſe and authority in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as they were under their troubles and perſecutions in Old <hi>England:</hi> and God may in kindneſſe to them ſend among them a fooliſh people to ſtir them up and provoke them to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie. Now the coming thus is not to
<hi>ſcatter corrupt opinions;</hi> but by the power of truth to ſcatter that, which ſcatters from the Lord; nor is it to draw to their way, but to the Lord, to Chriſt his living way, which they are exhorted to try, and feel, and certainly to know, before they receive: nor doth it make any
<hi>diſturbance</hi> but onely to that which is at eaſe in the fleſh, and fleſhly forms of worſhip. And Iſrael of old was often thus diſturbed by the Prophets of God, (though they ſtill could not bear it, but were enemies to the Prophets for it) notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had received their way of worſhip certainly from Gods hand: how much more may the Lord take liberty by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and meſſengers to diſturb theſe, who never ſo received it, but have formed up a way out of the Scriptures, whereof many that are truly conſcientious doubt whether it be the way or no, even as they themſelves doubt and are ready to contend againſt the waies that others have formed?</p>
            <p>Now thoſe that pick a quarrel with truth, and ſeek matter againſt it to perſecute it, do not call it truth, but errour, corrupt opinions, the way of a Sect, the making of diſturbance, or ſuch like. And perſecutors for the moſt part do not only ſay this, but bring forth their ſtrong arguments, inſomuch as the perſecutors <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115389:6"/> is commonly juſt in his own eyes, and the perſecuted is blamed as the evill doer, and cauſe of his own ſufferings. Were the Biſhops without their plea? nay did not he that was called Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> (in his book) ſeem to carry the cauſe clear againſt the <hi>Non-conformiſts?</hi> And why the Biſhops might not eſtabliſh their way by authority, or the Presbyters their way, as well as theſe accounted <hi>Independants</hi> their way (not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſſenters, or tender-conſcienced) I confeſſe I ſee not; but that they have juſtified the Biſhops by their practiſing the ſame thing, and ſo unjuſtly condemned them in words.</p>
            <p>But how can ye ſay, <hi>for ought that could appear?</hi> when ye were ſo unfit (through receiving of prejudices and reports, and beginning ſo roughly with them) to conſider what might be made appear, &amp; alſo ſo far from giving way to them to make what they could appear, as is before expreſſed? And doth not this alſo imply that there may be a juſt, righteous, and warrantable cauſe of their coming, in relation to God and his ſervice, though it doth not yet appear to you; and in a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and cooler temper, when another eye is opened in you, ye may ſee and acknowledge that cauſe, who are the Lords ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whether they come in his name or no; whether they are his truths or no, which they bring with them, theſe are things God opens to the humble, to the meek, to ſuch as fear before him and wait for his counſel therein: but thoſe that can determine things by intelligence before hand from other parts, and impriſon perſons ſo ſoon as they come, and ſo proceed on with a ſtiff reſolution againſt them, how are theſe in any capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to ſeek or receive counſel from God in a caſe of ſo great concernment? So that at laſt even when they have drunk their blood, they muſt be forced to ſay, <hi>for ought that could appear,</hi> this was their only end, work, and intent; but whether it was ſo or no, they do not certainly know.</p>
            <p>Thus far is in anſwer to the account they give, by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, to what led them to the making of this law of baniſhment and death. Now the grounds and conſiderations themſelves, which they hold forth to clear this to be warrantable and juſt, follow to be ſcanned, which are in number ſix.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The doctrine of this Sect of people</hi> (ſay they)
<hi>is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to fundamental truths of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115389:6"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the making of this argument forcible, two things are neceſſary; if either of which fails, it fals to the ground.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is neceſſary to make manifeſt, that perſons for holding or propagating doctrines contrary to fundamental truths of religion, are by Chriſts inſtitution puniſhable with diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, baniſhment, or death. For Chriſt is the head, King, and Law-giver to his Church: it is he that is the foundation of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the giver forth of fundamental truths of religion: and he is the proper Judge of what puniſhent is fit for ſuch, as either will not receive his fundamental truths of Religion, or afterwards ſtart back from them, and broach doctrines contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereto. Now it is required, in his name and authority, of ſuch Powers as will take upon them to inflict theſe kinds of puniſhments, upon ſuch kind of offenders, Chriſts inſtitution for this thing. Chriſt was as faithful in his houſe as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and if ſuch a courſe had been neceſſary for the preſervation of his Church, ſurely he would not have with-held it. But Chriſt overcomes the Devils kingdom by his ſpirit: by that he wins ſouls, and gathers into, and builds up his Church, and by that he is able to defend them. By his ſpirit he preacheth the truth and ſoweth the ſeed of the kingdome, and by his ſpirit he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds and maintains it. This is his way of overcoming all the miſts of darkneſſe, and falſe doctrines, and not a Magiſtrates ſword. <hi>The weapons of our warfare</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds,</hi> 2, Cor. 10.4. Are there ſtrong holds of darkneſs? are there falſe doctrines broached againſt the truths of Chriſt? Who are the warriers againſt theſe? Are they the civil ſtate, the Magiſtrate, the earthly powers; or are they the Miniſters and ſervants of Chriſt? And what are the weapons that are mighty to overthrow theſe? Are they Stocks, Whips, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, cutting off of ears, baniſhment, death? or are they of a ſpiritual nature? The ſpiritual weapons are ſanctified by God to this end, and are mighty through him, able to effect it throughly; whereas the carnal weapons are weak and unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and can reach only the carnal part, but the ſtrong hold remains untouched by theſe. And it is only the carnal part, which deſires to have the uſe of ſuch carnal weapons in the Church: the ſpiritual man would conquer by his own weapon, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115389:7"/> or not at all, Chriſt came not to deſtroy mens lives, nor never gave order to have men killed about his truths. If his People be diſobedient, and broach doctrines never ſo contrary and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to his kingdom, he hath a ſpiritual way of fighting with them now, and hath appointed his ſervants to have his mighty ſpiritual weapons in a readineſſe, <hi>for the revenging every diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.6, and he hath likewiſe a time of dealing with them hereafter; but he hath no where appointed that his ſubjects (if they could get the command of the ſword in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Country) ſhould kill ſuch. Abundance of blood hath been ſhed upon this pretence, which the Lord will make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition for: it would at length be ſeriouſly inquired into, what truth there is in this bloody doctrine? for under this cover all the perſecutions and ſheddings of the Saints blood ſhelter themſelves. O conſider at length, how cruel and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy men have made the Goſpel of peace by this principle: and what an advantage it gives to the carnal part in thoſe that are perſecuted, if once they can get the command of the outward ſword, to forget their own ſufferings, and ſuddainly turn perſecutors of ſuch as differ from them, though upon as weighty grounds (if not more weighty) than they differed from others upon. But this they that are uppermoſt will not yield to, that the grounds of ſuch as differ from them are ſufficient; even as thoſe that they differed from would not yield that their grounds were ſufficient. Thus ſtill they whoſe arguments go forth under the ſhelter, or by the command of the preſent authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they are looked upon as moſt weighty, and the others cauſe is trampled upon, though never ſo juſt, innocent, upright and weighty in it ſelf; and the meek of the earth, the humble-hearted, the tender-conſcienced towards God they are ſtill made the offenders and ſufferers: and their enemies are ſtill made their Judges. I do think theſe of <hi>New-England</hi> would have once thought it hard meaſure, that the Conformiſts whom they differed from, ſhould have been the Judges whether their grounds were ſufficient or no, and yet they (ever ſince they have had the power in their hands) have taken upon them to be the judges of the ſufficiency of the grounds of ſuch as differ from them, and have as freely condemned all that differed from them, and been as ſore a curb upon the tender conſcience, as <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115389:7"/> ever the Biſhops were. So that it is plain, that which they ſought was their own liberty (they did not like to be oppreſſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled contrary to their judgments) but not the liberty of the tender conſcience towards God, but rather the yoaking &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling of it to their judgments, and arguments, and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Scripture; which he that differs from, muſt be an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender with them, even as they were once accounted offenders for differing from the Conformiſts, and ſo are all become tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of the Law of God in doing that to others, which they would not that others ſhould do to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is requiſite alſo to make manifeſt, that the Doctrine of this ſort of people is deſtructive to the fundamental truths of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For if it be not ſo, then they are injured and miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; and both their baniſhment, and death, and all other puniſhments inflicted upon them on this account, will prove to have been unjuſt.</p>
            <p>There are four inſtances given, or four particular fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals mentioned, to which their Doctrines are ſaid to be deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive. Firſt,
<hi>the ſacred Trinity,</hi> Secondly, <hi>the perſon of Chriſt,</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the holy Scriptures as a perfect rule of faith and life,</hi> Fourthly, <hi>the doctrine of perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the making the thing clear and manifeſt to every ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber mind, it is requiſite firſt to conſider what the
<hi>Quakers</hi> hold in theſe ſeveral particulars, and then whether that which they hold in theſe reſpects, be contrary to the truth of theſe things, as they are plainly related in the Scriptures: for if that which they hold be according to the naked voyce and proper intent of the Scriptures, then they are not to be blamed, but the blame will light on their accuſers, who might eaſily be found guilty of injuring both them and the Scriptures, both in theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, were they not Judges.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning <hi>the ſacred Trinity.</hi> They generally both in their ſpeakings, and in their writings, ſet their ſeal to the truth of that Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. That <hi>there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Spirit.</hi> That theſe three are diſtinct, as three ſeveral beings or perſons, this they read not, but in the ſame place they read, that they <hi>are one.</hi> And thus they believe, their being to be one, their life one, their light one, their wiſdome one, their power one: and he <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115389:8"/> that knoweth and ſeeth any one of them, knoweth and ſeeth them all, according to that ſaying of Chriſts to <hi>Philip, He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father, John</hi> 14.9. Three there are and yet one, thus they have read in the Scripture, and this they teſtifie they have had truly opened to them, by that very Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which gave forth the Scriptures, in ſo much as they certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know it to be true, and own the thing from their very hearts. But as for this title of <hi>Sacred Trinity,</hi> they find it not in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and they look upon Scripture-words as fitteſt to expreſs Scripture-things by. And ſurely if a man mean the ſame thing as the Scripture means, the ſame words will ſuffice to expreſs it: but the Papiſts and School-men having miſſed of the thing which the Scripture drives at, and apprehended ſomewhat elſe in the wiſe imagining part, have brought forth many phraſes of their own invention to expreſs their apprehenſions by, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs we have no unity with, but are content with feeling the thing which the Scripture ſpeaks of, and with the words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Scriptures expreſs it. Now whereas they call this a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, we do not find it ſo called in Scripture, nor do we find the Diſciples themſelves underſtanding therein, but knew not the Father, <hi>John</hi> 14.8, 9. and Chriſt going about to inform them, does not tell them of another diſtinct being, or perſon: but <hi>haſt thou not ſeen me? and believeſt thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me?</hi> verſ. 10. And ſo the believers at <hi>Epheſus</hi> had not ſo much as heard that there was an holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. So that if ye will make this a fundamental truth, yet it is ſuch a fundamental, as true faith did ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, both in believers afore Chriſts death, and in believers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This is the great fundamental, <hi>that God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> 1
<hi>John.</hi> 1.5. and the great work of the Miniſtry is to ſhew men where this light is, and to turn men from the darkneſs, wherein is the power of Satan, unto this light: wherein is the power of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. And he that comes into this light, and into this power, is owned in the light and in the power, wherein is the life of all the Saints, and the true fellowſhip both with the Father &amp; the Son, &amp; one with another, 1 <hi>John</hi>
1.3. and 7. And the true trial of Spirits, is not by an aſſent to Doctrines (which the hypocrite may aſſent <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115389:8"/> to on the one hand, and the true believer may ſtartle at on the other hand) but by feeling of them in the inward vertue of the light, in the Spirit, and in the power. This was the Apoſtles way of trial, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.19, 20. <hi>I will know, not the ſpeech of them which are puffed up, but the power; for the kingdome of God is not in word, but in power.</hi> A man may ſpeak high words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the kingdome, and get all the Doctrines about it, and yet be a ſtranger to it, and quite ignorant of the power: and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother may want divers Doctrines concerning it, (perhaps ſome of thoſe which men call fundamentals) and yet be a Citizen of it, and in the power. But now under the Antichriſtian Apoſtacy, men wanting the feeling of the life and power, wherein the true judgment is, they own or diſown one another upon an aſſent or diſſent to ſuch and ſuch Doctrines, and ſo fall into this great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, of owning many whom Chriſt diſowns, and of diſowning many whom Chriſt owns: and if they find perſons not aſſenting to, or diſſenting from any of thoſe things, which they call fundamentals, then they think they may lawfully excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and perſecute them. So by this miſtake, they cut off that which is green, they perſecute that wherein is the living ſap, and cheriſh the dry and withered. That which is moſt tender towards God, and moſt growing in the inward ſenſibleneſs (which cauſeth it to ſtartle at that, which others can eaſily ſwallow) lies moſt open to ſuffering by this kind of trial.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning <hi>the Perſon of Chriſt.</hi> They believe that Chriſt is the eternal light, life, wiſdome and power of God, which was manifeſted in that body of fleſh, which he took of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: that he is the King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his people, and ſaveth them from their ſins by laying down his life for them, and imputing his righteouſneſs to them, yet not without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing and bringing forth the ſame righteouſneſs in them, which he wrought for them. And by experience they know, that there is no being ſaved by a belief of his death for them, and of his reſurrection, aſcention, interceſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without being brought unto a true fellowſhip with him in his death, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling his immortal ſeed of life raiſed and living in them. And ſo they diſown that faith in Chriſts death, which is only recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and entertained from the relation of the letter of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſtands not in the living power, and ſenſible experience of the begotten of God in the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115389:9"/>Now they diſtinguiſh, according to the Scriptures, between that which is called the Chriſt, and the bodily garment which he took. The one was fleſh, the other Spirit. <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Spirit quickneth, and he that eateth me, ſhall live by me, even as I live by the Father, John</hi> 6.57. and 63. This is the Manna it ſelf, the true treaſure, the other but the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible or earthen veſſel which held it. The body of fleſh was but the vail,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. The eternal life was the ſubſtance vailed. The one he did partake of, as the reſt of the Children did, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he which did partake thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. The one was the body which was prepared for the life, for it to appear in and be made manifeſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5. The other was the life or light it ſelf, for whom the body was prepared, who took it up, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it to do the will, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.7, 8. and was made manifeſt to thoſe eyes which were able to ſee through the vail wherewith it was covered, <hi>John</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p>Now is not this ſound, according to the Scriptures? and is it not a good way to know this, by unity with it; by feeling a meaſure of the ſame life made manifeſt in our mortal fleſh? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. This we confeſs is our way of underſtanding theſe things, and likewiſe of underſtanding the Scriptures which ſpeak of theſe things. And we have found it a far ſurer kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, namely, to underſtand the Scriptures, by experience of that whereof the Scripture ſpeaks, than to gueſs at the things the Scripture ſpeak of, by conſidering and ſcanning in the earthly part, what the Scriptures ſpeak of them. Such a kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as this, a wiſe man may attain to a great meaſure of, but the other is peculiar to him who is begotten of God, whoſe knowledge is true and certain, though it ſeem never ſo different from his who hath attained what he hath by the ſearch of his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning <hi>the holy Scriptures being a perfect rule of faith and life.</hi> The new covenant is the covenant of the Goſpel, which is a living covenant, a ſpiritual covenant, an inward co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the law or rule of it cannot be written outwardly. Read the tenour of the new covenant,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts.</hi> If God himſelf ſhould take the ſame laws, and write them outwardly; yet, ſo written, they are not the new covenant: at moſt they <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115389:9"/> would be but an outward draught of laws written in the new covenant. And mark, this is one difference given between the new covenant and the old, the laws of the one were written outwardly in tables of ſtone, the laws of the other were to be written in the heart. That is the book wherein the laws of the new covenant were promiſed to be written, and there they are to be read. So that he that will read and obey the Laws of the covenant of life, muſt look for them in that book, wherein God hath promiſed to write them: for though in other books he may read ſome outward deſcriptions of the thing, yet here alone can he read the thing it ſelf. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is
<hi>the way, the truth, and the life.</hi> What is a Chriſtians rule? is not the way of God his rule? is not Gods truth his rule? and is not the truth in Jeſus where it is taught and to be heard, and to be received even as it is in Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.21? Is not he the King, the Prieſt, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the Sacrifice, the Altar, the way to God, the truth of God, the life it ſelf, the living path out of Death, yea all in all to the believer, whoſe eye is opened to behold him? The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teſtifie of Chriſt, but they are not Chriſt: they alſo teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie of truth, and are a true teſtimony, but the truth it ſelf is in Jeſus, who by his living ſpirit writes it in the heart which he hath made living. And ſo a Chriſtians life is in the Spirit: <hi>if we live in the Spirit, let us alſo walk in the Spirit. Gal.</hi> 5.25. The whole life and courſe of a Chriſtian is in the volumn of that book, as the Lord opens the leaves of it in him. <hi>The gift of God, the meaſure of faith</hi> given him by God, that's his rule; that's his rule of knowledge, of propheſying, of obedience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. and 12.6. if he keep there, if he walk according to the proportion of it, he errs not: but out of the faith, in the the error, in all he knows, in all he believes, in all he does. <hi>The new Creature,</hi> that which God hath new created in the heart, in which life breaths, and nothing but life breaths which is taught by God, and true to God from its very infancy, that's his rule whereby he is to walk, the Apoſtle expreſly calls it ſo,
<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15, 16. That which is begotten by God is a Son: and the Son, as he is begotten by the breath of the Spirit, ſo he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and led by the ſame breath; and ſuch as are ſo led are Sons and none elſe: for it is not reading of Scriptures, and gathering rules out thence, that makes a Son, but the receiving of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115389:10"/> and the being led by the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14, 15. And being the whole worſhip of the Goſpel is in the Spirit, there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of receiving that in the firſt place; and then in it the ſoul learns to know and wait for its breathings and movings, and follows on towards the Lord in them. The Spirit cannot be with-held from breathing on that which he hath begotten, and that breath is a guide, a rule, a way, to that which it breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon. Now this is moſt manifeſt even from the Scriptures themſelves, they expreſly calling Chriſt the way, the truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the new creature, the rule, the faith, grace, or gift given to be the rule, teſtifying the heart to be that which God hath choſen to write his laws in: but where do they call themſelves a perfect rule of faith and obedience? <hi>They are they,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>which teſtifie of me, and ye will not come to me, that ye might have life.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 5.39, 40. Life cannot be received from the Scriptures, but only from Chriſt the fountain thereof: no more can the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures give the rule, but point to the fountain of the ſame life, where alone the rule of life, as the life it ſelf can be received. The Scriptures cannot ingraft into Chriſt, nor give a living rule to him that is ingrafted: but he that hath heard the Teſtimony of the Scriptures concerning Chriſt, and hath come to him, muſt abide in him, and wait on him for the writing of the law of the Spirit of life in his heart, and this will be his rule from the law of ſin and death, even unto the land of life. Now if men have miſtaken in the night of darkneſs, and put the Scriptures out of their place (even into the place of the Spirit) and ſo have become Miniſters, not of the Spirit, but of the letter, whereas the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were made <hi>able Miniſters of the new Teſtament, not of the letter but of the Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. Let them not be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the Spirit of God for teaching us otherwiſe, nor at us for learning as the Spirit of God hath taught us, the Scriptures alſo teſtifying that this is the rule, but no where ſetting up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the rule. And it is the ſame Spirit, which would now fix men in the Scriptures, to keep men from Chriſt the living rule and only way to life eternal, as formerly kept men by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions from the Scriptures, though it is hard for them who are intangled in this deceit, to ſee it.</p>
            <p>Now for the proof of theſe things thus barely here charged, the reader is referred to Mr. <hi>Norton's</hi> (as they ſtile him) Tractate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115389:10"/> againſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi> Concerning the validity whereof, I refer the Reader to <hi>Francis Howgils</hi> Anſwer thereto, wiſhing him to read both in the fear and dread of the Almighty, waiting for his counſel to guide him in the true diſcerning, which of them ſavours of mans wiſdome, and which of them writes from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the truth it ſelf. In which Anſwer of his he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites ſuch errors of that
<hi>Norton,</hi> as would make a great ſound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> if any ſuch could juſtly be charged upon them. I ſhall mention only two or three of them, <hi>viz:</hi> That God is a diſtinct Subſiſtence from the Son and Spirit; and That the Son is a diſtinct Subſiſtence from the Father and the Spirit: and becauſe it is ſaid, the <hi>Father ſhall give you another Comforter,</hi> this <hi>another</hi> he ſaith is intelligible of the Eſſence. (Are there then three diſtinct infinite Eſſences or Beings?) <hi>That the Spirit of God without the Letter is no Spirit.</hi> (He was before the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he was never limited to the Letter, he will be after the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and he is what he is without the Letter.) <hi>That Chriſts words</hi> John 17.21. <hi>give an uncertain ſound,</hi> (where have any of the <hi>Quakers</hi> caſt ſuch a blemiſh upon any portion of Scripture?) Surely this man had more need to ſeek to have his own veſſel cleanſed, than to accuſe others of Errors or Blaſphemy. And if he have no other way to overthrow them, than by maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch kind of things as theſe againſt them, he will never get victory over them any other wayes than by the outward ſword: but by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of his teſtimony, and not loving their lives unto the death, they will eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all ſuch kind of Champions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt inſtance which they give of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiveneſs of their Doctrine to the fundamental Truths of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is, <hi>That opinion of theirs of being perfectly pure and without ſin, which</hi> (ſay they) <hi>tends to overthrow the whole Goſpel, and the very vitals of Chriſtianity: for they that have no ſin, have no need of Chriſt, or of his ſatisfaction, or blood to cleanſe them, nor of Faith, Repentance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the Lord God is able perfectly to redeem from ſin in this life; that he can caſt out the ſtrong man, cleanſe the houſe, and make it fit for himſelf to dwell in; that he can fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh tranſgreſſion and ſin in the heart, and bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs; that he can tread down Satan under the feet of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115389:11"/> his Saints, and make them more than Conquerors over him; this they confeſs they ſteadily believe. But that every one that is turned to the light of the Spirit of Chriſt in his heart, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently advanced to this ſtate, they never held forth: but that the way is long, the travail hard, the enemies and difficulties ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that there is need of much Faith, hope, patience, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, watchfulneſs againſt temptations,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> before the life in them arive at ſuch a pitch. Yet for all this, ſaith Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>Be ye perfect,</hi> directing them to aim at ſuch a thing, and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let us go on unto perfection,</hi> and Chriſt gave a Miniſtry <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints:</hi> and they do not doubt but that he that begins the work, can perfect it even in this life, and ſo deliver them out of the hands of ſin, Satan, and all their ſpiritual enemies, as that they may ſerve God without fear of them any more, in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him all the dayes of their lives.</p>
            <p>Now how is this Doctrine, or how is this People becauſe of their believing and holding forth this Doctrine, guilty of all this great and heavy charge that is laid upon them here, as that <hi>they have no need of Chriſt, his ſatisfaction, his blood, nor of faith, repentance, growing in grace, Gods Word and Ordinances, nor of watchfulneſs and prayer?</hi> &amp;c. Let us conſider the thing a litttle further.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Doctrine of Perfection, if it ſhould be granted to deny all this, yet cannot be ſuppoſed to deny the need thereof, until the ſtate of Perfection be attained. Nay, they that truly believe that ſuch a ſtate is attainable, cannot deny the uſe of thoſe things which are proper to lead to that ſtate, but will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly apply themſelves thereto, and preſs all others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, who deſire to attain that ſtate. And they that have either heard them ſpeak, or read their Writings with any equality of mind, may abundantly teſtifie for them againſt the unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and injury of this charge. Their life lies in Chriſt, their peace in his <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for them, and in a ſenſible feeling of his <hi>blood</hi> ſprinkled in their conſciences to cleanſe them from ſin; and by that <hi>faith</hi> which is Gods gift, they feel, and wait further to feel the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to them for juſtification. And as for being <hi>perfectly juſt in themſelves,</hi> it is a very unrighteous charge upon them: for their juſtice and righteouſneſs is in Chriſt <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115389:11"/> for ever, and not of themſelves; but in the denyal and crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſelf are they made partakers of it, which is beſtowed by the free grace, mercy, and power of him who hath mercy on them, and not by any willing or running of theirs. And as for
<hi>Repentance,</hi> they feel the need of it, and find a godly ſorrow wrought in them, and a bitter mourning over him whom they once pierced, and ſtill pierce, ſo far as they hearken to the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and follow the motions and luſts of the tranſgreſſing nature. And they do both
<hi>watch</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> againſt ſin, and feel what a bitter thing it is to have the watch ſo ſlackened, whereby the temptation prevails, which would lead to ſin. And as for <hi>purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves dayly,</hi> and <hi>putting off the old man,</hi> and <hi>putting on the new;</hi> it is that which their hearts delight to be continually exerciſed about: and all this with an hope that it may be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the veſſel may be made holy to the Lord, a fit ſpiritual Temple for him to dwell in, that he may diſplay his life, glory, power, and pure preſence in them. But if the belief that this may be attained, in the way wherein God leadeth them towards it, and an hope to attain it, with an acknowledgment of it ſo far as it is attained; I ſay, if this make them guilty of ſo great a charge, then they are indeed guilty: for they cannot but believe it, wait for it, hope for it, and acknowledge it, ſo far as they feel it wrought in them. But how can this poſſibly make them guilty of denying theſe things, ſeeing the exerciſe of theſe things not only ſtandeth with, but is increaſed by ſuch a belief and hope?</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſtate of Perfection it ſelf doth not exclude theſe things, in ſuch a way as this charge ſeems to intimate. For in the ſtate of perfection, the blood is not laid aſide as uſeleſs, but remains to keep pure for ever. It is <hi>the blood of the everlaſting Covenant,</hi> (Heb. 13.20.) both the Covenant and the Blood laſt for ever, and are uſeful even to them that are perfect. And there is need and uſe of the Faith in the Blood, to believe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. As the Covenant it ſelf laſts; ſo that which lets in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and keeps in the Covenant laſts alſo. That which unites, and ties the ſoul to Chriſt the life, abides in the ſoul for ever, even as the union it ſelf abides. And there is a growing in the life, even where the heart is purified from ſin, even as Chriſt did grow and wax ſtrong in ſpirit: for a ſtate of perfection doth not exclude degrees. And ſo there is alſo need of watching againſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115389:12"/> in a perfect ſtate: for <hi>Adam</hi> was perfect, and yet he need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a watch: and Chriſt was perfectly pure and without ſin, and yet he did both watch and pray. So that if any were brought to the ſtate of a perfect man, even unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, which the Miniſtry was given to bring all the Saints unto,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. if any were taught and enabled ſo to walke in the light, as to be cleanſed by the blood from all ſin, and to have ſuch fellowſhip with the Father, and the Son, as might make their joy full, 1
<hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 4, 7. If any were brought to that ſtate of glory, as to be chaſt Virgins, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. without ſpot or wrinkle of the fleſh, but holy and without blemiſh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. If any ſhould be made perfect in every good work to do his will, which was a thing the Apoſtle prayed for, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.21. If any ſhould have ſo put off the old man, and have put on the wedding garment, as to be made ready and fit to be marryed to the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. Yet this would not exclude faith in the blood, or prayer, or watchfulneſs to keep the garment pure, &amp;c. nor growth in the life. And this we are not aſhamed to profeſs, that we are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing after, and ſome have already attained very far, even to be made perfect as pertaining to the conſcience, being ſo ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſt the power of God, ſo planted into the likeneſs of his death and reſurrection, ſo encompaſſed with the walls and bulwarks of ſalvation, as that they feel no condemnation for ſin, but a continual juſtification of the life, being taught, led, and inabled to walk, not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>From what they bave ſaid concerning this opinion of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as they call it) they draw an argument againſt their other doctrines, in theſe words. <hi>Such fundamentals of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are overthrown by this one opinion of theirs, and how more by all their other doctrines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I ſhall ſay this, if their grounds and proofs againſt any other doctrines of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> be no more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and demonſtrative, then thoſe they have here brought forth againſt the doctrine of perfection, they may ſpare entertaining prejudices againſt them and condemning them, and in the firſt place weigh them in a more equall ballance than they have done this. And I dare appeal to any naked unbyaſſed ſpirit, who ſhall <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115389:12"/> fairly conſider what is above written, whether the doctrine of perfection be ſuch an hideous error as they have repreſented it? Nay whether it be not a precious truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt, and a great incouragement to him who ſhall follow the command of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>be ye perfect,</hi> to believe that, (in the way of faith and obedience) he may be wrought up to ſuch an eſtate by the free grace, mercy, love and power of God? Yea let me add this word more, he that feeleth the everlaſting arme working one ſin out of his heart, cannot but believe that the ſame arme can work out all, and pluck up every plant which the heavenly father hath not planted; which hope and beliefe cauſeth him, with joy to follow this arme through the regeneration. But if I did believe there were no perfecting the worke of redemption in this life, but I muſt ſtill in part be a ſlave to Satan, ſtill crying out of the body of ſin and death, and never have my heart purified for the holy one to inhabit in, but remaine in part unconverted, unchanged, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerated, unſanctified; Oh how heavily ſhould I go on, I am ſure it would be as a weight upon my ſpirit in reſiſting of ſin and Satan. This is not the glad tidings of the everlaſting Goſpel, but ſad news from the borders of death, whith would keep the creature not only in the bonds of death but without hope of deliverance in this life, and refer the hope to that day wherein there is no more working out of redemption, but the eternall judgement of the tree as it fals.</p>
            <p>Now, having after this manner proved that the doctrines of the
<hi>Quakers</hi> are deſtructive to the fundamental truths of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they lay down their argument whereupon they conclude that it is lawful for them, nay their duty to put them to death, in theſe words. <hi>Now the commandement of God is plain, that he that preſumes to ſpeak lies in the name of the Lord, and turns people out of the way which the Lord hath commanded to walk in, ſuch an one muſt not live but be put to death,</hi> Zech. 13.3. Deut. 13.6.
<hi>and</hi> 18.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By what hath been ſaid againſt them, it is not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that they have ſpoken lies in the name of the Lord. Nay, if they themſelves who thus charge them, could but ſoberly, and mildly, with a Chriſtian ſpirit, weigh the thing, would it not rather appear, that they in thus falſly charging them, and <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115389:13"/> managing ſuch untrue and unrighteous arguments againſt them have ſpoken lies both concerning them, and againſt the Lord and his truth? And as for turning men out of the way, that cannot be juſtly charged on them, who turn men to Chriſt the living way, and deliver the ſame meſſage the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did, <hi>that God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> &amp; who point them to that place, where God hath ſaid, this light is to be found, which is the heart, where God writes the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and the Laws thereof. <hi>Heb.</hi>
8. where the word of faith is nigh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. ſurely they that direct hither, do not turne men out of the way. But they that point men to gueſs at the meanings of Scriptures, and to gather knowledge, and form rules to themſelves out of it by their own natural wit and underſtanding, which can never reach the myſteries of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and which God hides the true knowledge of the Scriptures from, theſe are thoſe that turn men out of the way. For they that rightly underſtand the Scriptures, muſt firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a meaſure of the ſpirit to underſtand it with; even as they that wrote any part thereof, did firſt receive a meaſure of the ſpirit to write it by.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not manifeſt by theſe places quoted, that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of <hi>New-England</hi> have received authority from the Lord to put the <hi>Quakers</hi> to death, if their doctrines were ſuch as they accuſe them to be. That of <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. is a manifeſt caſe concerning one that ſhould tempt to the following of other Gods, of the Gods of the people round about, nigh or far off, in ſuch a caſe the offender was to be ſtoned to death, <hi>v.</hi> 10. but is this appliable to caſes of doctrine? That of <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.20. gives a clear note how the Prophet may be known that ſpeaks a lie in the name of the Lord, and what kind of lie it is, for which he is to be put to death, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. but it doth not ſay that every man in the common-wealth of Iſrael, that holdeth any doctrine contrary to what ſome of them might call the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental doctrines of the Law, ſhould be put to death. That of <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.3. is a propheſy, not a command, and is not to be underſtood in mans wiſdome, nor to be fulfilled in mans will. It were better to wait for the true openings of propheſies in the ſpirit, than to let the carnal part looſe to gather ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of them for the ſatisfying of the fleſh, and making its
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115389:13"/> thirſt after the blood of Gods lambs appear more plauſible. I would but put this queſtion to your conſciences in the ſight of God, whether in a conſcientious ſubmiſſion to the will of God in this ſcripture, ye put them to death, or whether from this ſcripture ye ſeek a ſhelter and cover for the thing, having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy done it, or fully purpoſed to do it?</p>
            <p>So that the caſe is not here the ſame with any of the caſes mentioned in thoſe ſcriptures: for if ſome of their doctrines were lies (which ye have been very far from proving) yet it was not for ſuch kind of lies that death was appointed in the common-wealth of Iſrael. And yet there is a large difference between what was lawful to be done in the kingdom or common-wealth of Iſrael, and what is now lawful to be done. The kingdome or common-wealth of Iſrael was a ſtate outwardly repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, of what was inwardly to be done in the ſtate of the Goſpel by Chriſt the King thereof. He is the King and Law-giver to his people, and he is their Judge concerning their receiving or rejecting them, concerning their obeying or diſobeying them, concerning their holding the faith, or their letting go the faith, and maintaining things contrary thereto. And he doth judge his people here in this life, ſo far as he thinks fit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.30, 31. reſerving alſo what he thinks fit for another time of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. And who is he that ſhall take his office out of his hand, and judge one of his ſervants in the things of his kingdome?
<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. Is not this an intruding into Chriſts Kingly office? He gave authority to, &amp; command for the doing of ſuch things outwardly before his coming, as might repreſent what he would do inwardly after his coming: but where hath he given authority ſince his coming to do ſuch things any more? Doth not the typical King, with his typical government ceaſe, after that king with his government, which it figured out, is come?</p>
            <p>O Governours of <hi>New-England,</hi> to take away the life of a man is a weighty thing, and the Lord will not hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, who either doth it in a violent manner, or who maketh an unjuſt law to do it by. But how pretious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his ſaints! O how will ye be able to bear the weight of their blood, when the Lord maketh inquiſition for it? ye had need have a very clear warrant in this caſe, O how will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115389:14"/> ye anſwer this thing at the judgement ſeat of Chriſt! Alas, ſuch arguments as theſe will ſtand you in little ſtead? But ye have done it and now muſt maintain it: and it is exceeding hard for you (being thus deeply ingaged in the ſight of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) to come to a ſober and ſerious conſideration of the ſtate of the caſe, as it ſtands before the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ground or conſideration which they hold forth to clear their Law of baniſhment and death againſt the
<hi>Quakers,</hi> to be warrantable and juſt is this. <hi>Becauſe they are far from giving that honor and reverence to Magiſtrates which the Lord requireth, and good men have given to them: but on the contrary ſhew contempt againſt them in their very outward geſture and behaviours, and ſome of them at leaſt ſpare not to belch railing and curſing ſpeeches, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we do not give that honour and reverence to Magiſtrates which the Lord requireth, deſerves a weighty proof. For what we do, or forbear in this kind, we do as in the ſight of the Lord, as perſons who are not only liable to ſuffer from men, but alſo to give an account to him at the laſt day. Now towards Magiſtrates our carriage is thus, as in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We obſerve their commands in all things that are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God. We ſubmit our ſelves to the government that is ſupream, and to the Governours under the ſupream, for the Lords ſake, who in their ſeveral places ought to be for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well, according to, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. This is Gods ordinance, and here Magiſtracy is in its right place, namely in puniſhing the evil doer for his evil deeds, but not make a man an offender for a word, or for a geſture, which is neither good nor evil in it ſelf, but as it is done. He that pulleth off his hat or boweth in flattery, or to pleaſe man, in him it is evil: he that forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to do it in obedience to God, and in the fear of his name, in him it is good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When any Magiſtrates puniſh us for wel-doing, for our obedience to the Lords ſpirit, though we know God never gave power to any Magiſtracy to puniſh therefore, yet we patiently ſuffer under them, referring our cauſe to him that judgeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and waiting on him for ſtrength to carry us through our ſufferings for his names ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115389:14"/>3. When we appear before them, we appear as in the Lords preſence, deſiring his guidance, that we may give due honour and reſpect to all that is of him in them, and may be kept from honouring or pleaſing that which is not of him, and which he would not have us honour. This is the temper of our Spirits, and accordingly is our carriage as in the ſight of the Lord, what ever men deem of us.</p>
            <p>But the great matter is, becauſe we do not pull off our hats, and bow to them, or that we uſe plain language to them, (as thou and thee to a particular perſon) which ſome of them will needs interpret to be contempt, though others of them, who are more ſober and conſiderate, can clearly diſcern that it is not at all in contempt either to their authority, or their perſons, but in meer ſingle-hearted obedience to God. Now to drive this a little towards a fair trial, conſider in meekneſs and in Gods fear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What kind of honour this is which is thus much ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is it the honour which is from above, or the honour which is from below? What part ſprings it from in man? from the new-birth, or from the earthly nature? &amp; what doth it pleaſe in man? doth it pleaſe that which is begotten of God? doth it pleaſe the meekneſs, the humility, the lowlineſs, the new nature? or doth it pleaſe &amp; help to keep up the old nature, the lofty ſpirit, even that part which is prone in every man to be exalted out of the fear of God? For this I may freely ſay, that whatſoever is of the earth hath an aptneſs in it to feed the earthly part: and particularly, this of outward bowing to the creature, is apt to hurt him that doth it, and is likewiſe apt to hurt him that reciveth it. In mans giving and receiving honour, God hath been forgotten. They have forgotten God, who have been giving honour to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and they have forgotten God, who have been receiving honour from one another. And what if the Lord, who hath made us ſenſible of the evil herein, hath laid a reſtraint upon us? can any forbid the Lord from laying ſuch a thing upon us? or is it lawful for any to go about to hinder us from obeying the Lord therein? Thou who art thus eager in contending for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Art thou ſure it is not the evil part in thee, which doth ſo deſire it? If it be the good part in thee, thou wilt deſire it in meekneſs, and gentleneſs, yea and will be able to bear the want of it with joy, where it is denyed thee upon ſuch an account, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115389:15"/> that it may run more purely towards the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now if it be earthly honour, it is of a periſhing nature, it is not alwayes to laſt, but is one of the faſhions of this world which is to paſs away (how long a time ſoever it hath had) and God may call his people from it at his pleaſure: and if he call from it, they muſt leave it off though the earthly nature and powers be never ſo angry thereat. The Lord hath let man have a long day, wherein man hath been lifted up, and appeared great by receiving that honour which is of the earth, not of the faith: but at length the Lord will bring forth his day, wherein he will be great, and have every knee bow to him, and every tongue confeſs to him: and then man ſhall be little, and his honour fall, and the Lord alone be exalted, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
2.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth not the image of God grow up into the likeneſs of God? Doth God reſpect mens perſons? Did Chriſt regard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans perſon? Did not <hi>James</hi> ſay, <hi>If ye have reſpect to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ye commit ſin, and are convinced of the law, as tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</hi> James 2.9. Of what law? Of the law of faith, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth the new birth, and layeth flat the creature in its tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing nature, eſtate, and honour. For ſaith Chriſt, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not honour from men, nor gave honour to men,
<hi>how can ye believe, which receive honour one of another?</hi> John 5.44. That which receiveth earthly honour, is of the earth, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe, and that which giveth earthly honour, is of the earth, and ſo not of the faith. The faith is a denying of the earth, a taking up of the croſs to the earthly honour, which is as a block in the way of faith. How can ye believe, when ye cheriſh that part in you which is againſt the faith? The immortal ſeed of life, in the day of the Goſpel, grows up out of the earth, leaving it with its cuſtomes, faſhions, honours, yea and its nature and worſhips too, behind it.</p>
            <p>So that look into the ground of the thing, with the eye which ſeeth over the tranſgreſſing ſtate, and over all things which have ſprung up from the tranſgreſſing part, and which pleaſe that part which is out of the faith, out of the life and power, drawn from God into the earth, and it wil be manifeſt that earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour hath its root, foundation and ſervice there; but falleth off like a ſhackle from mans ſpirit, as the life riſeth in him and as he is redeemed out of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115389:15"/>Now as for <hi>Abrahams</hi> and
<hi>Jacobs</hi> bowings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thoſe things had their ſeaſon under the law (which made nothing perfect) as other things had, but now God calleth every man to bow to the Son, and will not permit ſo much as bowing to an Angel, who is far more honourable than any Magiſtrate. And the Son calleth to honour the Father, and to ſeek the honour which cometh from God only: and he that will be his Diſciple, muſt take up his croſs to the earthly part, and follow him, who neither gave earthly honour, nor received earthly honour, but condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. Therefore let men conſider the ground of the thing, and the different ſtate between Jews under the law, and Chriſtians under the Goſpel, and not think the bringing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances from them of old time, can diſpence with us in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt according to the law of faith, who gave us this pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of not receiving or giving honour to mens perſons, and let not the weight of our plea (it having ſo great impreſſion on our hearts) be deſpiſed by any that pretend relation to our Lord and Maſter, which I ſhall briefly thus recite.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is the ſingle and ſincere deſire of our hearts, to give all the honour and obedience to Magiſtrates, which is due unto them according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is manifeſt that we are careful of obſerving all juſt laws, and patient in ſuffering through unjuſt laws, or where the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate doth perſecute us without or againſt law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This kind of honour of pulling off the hat, and bowing to the perſon, we do not find commanded in Scripture, but we find Chriſts command againſt it, who ſaith, <hi>follow me,</hi> who both denyed to receive it, and did not give it; but condemned it. And we find its riſe to be from the earthly part, and to the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part it is given, which it pleaſeth being given to it, or is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at being denyed it: and this part we are taught by the Lord to crucifie in our ſelves, and not to cheriſh in others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The bowing of perſons under the law (which was an earthly ſtate, wherein many things were permitted, which are not permitted under the Goſpel) doth not bind Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, nor doth not limit the Spirit of God from taking of any one, or more, or all of his people, from giving that which the earthly part calleth honour, to that which is of the earth.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115389:16"/>5. We do appeal to the Lord our God (who is our judge and law-giver) that he hath laid this upon our Spirits, and hath ſmitten ſeveral of us, when there hath ariſen ſo much as a deſire in us to pleaſe men in this particular: and in the fear of his name, and in obedience to him do we forbear it, and not either in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of authority, or of the perſons in authority.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We find by much experience, that the forbearing of this is a ſervice to our Lord and Maſter, and an hurt to his enemy. It offendeth the paſſionate, it offendeth the rough, it offendeth the proud and lofty, that ſpirit is ſoon touched and ſtirred by it: but that which is low, that which is meek, that which is humble, that which is gentle, that is eaſily drawn from valuing and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, and findeth an advantage therein. And of a truth the earthly ſpirit knows, and feels that God is taking the honour from it, and giving it to the meek and humble, which makes it muſter up its forces and arguments to hold it as long as it can.</p>
            <p>Now what moderate man (much more any Chriſtian) could not forgo the putting off of an hat, or bowing of the knee upon ſo ſolemn and weighty an account as this. If this were thine own caſe, wouldſt thou be forced, impriſoned, fined, or have this made an argument againſt thee to baniſh thee or put thee to death? Thou doſt not know how the Lord may viſit thee by his Spirit, and what he may require of thee. He may call thee alſo to give forth thy teſtimony (and to fight under the banner of his Spirit) againſt all the faſhions, cuſtomes, honours, yea and worſhips of this World. That which is born of God, is not of this World: and as it groweth up in any earthen veſſel, ſo it draweth the veſſel alſo more and more out of this World. <hi>Ye are not of the World</hi> (but called out of the World)
<hi>therefore the World hates you.</hi> That which can pleaſe the World, that which can bow to it and honour it, that the World loves; but the immortal ſeed which cannot bow, but teſtifies againſt the Worlds honours, that they are not of the Father, but of the World, this ſeed the World hates, and the veſſels in whom it bubbles up, and through whom it giveth forth its teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the World.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But in the new Teſtament</hi> Luke <hi>ſtiles</hi> Theophilus <hi>moſt excellent, and</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaking to</hi> Feſtus
<hi>ſaid, moſt noble</hi> Feſtus, <hi>which are terms or expreſſions of honour and reverence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115389:16"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt did promiſe his Diſciples and Miniſters that he would be with them, and give them what to ſay. Now if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and true excellency did appear in any perſons, and he led them by his Spirit to acknowledge it, this is no ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for men to do the like in their own wills, or to give ſuch titles to perſons being in authority, whether they be ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or no. <hi>Luke</hi> knew
<hi>Theophilus</hi> to be excellent, and he was led by the Spirit of God to ſtile him excellent: for by the Spirit of God he wrote that Scripture,
<hi>Luke</hi> 1.3. wherein he ſo ſtiles him. And for <hi>Feſtus,</hi> he that ſhall ſtrictly obſerve his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, will find it to be very noble, in that he would not be won by the importunity and informations of the high Prieſt and chief of the Jews, and of the multitude alſo againſt
<hi>Paul,</hi> but apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to an upright conſideration of the cauſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.2, 24. to the end. The ſame Spirit which ſhewed the unworthy carriage and ignobleneſs of the high Prieſt, &amp; zealous profeſſing Jews, might move <hi>Paul</hi> to ſet this mark of honour upon
<hi>Feſtus.</hi> The Lord loveth truth in the heart, and truth in words, and the following of the guidance of his Spirit into truth: but to give a man high titles, meerly becauſe he is great and high in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without diſcerning that he is ſuch, and without the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Spirit ſo to do, this is of the fleſh, according to the will of the fleſh, out of the faith, and not according to truth and righteouſneſs: and in the fear of the Lord there is a watch ſet over our ſpirits in theſe things, leſt we ſhould eſteem and honour men according to the will of the fleſh, and not in the Lord. Titles of office, or of relations, as maſter, father, &amp;c. we find freedome to give, but titles which tend towards flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or exalting man out of his place, and the lifting up of his heart above his brethren, we have not freedome in the Lord to uſe; and <hi>Eliah</hi> alſo found a reſtraint upon him in this reſpect, <hi>Job</hi> 32.21, 22.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>It is noted as a brand and reproach of falſe teachers, that they deſpiſe dominion and ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.10. <hi>and</hi> Jude 8. <hi>Now it is well known that the practiſe of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>is but too like thoſe falſe teachers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It were worth a narrow ſearch and enquiry what the dominion and dignities (or glories) are, which the falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſpeak evil of or blaſpheme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Search the Scriptures, where
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115389:17"/> do ye find the falſe teachers ſpeaking evil of the earthly authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? nay they ſtill cling cloſe to them, exalt them, get them of their ſide and cry them up, and will be ſure enough never to fail in pleaſing the Magiſtrate with cringing and bowing, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of that nature. But there is the dominion of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the heart, there is the rule of his ſpirit over the fleſhly part, there is the truth in the inner man, there are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual dignities (or glories) theſe the falſe teachers in all ages did deſpiſe, and were not afraid to ſpeak evil of, though they ſhould have feared to ſpeak evil of the movings, and guidings, and loweſt appearings of the ſpirit of God (which excel in nature and worth the greateſt earthly dignities) yet they have not, but have blaſphemed the holy life and appearances of God in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nay they have not ſpared his more eminent breakings forth in his very Prophets, holy Apoſtles, or Chriſt himſelf. Mark what they ſpake evil of, they ſpake evil of <hi>the things they knew not:</hi> verſ. 10. What were the things they knew not? The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward movings and vertue of his ſpirit, the inward power, life, glory, and dominion of truth in the heart they knew not: it was againſt Chriſt in his people their evil deeds and hard ſpeeches were,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 15. But as for the high and great ones, the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and dignities of the earth, they knew them well enough, and did not ſpeak evil of them, but had their perſons in admiration, becauſe of the advantage they had by them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. They have alwayes had a double advantage from theſe, both of gain to themſelves, and of overbearing the lambs of Chriſt by their great ſwelling words. The Lord hath ſtill ſo ordered it in his wiſdome both before the coming of Chriſt, at his coming, and ſince, that the falſe Prophets and Teachers ſhould ſtill have the advantage of the outward authorities, and his people be a poor, afflicted, deſpiſed perſecuted remnant, whoſe glory is inward, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſcerned by the outward eye, no not of Gods <hi>Iſrael.</hi> See the dignities particularly expreſſed, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.6. <hi>The name of God,</hi> his holy power in his people, <hi>the Tabernacle</hi> which is ſanctified and made honourable for him by his ſpirit, <hi>them that dwell in Heaven,</hi> who are redeemed out of the earth, and have their converſation above, theſe are dignities which the earthly authorities, nay the falſe teachers themſelves never knew the worth of, and ſo they are not afraid to blaſpheme them. <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115389:17"/> The firſt beaſt, on which the falſe church rode, with the ſecond beaſt, which are of the very race of theſe falſe teachers, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an image to the firſt beaſt becauſe of advantage, all join to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in blaſpheming theſe dignities, <hi>Rev.</hi>
13. <hi>and chap.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>To open this a little further, <hi>John</hi> ſaid in his days, that it was then the laſt time: For there were many Antichriſts then come,
1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18. From whence came they? <hi>They went out from us,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but they were not of us,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>They were ſenſual, they had not the ſpirit,</hi> and ſo could not abide the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, life, judgement, and power of the ſpirit, but <hi>ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated themſelves,</hi> Jude, 19. But whither went they, when they went out from the true Church? why, they went out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.2. They got the form of godlineſs, which would ſtand well enough with the luſts &amp; eaſe of the fleſh, and went and preached up that in the world. And now ſpeaking the things of God in the worldly ſpirit, the world could hear them
<hi>v.</hi> 5. Thus having got a great party into the form of truth, now they blaſpheme the power, now they mock at the movings of the ſpirit, the leadings of the ſpirit, the living name, the true ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, the true inhabitants of heaven, who have their conver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation above in the heavenly nature, in the heavenly principle, in the pure ſpirit of life (for as they are begotten by the ſpirit, ſo they live in the ſpirit, and walk in the ſpirit:) This the falſe teachers (who have got the form of doctrine and the form of diſcipline, holding it in the fleſhly wiſdome, where they may hold their luſts too) mock at and blaſpheme, <hi>Jude</hi> 18. And this hath been the great way of deceit ſince the Apoſtacy, God gathered a ſeperated people from the world, the falſ teachers get the form of godlineſs from them and ſet it up in the world, and then turn againſt the power, and deny it, ſpeaking evil of, or blaſpheming the ſpirit which is the dominion, and his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations (in the ſpirits of his people) which are the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or glories of the new teſtament, which excel all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignities, and alſo the miniſtration of the firſt Covenant, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 8.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe for <hi>rayling ſpeeches.</hi> The falſe prophets can ſpeak ſmooth words; ſpeaking in the fleſhly wiſdom, they can pleaſe the fleſhly part in their very reproofs: but he that ſpeaks from God, muſt ſpeak his words, how harſh ſoever they ſeem to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115389:18"/> the fleſhly part: And he that ſpeaks in his name, ſpirit, Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and authority is exalted high above the conſideration of the perſon to whom he ſpeaks. What is a Prince, a Magiſtrate, a Ruler before the Lord, but clay or duſt and aſhes? If the Lord bid any of his ſervants call that which was once the faithful city, harlot, and ſay concerning her Princes that they are rebellious, and companions of thieves,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.21. <hi>and</hi> 23. What is the poor earthen veſſel, that it ſhould go to change or mollifie this ſpeech? And ſo for the falſe Prophets and teachers: If the ſpirit of the Lord (in the meaneſt of his ſervants) call them idol-ſhepherds, hirelings, thieves, robbers, dogs, dumb dogs, greedy dumb dogs that cannot bark, (though they can ſpeak ſmooth pleaſing words enough to fleſhly Iſrael and the earthly great ones) generation of vipers, hypocrites, whited Sepulchres, graves that appear not, &amp;c. who may reprove him for it, or find fault with the inſtrument he chuſes? Now man judging by the fleſhly wiſdom, may venture to call this rayling; and the Prophets of the Lord have been accounted rude, and mad, and troublers of Iſrael; and ſo it is at this day: but the Lord being angry with the tranſgreſſor, may ſend a rough rebuke to him, by what meſſenger he pleaſeth; and what is the poor creature, that he ſhould gainſay his maker, and deſire the meſſage might be ſmoother? But now theſe falſe teachers, who can ſpeak ſmoothly to the fleſhly part, flatter the great ones, and the profeſſors that fall in with their form of doctrine and diſcipline, they deny the power, blaſpheme the movings and goings forth of the ſpirit of God in his people, and if any be drawn by the ſpirit to ſeperate from their formal way, and to ſeek after the life and preſence of the power, him they cry out of as a Sectary, a blaſphemer, an heretick, and ſo bring rayling accuſations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that life and ſpirit by which he is drawn, and of him for following the drawings of it: and thus they become guilty of ſpeaking evil of what they know not, <hi>Jude</hi>
10. They that are drawn out of the worlds worſhips, know from what they were drawn: but they that remain ſtill in them, do not know the power which drew out of them, nor into what it drew, but looking on it with a carnal eye, it appears mean to them, and ſo they readily diſdain it, and think they may ſafely ſpeak evil of it, though in truth they know it not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115389:18"/>And as for <hi>curſings;</hi> There are children of the curſe, as well as of the bleſſing: and the ſpirit of the Lord may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his curſe againſt any children of the curſe by whom he pleaſes. Curſe ye <hi>Meroz,</hi> curſe ye bitterly, the inhabitants thereof, <hi>Judges</hi> 5.23. and yet <hi>Meroz</hi> did not perſecute, but only not come to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty. So the profeſſing Jews with their rulers and teachers were curſed by the ſpirit of the Lord, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 69.22. &amp;c. So <hi>Judas</hi> was curſed, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 109.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For <hi>Peter</hi> applieth it to him, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. Now if the curſe be cauſleſs, it ſhall not come, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.2. and well will it be with him whom men cauſleſly curſe, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11.) although they were the higheſt, devouteſt and moſt zealous profeſſing Jews, with their Prieſts and Rulers in thoſe daies; and although they ſhould be the higheſt, moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and devout formal Chriſtians, with their rulers and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in theſe days, who may have got this form, as well as they got that form, and yet hold the truth in the unrighteouſneſs, &amp; deny the power, as falſe teachers formerly did, who held the form, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. But the caſe of <hi>Shimei</hi> is not at all proper to the thing in hand, becauſe he did not pretend to curſe in the Lords name and authority, but manifeſtly out of the fear of God, curſed the Lords annointed in his low ſtate. Neither were theſe two <hi>Quakers</hi> put to death for curſing. So that if <hi>Humphry Norton</hi> were never ſo blamable, yet that reacheth not to them, but is to be reckoned to him that did it, who is to ſtand or fall to his own maſter therein. Yet this I may ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo extraordinary a caſe (we having not known the like) that if he had not the Lords clear warrant for what he did, ſurely the Lord will very ſeverely judge him, for ſpeaking ſo peremptorily and preſumptuouſly, in his name, if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by him.</p>
            <p>And ſo as touching <hi>contemptuous carriages.</hi> When there is not contempt in the heart, it is not eaſie to ſhew contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous carriages: but the fleſhly part miſſing of the honour which is pleaſing to it, and being offended thereby, is ready to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that to be ſpoken and done in contempt, which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and done in the humility and fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ground or conſideration to juſtifie their Law of baniſhment and death of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> is drawn from <hi>Solomons
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115389:19"/> confining of Shimei, and of putting him to death for breach of his confinement,</hi> whereupon they argue, that <hi>if execution of death be lawful upon breach of confinement, may not the ſame be ſaid for breach of baniſhment, baniſhment being not ſo ſtrait, but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more liberty than confinement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The queſtion is not whether the Magiſtrate upon no occaſion may baniſh upon pain of death, but whether the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Quakers</hi> upon pain of death was juſt or no? If it were never ſo manifeſt that a Magiſtrate might baniſh, and put to death in caſe of not obſerving his Law of baniſhment; yet that doth not prove that every Law of baniſhment is juſt, and that the death of ſuch as do not obey their Law, is juſt alſo; but he may make a Law in his own ſelf-will, pride, paſſion, reſolved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtiffneſs of ſpirit, and ſo draw the ſufferings of perſons under that Law (either of baniſhment or death) upon his own head. Now the <hi>Quakers</hi> coming in the name of the Lord, by his commiſſion, and upon his work (whom all the Magiſtrates of the earth are to reverence and bow before) if Magiſtrates will preſume to make a Law to baniſh them upon pain of death, yet if the Lord require them either to ſtay or return, they know whom to fear and obey, which delivers them from the fear of them who can only torture and kill the body: and they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther die in obedience to the Lord, than feel the weight of his hand upon their ſouls for their diſobedience. It is not in this caſe as it is in ordinary baniſhment upon civil accounts, where it is in mens will and power to abſtain from the place from which they are baniſhed; but they muſt fulfil the will of their Lord, not at all regarding what befals them therein.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth Ground or Conſideration to juſtifie their Law of Baniſhment and Death againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> is drawn from
<hi>their right and propriety which every man hath in his own houſe and land,</hi> and from <hi>the unreaſonableneſs and injuriouſneſs of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers intruding and entring into it, having no authority there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yea and when the owner doth expreſly prohibit and forbid the ſame. And that if any preſume to enter thus without legal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he might juſtly be impleaded as a thief or uſurper; and if in caſe of violent aſſault, he ſhould be killed, his blood would be upon his own head.</hi> Whereupon it is argued thus, that <hi>if pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons may in ſuch caſe ſhed the blood of ſuch intruders, may <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115389:19"/> not the like be granted to them that are the publick Keepers and Guardians of the Common-wealth? have not they as much power to take away the lives of ſuch, as contrary to prohibition ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade or intrude into their publick poſſeſſions or territories?</hi> And that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do thus invade, and intrude without authority they urge thus. <hi>For who can believe that</hi> Quakers
<hi>are Conſtables to intrude themſelves, invade, and enter, whether the Colony will or no, yea contrary to their expreſs prohibition? If in ſuch violent and bold attempts, they loſe their lives, they may thank themſelves as the blamable cauſe and authors of their own death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is no invaſion nor intruſion, for any Meſſengers and Servants of the Lord to enter into any part of his earth at his command, upon his errand, and about his work. And if any ſhould be ſo ſent to the houſe of a particular perſon, to deliver a meſſage from the Lord, and the owner of the houſe inſtead of hearing and conſidering his meſſage in meekneſs and fear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were of God or no, ſhould be rough and violent with him, and command him off before he had delivered his meſſage, and either upon his not immediate going off, or his return with another meſſage, (for the Lord if he pleaſe may ſend him again) ſhould fall upon him and kill him; upon whoſe head would this mans blood light?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If men will needs have it go for an invaſion, it is an invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſpiritual nature, and the defence from it cannot be by carnal weapons. Killing of mens perſons, is not the way to ſuppreſs either truth or error. How have the <hi>Papiſts</hi> been able to defend their Kingdome, or ſuppreſs the truth by their bloody weapons? They may prevail in their Territories againſt mens perſons for a ſeaſon, but the truth will have a time of dominion, and will in the mean time be getting ground in mens minds and conſciences by the ſufferings of the Witneſſes to it. Nay, my friends, if ye will defend your ſelves from this invaſion, ye muſt get better weapons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is this your rule concerning any that ſhall come in the name of the Lord, that if they be not Conſtables, or other earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Officers, ye will baniſh them and put them to death? Is the Lord of heaven and earth limited to ſend none but Conſtables a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? Well, ye may judge by your Law while your day laſts; but the Lord in his day will clear his Servants and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, though they have not been Conſtables, and lay it upon the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115389:20"/> head of them who have unrighteouſly ſhed it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth Ground or Conſideration whereby they juſtifie their Law of Baniſhment and Death againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> is this. <hi>Corruption of mind and judgement is a great infection and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and it is the Lords Command that ſuch corrupt perſons be not received into the houſe, which plainly enough implies that the houſhoulder hath power enough to keep them out, and that it was not in their power to come, if they pleaſed, whether the houſholder would or no. And if the father of the Family muſt keep them out of his houſe, the Father of the Common-wealth muſt keep them out of his juriſdiction (they being nurſing Fathers and nurſing Mothers by the account of God.) So that what an houſholder may do againſt perſons that are infected with the plague or peſtilence, (who may kill them if otherwiſe he cannot keep them out of his houſe) a Magiſtrate may do the like for his Subjects. And if Sheep and Lambs cannot be preſerved from the danger of Wolves, but the Wolves will break in amongſt them, it is eaſie to ſee what the Shepheard or Keeper of the Sheep may lawfully do in ſuch a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is granted, that Corruption of mind and judgment is defiling and infectious, and therefore every heart that knows the pretiouſneſs of truth is to wait on the Lord in his fear, in the uſe of thoſe means which he hath appointed for preſervation from it: but that killing the perſons is one of the means God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, this is ſtill the thing in controverſie, and is ſtill denyed to be either proper in it ſelf, or ſanctified by God to this end. The Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>there muſt be Hereticks, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt,</hi>
1 Cor. 11.19. but he doth not ſay, hereafter when there are Chriſtians Magiſtrates, they muſt baniſh or cut off the Hereticks, as faſt as they ſpring up: but God hath uſe of theſe things, for the exerciſing of the ſpirits of his people, and the truth gains by overcoming them in the faith and power of the ſpirit. And ſo, as touching <hi>Wolves,</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> called the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and told them that <hi>after his departure, grievous Wolves ſhould enter in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, not ſparing the flock,</hi> Acts 20.28, 29, 31. The Lord hath put into the hands of his Shepherd a ſword, which will pierce to the heart of the Wolf, he ſtanding faithful in the power of God, in the life of righteouſneſs, need not fear any Wolf, but <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115389:20"/> by the power of the ſpirit and preſence of the truth, ſhall be able to preſerve the conſciences of his flock pure to God. What kind of Shepherd is he, that cannot defend his flock without the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſword? but take away that, the Wolf breaks in, &amp; preys upon his ſheep. Surely the true Shepherd, who knows the vertue of the ſword God hath put into his hand, will never call to the Magiſtrate for his ſword of another nature, which cannot touch the Wolf, the Heretick, the Seducer, but only fleſh and blood, with which the Miniſters of Chriſt never wreſtled nor fought. And this is not the way to preſerve the hearts and conſciences of the flock (it may perhaps ſtrike terror into the fleſhly nature) but their conſciences are ſo much the more apt to be wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the doctrines, patience and ſufferings of thoſe who are thus dealt with. The Magiſtrates ſword being thus uſed, doth not at all preſerve that which is tender, but hurts it, diſ-ingages it, ſtirs up a Witneſs in it againſt thoſe that thus go about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that which they call truth, that build up their Jeruſalem with blood, and govern their flock with force, affrighting them from that which they call errors, and affrighting them into that which they call truth with an outward ſword; whereas the true Temple is built in peace, governed in peace, maintained in peace, defended by peace, and Errors and Hereticks diſpelled by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the ſpirit, manifeſting the deceit to the conſcience, and not by the ſword of the Magiſtrate, dealing with them as with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Malefactors. Now this I ſay as before the Lord, The true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, who hath received the ſword of the Spirit, and hath tried the vertue of it, cannot diſtruſt it, cannot deſire the Magiſtrates help by outward force againſt errors or hereſies: he that looketh upon it as inſufficient, and calleth to the Magiſtrate for his ſword, plainly diſcovers that he hath not received, or knoweth not the vertue of the true one, and diſhonoureth both his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters work and weapon.</p>
            <p>For that place of 2 <hi>John</hi> 10. It is one thing for a man not to receive a man into his houſe, and another thing for him to kill that perſon who offers to come againſt his will. Do ye believe in your hearts, that the Apoſtles intent was to direct the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to whom he wrote, to keep them out by violence, and to kill them if they could not otherwiſe keep them out? Though the parrallel is not proper, for God hath often ſent his Servants <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115389:21"/> into countries, cities, &amp; places of reſort againſt the will of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Prieſts, and falſe Prophets, but never to break violently into any mans houſe.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate keeping in his place, cannot but be <hi>a nurſing Father to the Church;</hi> for let him draw out his ſword againſt that wickedneſs which is proper for him to cut down, it will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly help to nurſe up the Church: but where hath the Magiſtrate commiſſion to meddle with any of the ſpiritual ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds work? Nay his ſword was never appointed to cut down errors, or hereſies, or hereticks, but the ſword of the Spirit in the hand of the ſpiritual Shepherd. God hath ſet up an hedge between theſe two powers, which he that breaketh down layeth both waſte as to their true uſe, vertue, and order: and this, Antichriſt hath long done in many appearances. The bringing of theſe two to rights, ſetting each in their proper place, will give ſuch a wound to his kingdome, as he will not be able to recover. And mark this by the way, Antichriſt, hath all along made uſe of the Magiſtrates ſword to ſlay the Lambs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Hereticks, Sectaries, Wolves, Blaſphemers: but Chriſt comes with
<hi>the ſpirit of his mouth</hi> to ſlay Antichriſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
2.8. That's the ſword all the Hereticks, Seducers, and falſe Prophets were ſlain with in the Apoſtles dayes before the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, and thats the ſword that Antichriſt (who hath made uſe of the other ſword againſt Chriſt all along the Apoſtacy) ſhall be ſlain with after the Apoſtacy. When Chriſt comes to fight againſt Antichriſt (who hath cruelly torn, rent and butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his people under the name of wolves) he will take his own ſword which is the words of his mouth: That did the work at firſt, that muſt do the work again. But in the middeſt, between theſe two ſeaſons; there hath been bad work made with the Magiſtrates ſwords, the witneſſes upon every appearance and breaking forth of Gods truth in them, having been liable to feel the ſmart of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Their ſixt and laſt ground and conſideration, whereby they juſtifie their law of baniſhment and death againſt the
<hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> is this. <hi>It was the commandment of the Lord Jeſus unto his Diſciples, that when they were perſecuted in one City, They ſhould flee unto another, and according it was his own practiſe, and the practiſe of the Saints, who when they have been perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, have fled away for their own faſety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115389:21"/>
               <hi>This</hi> (they ſay) <hi>reaſon requires, that when men have liberty unto it they ſhould not refuſe ſo to do, becauſe otherwiſe they will be guilty of tempting God, and of incurring their own hurt, as having a fair way open for the avoyding thereof, but they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly expoſe themſelves thereto.</hi> Whereupon they argue thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If therefore that which is done againſt the</hi> Quakers,
<hi>were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed perſecution, what ſpirit may they be thought to be acted and led by, who are in their actings ſo contrary to the commandment and example of Chriſt and of his Saints in the caſe of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which theſe men ſuppoſe to be their caſe? Plain enough it is, that if their caſe were the ſame, their actings are not the ſame, but quite contrary. So that Chriſt and his Saints were led by one Spirit, and theſe people by another: for rather than they would not ſhew their contempt of authority, and make diſturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his people, they chuſe to go contrary to the expreſs directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, and the approved example of his Saints, to the hazard and peril of their own lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Afflictions, tribulations, tryals, perſecutions are not to be fled from, but to be born and paſſed through to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, into which the entrance is through many of theſe, <hi>Acts</hi>
14.22. and Chriſt ſaith, he that will be his Diſciple, muſt take up his croſs daily and follow him, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. Now perſecution for Chriſt is part of the croſs, which the Diſciple muſt not run away from, but take up and follow Chriſt with. Yea the Apoſtle is very expreſs, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Yea, and all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> It is the portion of all, and all muſt bear it. The World hateth and perſecuteth (in ſome degree or other) all that are not of the World; and all muſt be content with their daily portion thereof, waiting on God for ſtrength to bear the croſs, not flying it: and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle commends the <hi>Hebrews</hi> for <hi>enduring the great fight of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,</hi> Heb. 10.32, 33, 34. The Jews were zealous for the Law and Ordinances of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and grievous perſecutors of the Chriſtians (eſpecially of ſuch as had been of them before) now the Chriſtians are commended for ſtanding the ſhock, for bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the brunt, for not fearing the loſs of name, goods, life or any thing, but eyeing the heavenly treaſure. So Chriſt warning of perſecution, bids the Church to <hi>fear none of thoſe things which ſhe ſhould ſuffer,</hi> but <hi>be faithful unto the death:</hi> and he that thus <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115389:22"/> overcometh, ſhould not be hurt of the ſecond death, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.10, 11. and the Apoſtle
<hi>Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>if ye ſuffer for righteouſneſt ſake happy are ye, and be not afraid of their terror, neither be troubled,</hi> 1 Pet
3.14. and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> bids the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one mind ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing terrified by your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of ſalvation, and that of God.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the, <hi>Hebrews,</hi> as having done well in bearing the great ſight of afflictons, encourages them to go on ſtill, and not be <hi>weary or faint in their minds, but reſiſt even to blood,</hi> eyeing Chriſt, who endured the contradiction of ſinners to the very laſt,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.3, 4. And he practiſed as he taught, for he was not terrified with bonds or afflictions, nor accounted his life dear unto him, but that which was dear unto him was the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his Lord and Maſter, in preaching and witneſſing to his truths, as his ſpirit led him,
<hi>Acts</hi> 20.23, 24. truſting on the Lord to uphold him in enduring of them, or to deliver him out of them, as he pleaſed, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.11. but that which he, and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Saints of Chriſt applyed themſelves to in caſe of perſecution, was to ſuffer, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
4.12. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are that will be Chriſts faithful Diſciples now, muſt look to meet with the ſame croſs as they did, not only from the prophane World, but from the worldly profeſſors alſo: for there were not only zealous worldly profeſſors in that age, but the ſame ſpirit hath remained in every age ſince, which ſtill gets into the beſt form it can (when need requires) to oppoſe the power thereby. And they that are in the Spirit and in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, muſt expect to be perſecuted by ſuch: and they are to bear it, and not to flie from it, unleſs by a particular call and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation from the Lord for a particular ſervice, which is not the rule (as it is here made) but rather an exception from the rule. So Chriſt ſending his Diſciples in haſt to preach the Goſpel, bids them not ſalute in the way, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.4. nor be ſtopped by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, but haſten to publiſh the ſound of Chriſts coming in the Cities of
<hi>Iſrael: for the harveſt was great, but the laborers few, Mat.</hi>
9.37. and yet notwithſtanding all the haſt they could make, they ſhould not have <hi>gone over the Cities of Iſrael, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Son of man come, Mat.</hi> 10.23. There is a time to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115389:22"/> perſecution, and a time to flee from perſecution; and both theſe are to be known in the Lord, and to be obeyed in the leadings of his Spirit: but to lay it down as a general rule for Chriſtians to obſerve, that when they are perſecuted, they ſhould flee, this is expreſly contrary to the Scriptures afore mentioned, which ſhew that Chriſtians are not generally to flee, but to ſtand in the ſervice and work to which they are called, bearing witneſs not only by believing and publiſhing, but alſo by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the teſtimony of the truth. They are Chriſts Souldiers, and their duty is to ſtand in the battel, and bear all the ſhot and perſecutions of the enemy: if God call them off to any other ſervice, that is a ſufficient warrant for them: but flying upon other termes may prove a great diſhonour to their Maſter, and to his cauſe, and truth, and may be the occaſion of a great loſs to their Spirits, who are ſo tempted to flee. Neither is this bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the brunt of perſecutions, and ſtanding in Gods work and ſervice (notwithſtanding them all, even unto death) any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, but an obedient taking up of the croſs according to his will and command. And whereas you plead that reaſon requires it; what kind of reaſon is it which bids avoid the croſs of Chriſt, and flee for ſafety? And what kind of Spirit is that, which preacheth this Doctrine, laying it down as a general rule, for Chriſtians to flee when they are perſecuted? Is it not that Spirit which fain would be at eaſe in the fleſh, in ſo much as it ſelf will rather perſecute, than be diſturbed of its fleſhly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, though its very unwilling to bear the reproach of being accounted a perſecutor? Ah how did the Jews cry out againſt their Fathers for killing the Prophets, and verily thought if they had lived in their dayes, they ſhould by no means have done it: and yet the ſame Spirit was in them, though they ſaw it not, but thought themſelves far from it. That which blinded them was a wrong knowledge of the Scriptures, and a great zeal and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion about their Temple, worſhip and Ordinances, without a ſenſible feeling of the guidance of Gods Spirit. The ſame Spirit that deceived them, layeth the ſame ſnare in theſe dayes, and men ſwallow it as greedily, &amp; with as great confidence as they did, the zealous profeſſors of religion for the generality, ſtill becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecutors of the preſent appearance of truth, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115389:23"/>Thus in the fear of the Lord God, and in love to your ſouls, with a meek and gentle ſpirit (not being offended at what ye have done, but looking over it to the Lord, who bringeth glory to his name, and advantage to his truth by the ſufferings and death of his Saints) have I anſwered your grounds and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and in the ſame fear, love and meekneſs, have I ſome things further to propoſe to your conſiderations, which are of great concernment to you, and deſerve to be weighed by an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual hand in the equal ballance, without prejudice or partiality.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider meekly and humbly, whether the Scriptures be the rule of the Children of the new covenant? for if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was not intended by God for the rule, and ye take it to be the rule, then ye may eaſily miſtake the way to eternal life, and alſo err in your underſtanding and uſe of the Scriptures; making ſuch an uſe of them as they were never intended for, and ſo miſſing of the true uſe and intent of them.</p>
            <p>Now that the Scripture was not intended, nor given forth by God to be the rule of the Children of the New Covenant, beſides our faithful Teſtimony from the ſight of the thing in the true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal light, weigh our arguments from the Scripture, many are mentioned in our writings, conſider at preſent of theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Scripture is an outward rule or law, but the Scripture ſaith, the law of the new covenant ſhall be an inward law. It is written in the Prophets, that all the Children of the new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or new
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhall be taught of the Lord (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13.) who teacheth them inwardly by his Spirit, and writeth his law in their hearts,
<hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. and after this manner did the Lord take his people into covenant with himſelf, and teach them in the Apoſtles dayes, 1
<hi>John</hi> 2.27. The covenant is inward, the teacher inward, the writing inward, the law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: and there it is to be read, learned and known, where the Spirit teacheth and writeth it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Scripture (or the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets) was not the law of the Children of the new covenant (as ſuch) not in the time of the old covenant. The law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was the rule of their outward ſtate, it was the rule of the outward <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> but not the rule of the inward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no not then in thoſe dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115389:23"/>In <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.1. <hi>Moſes</hi> makes a Covenant with Iſrael by expreſs command from God, beſides the former covenant which he made with them in <hi>Horeb.</hi> And he ſaith the commandment of this Covenant is not to be looked for where the other was written, but in another place, in a place neerer to them, even in ther mouth and in their heart, there they were to read, hear, and receive the commandment of this covenant. <hi>For this commandement which I command thee this day, it is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off,</hi> Deut. 30.11. <hi>it not in heaven,</hi> ve. 12. <hi>neither is it beyond the ſea,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>but the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayſt do it,</hi> ver. 14. <hi>and this was the way of life then,</hi> ver.
15. <hi>ſee</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>I have ſet before thee this day life and good, and death and evil.</hi> Here thy eternal happineſs depends: obey this word and live, diſobey it and die. And if they had kept to this word, they would alſo have walked in obedience to the Law: but neglecting this, they could never keep the Law, but ſtill came under the curſe of it and miſſed of the bleſſings. They thought to pleaſe God with ſacrifices, and oyle, and incenſe, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving new Moons and Sabbaths, wherein the Lord ſtill rejected them, for want of their obedience to this word: and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſtill guide them to this word, bidding them
<hi>circumciſe their hearts,</hi> which alone can be done by this word,
<hi>and waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the evil of their doings,</hi> which alone can be done by this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Yea after much conteſt between the Lord and them, when they ſeemed very deſirous to pleaſe the Lord with what he ſhould require, whether <hi>burnt offerings, calves, rams, or oyl</hi> in great plenty, the Prophet laies by all that, and points them to the obedience of this word, as the way to pleaſe God, and as the only thing that he required of them: <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> Micah 6.8. All this is written in thy heart man, read there, obey that word, that is the thing that God requires. So <hi>Davids Law</hi> was the word written in his heart; he ſaw through ſacrifices and burnt offerings to the inward writing, and this made him wiſer than all his teachers, who were buſied about the outward. The outward Law was but a ſhadow of good things to come, it made nothing perfect: but <hi>David</hi> knew a <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115389:24"/> perfect law, <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul,</hi> Pſal. 19.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scriptures of the New-Teſtament never call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves the rule, but they call another thing the rule: they call the writings of Gods ſpirit in the hearts of his people the Laws of the new Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. they call Chriſt the way, the truth, the life,
<hi>John</hi> 14.6. (the way is the rule, the truth is the rule, the life is the rule) they call the new creature the rule, walking according to which, the peace and mercy is received and injoyed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. they refer to the comforter as the guide into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. yea as the compaſs of all truth, wherein the believer is to have his whole life and courſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.25. live in the ſpirit, walke in the ſpirit, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſpirit, keep within that compaſs and ye connot err. A man may err in underſtanding and interpreting of Scriptures: but he that hath received the ſpirit, knoweth the ſpirit, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpirit, keepeth to the ſpirit, ſo far as he doth ſo, cannot poſſibly err. So ſaith
<hi>Iohn,</hi> writing concerning ſeducers, warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them, 1
<hi>Iohn</hi> 2.26. <hi>Ye have received an anointing, which teacheth you of all things,</hi> keep to the teachings of that in every thing, and ye are ſafe. But may we not be deceived? Nay the annointing keeps from all the deceit in the heart, and from all the deceits of ſeducers; <hi>it is truth, and no lie, ver.</hi> 27. and it leads into all truth, and our of every lie: And this will teach you to abide in him. In whom? in the word which was from the beginning, which is ingrafted into the heart of the believer, and into which the heart of the believer is ingrafted; and ſo he truly is in the vine, and the ſap of the vine runs up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, which makes him fruitful to God, he abiding in the word which he hath heard from the beginning, and the word which was from the beginning abiding in him, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly, that the righteouſneſs of faith cometh by the hearing of this word, making the ſame word the rule to the children of the new covenant now, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid was the commandement of God to them then, quoting this place of <hi>Moſes</hi> for it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that <hi>Paul</hi> indeed taught nothing but <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, pointing to the very ſame word and commandement of eternal life, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had done. <hi>That is the word of faith which we preach,</hi> that word which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115389:24"/> taught, which he ſaid was nigh in the heart and in the mouth (no man need aſcend up to heaven, or go down to the deep, or ſeek any where elſe for it) that's the very thing we point you to, that's the word of faith, that's the commandement of life. And with what zeal would <hi>Paul</hi> (were he now alive in the body) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt ſuch, who ſhould over-look or deny this word, and ſet up his writing, with the writings of the reſt of the Apoſtles, for a rule inſtead thereof? yea I could ſhew yet further, how the ſpirit of prophecy, or teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> or living appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God in the heart, hath been a rule to the witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſts deceit, all along the night of Apoſtacy (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. and 19.10.) though they themſelves, being in the night, diſtinctly knew not what was their rule, but by a ſecret breath of life were quickned, guided, preſerved, and in it accepted: but theſe things will open of themſelves, as the miſt is expelled, and the vail rent which hath over-ſpread all Nations, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red profeſſors generally in this night of Antichriſtian darkneſs, and univerſal apoſtacy from the living power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider whether the Scripture be your rule or no? that is whether in ſingleneſs of heart ye wait on the Lord, to open the Scriptures to you by his ſpirit, and to keep out your carnal reaſon from thence (which cannot underſtand them, but will be wreſting them, and making them ſpeak as it would have them) or whether ye take ſcope to ſearch into them with that part, which ever was ſhut out from the right knowledge of them. <hi>The natural man underſtandeth not the things of the ſpirit of God,</hi> the ſpirit of the Lord alone underſtandeth the meaning of his own words, and he alone gives the underſtanding of them, which he gives not to the wiſe Searcher and Diſputer (nor to the prudent profeſſor,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25.) but to the babe which he begets, to which he gives the kingdom, and opens the words which the Scripture ſpeaks concerning the kingdome. <hi>The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the fleſh is enmity againſt God,</hi> and if that ſearch into the Scriptures, it will gather only a knowledge ſuitable to its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> were great enemies, and ſtrong enemies, by the knowledge which they had gathered out of the Scriptures written to them: and the ſame ſpirit hath alſo wound it ſelf into the Scriptures written ſince: And as then that ſpirit fought againſt Chriſt and his Apoſtles, with thoſe very Scriptures which the <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115389:25"/> ſpirit of Chriſt had formerly written: ſo the ſame ſpirit fights now againſt the Lambs and witneſſes of Chriſt, with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which were written ſince. Yea the great ſtrong hold of Antichriſt at this day, is Scripture interpreted by the fleſhly wiſdome: for Antichriſt comes not in a direct denial of Chriſt or Scriptures (he is too cunning to be found there) but bends them aſide by the fleſhly wiſdom to ſerve the fleſhly will: and thus undermines the ſpirit, and exalts the fleſh by a fleſhly underſtanding and interpretation of thoſe very Scriptures, which were written by the ſpirit againſt the fleſh. And through this miſtake it is, that ſome innocently cry up things practiſed at the firſt ſpringing up of truth, not ſeeing of what nature they were, and upon what account they were done, and what of them were caſt off by the ſame ſpirit, which before had led to the uſe of them, though the Scripture expreſly teſtifieth thereof. For <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2. there was the meaſuring of the building which Gods own ſpirit had built, part whereof was reſerved for God, part given to the Gentiles, or uncircumciſed in heart, who are now the Gentiles, ſince the breaking down of the former di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betwixt <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi> That which God reſerved for himſelf was, <hi>the Altar, the Temple, the worſhippers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> all theſe are inward. <hi>The outward Court was given to the Gentiles,</hi> to thoſe who would be worſhippers under the Goſpel, and yet had not the circumciſion of the Goſpel, to them the Court which is without the Temple is given; and this they get and cry up, and then tread under foot <hi>the Holy City,</hi> tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling upon the inward, and undervaluing it: Chriſt within, the Spirit within, the Law within, the power within becomes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: and this they have power to do, even to keep down the inward and cry up the outward all the time of the forty two months, and to perſecute and ſlay the witneſſes whom God raiſed up to teſtifie for the inward, and againſt the outward (as it is now in the Gentiles hands, and made uſe of by them to keep down the inward) and ſo the building being thus taken down, the Church flies out of it into the wilderneſs, where ſhe had a place prepared of God for her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6. Mark, ſhe is not where ſhe was before, that building was meaſured, taken down, and diſpoſed of by God: but ſhe hath been, and is all the time of <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115389:25"/> the 42. months or 1260 daies in another place, prepared by the ſpirit of God for her, whither ſhe fled, and where ſhe was nouriſhed from the face of the Serpent, who was ſeeking after her and making war with the remnant of her ſeed,
<hi>ver.</hi> 14. &amp;c. And they that ſeek for her now in her former building, will miſs of her, and may meet with another woman, (which in ſeveral appearances, and diſguiſes, and practiſing of ordinances ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the outward Court) blaſphemes the holy City, the true Temple, Altar, and Worſhippers. Happy is he that can read this, for it is the myſtery of this book, ſealed from all the Gentiles and Worſhippers in the outward Court.</p>
            <p>Many ſorts cry up the Scriptures for their rule, but which of them is taught by the ſpirit to keep the carnal part out of the Scriptures? Which of them keeps out their own will and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, receiving their knowledge of Scriptures from that Spirit which wrote them? Do not men rather gather a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the fleſh, and then grow ſtrong; and wiſe, and able to diſpute, and confident in their own way, and become feirce deſpiſers of thoſe who cannot own their interpretation of theſe Scriptures? and thus the mind of God, the true meaning of the Scriptures is not their rule, but an image which they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out of it, a meaning which their wit hath ſtrongly imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and fenced with arguments, and the real mind and intent of the ſpirit is hid from them. So by this means many both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their own ſouls, and help to deceive the ſouls of others, miſſing of the plainneſs and ſimplicity of the ſpirit, and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſences in the wit and ſubtilty of the fleſhly part, where the ſerpentine wiſdom lodgeth and twines about the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Now what do theſe men do? whom do they ſerve? and whither do they run themſelves, and lead many other poor ſouls, whom they pretend to be helpful to ſave?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider whether ye did not flee from the Croſs, in your tranſplanting into <hi>New-England,</hi> and ſo let up that part in you there, which ſhould have been kept down by the Croſs here, and gave advantage to that ſpirit to get ground in you, which ye outwardly fled from? The ſafety is in ſtanding in Gods counſel, in bearing the Croſs, in ſuffering for the teſtimony of his truth: but if at any time there be a fleeing of the Croſs: (whether the inward or the outward) without Gods direction, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115389:26"/> the evil Spirit is thereby let in, his part ſtrengthened, and the life weakned. That Spirit which would ſave it ſelf from the croſs, is the ſame with that which would perſecute that which will not ſave it ſelf. Mark how ſharply Chriſt ſpeaks to
<hi>Peter</hi> upon this account, when he would have tempted him to avoid the croſs, <hi>get thee behind me Satan, thou art an offence unto me, for thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voreſt not the things of God,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 16.23. The ſeed offers up all to God in his ſervice, will ſuffer any thing for his names ſake, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the loſs of liberty, goods, yea life it ſelf for the teſtimony to the leaſt truth: now that which ſayes to the ſeed, when ſufferings come for the teſtimony of truth, <hi>avoid it, ſave thy ſelf, let not this be unto thee,</hi> or the like, that's Satan: and if Satan be not caſt behind, but that counſel hearkned unto which leadeth from the croſs, Satan is followed. And if ye fled your proper croſs, in your removal from hence unto
<hi>New-England,</hi> though ye might meet with many others there, yet hereby ye loſt your proper advantage of ſerving and honouring God in your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: yea ye loſt that, which would have kept your Spirits tender, and open to the voyce of Gods Spirit, and then no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel if afterwards ye grew hard and fit to perſecute, who firſt had ſhewed your ſelves unfit and unworthy to ſuffer. Ye might meet with many croſſes afterwards, which might neither be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to humble you, nor keep you tender, having once loſt that croſs which was appointed of God to do it: for all croſſes do not break, humble or keep the heart low, and meek, but ſuch as are ſent, and ſanctified by God thereunto.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, when ye came to <hi>New-England,</hi> whether ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs grew up in you, and was abundantly exerciſed towards ſuch as might differ from you, or whether ye were as eager for the way that ye thought to be right, as the conformiſts you fled from, were for the way they thought to be right? When <hi>Iſrael</hi> came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into their own Land, they were to be tender even toward an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> much more towards their own bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Now, when ye were out of danger of being perſecuted your ſelves, did ye lay a foundation of tender uſage towards all that ſhould differ from you, or did you lay a foundation of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting ſuch as differ, and would ſuffer none differing from you, but perſecute them, juſt as the Biſhops perſecuted you? Did ye flee the having of your ſelves perſecuted, or did ye flee the <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115389:26"/> perſecuting Spirit? For if ye did flee only your own perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not the perſecuting Spirit in your ſelves, no marvel though it fell a perſecuting, ſo ſoon as the fear of your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was over. In this fleſhly part there is a perſecuting Spirit, which if it be not kept down by the power of God, though it loves not to be perſecuted, yet will ſoon be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Did you feel your ſelves to grow in the inward life, upon your coming into <hi>New-England,</hi> or did that begin to flag and wither, and your growth chiefly conſiſt in form and outward order, in which ye might eaſily be miſtaken too? for many who have given a true teſtimony, and have been faithful in helping to pull down, yet have erred when they came to build up. That Spirit which is kept low by perſecution, and gives forth its teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt things in fear and trembling, is many times exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when it is out of the fear of perſecution, and can weigh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, conſider, and reſolve things in that part which cannot build for God. <hi>Ephraim</hi> under the rod ſpake trembling, but the rod being off, he could exalt his own wiſdome, and offend in <hi>Baal.</hi> That worſhip and way of government and order, which a man takes up in the fleſhly reaſon, and which falls in with the worldly intereſt, he ſerves not the true God in, but <hi>Baal.</hi> This is that deſtroyes and eats out the life of Religion in many, namely the mixing of it with their worldly intereſt, for then the offence of the croſs ceaſes to them, and they begin to be offended at others on whom the croſs is ſtill laid by God, thinking that they may comply with them in joyning their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and worldly intereſt together, and ſo avoyd the croſs as well as they. Nay, he that will follow Chriſt, muſt take up the daily croſs, even that croſs which God daily layes upon him, who will ſtill be requiring ſomewhat which is contrary to his own fleſhly part, and contrary to the fleſhly part of thoſe with whom he converſes. And as this croſs is taken up, the worldly part is offended, and the life grows, cutting down worldly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and wayes of Religion daily: but as worldly intereſts are followed and kept up, the fleſhly part thrives, and the life de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes and ſuffers, even till at length it come under death, and then death hath the dominion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider whether your chief ſtrength of ſetting up your <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115389:27"/> Church Government &amp; order at firſt, &amp; of bringing perſons into it, and of preſerving them in it, lie in the ſpirit and ſpiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, or in the fleſh and carnal weapons? if in the ſpirit and ſpiritual weapons, then ye will be able in God to perſwade mens conſciences to it, and to preſerve them by the ſame vertue and ſtrength which perſwaded them, and this ye will ſtill have the main recourſe to: but if in carnal, then ye will have recourſe to the carnal, and there will be your main confidence of keeping up your Church. For if it was built by that power, it muſt be upheld by that power: ſo that take that away, it falls. This is Antichriſts ſtrength; he ſets up a form in the wiſdome, and maintains it by the outward ſword. Take him off from this, and put him to gaining ground by the demonſtration of the Spirit to mens conſciences as in the ſight of God, or to preſerving his ground ſo, here he is at a loſs, and his Kingdome daily falls, even in the moſt refined parts of it. Let every Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that nameth the name of Chriſt, depart from the wayes of Antichriſt, and make the Spirit of Chriſt their ſtrength: for that is indeed the only ſtrength of the true Religion, both of the inward and outward part thereof. In that it begins, by that it is preſerved, and there alſo it grows and is perfected.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Conſider (for it lies upon me to preſs it yet further, and lay it yet more home to you for your good) whether the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit did not take its advantage of aſſaulting you, upon your getting from under the croſs here into <hi>New-England,</hi> and whether it did not ſoon find a place in you there, and grow up in you, and bring you from ſtep to ſtep to that degree of hardneſs, that ye could at length even drink the blood of the Saints?</p>
            <p>That it was then the proper time of the perſecuting Spirit to ſeek to get an entrance into you, that is very manifeſt; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it did get entrance or no, that belongs to you narrowly to ſearch and examine. When ye were under the hatches, while ye your ſelves were perſecuted, then there was little room for that Spirit in you, then was not a proper time for your enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of it: but when ye were at liberty to chuſe a way and form of worſhip, then was a proper time for this temptation to prevail with you, of ſetting up your own way as the chief or only way, and under a pretence of zeal for God, to perſecute <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115389:27"/> the breakings forth of his light in others: for it could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that that Spirit ſhould directy tempt you (who had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo much by perſecution) ſuddainly to become perſecutors of others, but to hide its bait under a cover, and under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of zeal for God, his truths and way of worſhip, to blind your eyes and draw you aſide into that, which is indeed perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. Sin is very deceitful and ſeeks covers, and of all ſins per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution has moſt need of covers, it is of ſo contrary a nature to the tender Spirit of the Goſpel. Now when ſin hath got its cover, then by degrees it hardens the heart, both from and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth. <hi>Take heed,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>leaſt any of you be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, Heb.</hi> 3.12, 13. and perſecution moſt hardens of any ſin. How cruel, how bloody doth it make? it even unmans men. Priſons, Whips, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of ears, Baniſhment, Death, all is little enough, if not too little. And what reviling doth it fill mens pens and tongues with, making them ſo hot and paſſionate, that they cannot equally conſider the cauſe, but miſunderſtand it, miſrepreſent it, &amp; ſtrive to make it appear another thing both to themſelves and others, than indeed in truth and plainneſs it is. Look over your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, conſider the cauſe again in a more meek and upright Spirit, and ye your ſelves will eaſily ſee, how in your heat ye have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and dealt more injuriouſly with others, than ye your ſelves were ever dealt with.</p>
            <p>There is a time of righteous judgment, wherein the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward covers ſhall be ripped off, and the ſinner appear what he is; and then the perſecutor ſhall bear that ſhame, that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that miſery which is the portion of that Spirit. It is but a ſmall advantage to it, to cover its iniquity for a little moment. If ye could make all the world believe that ye are not perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, what would this profit you, if in the day of the Lord ye ſhould be found ſuch? But having proceeded thus far, it is hard for you to conſider and retreat. That Spirit hath great advantage over you, to make you accept of any cover, it can now offer you to hide your ſelves under. Oh that ye could ſee how ye have wreſted Scriptures, and what ſtrange kind of r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments ye have formed, to make that which ye have done paſs with your own hearts, and to make it appear ſomewhat plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115389:28"/> to others. Yet all this will not do, the eye of the Lord ſees through you; and that light which ye reproach, makes you manifeſt to be at preſent in ſubjection under the bloody dark power, who will hold you as long as he can, and furniſh you with ſuch weapons as he has, againſt the Lamb and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. But ye come forth to the battel in a bad day, for the light is ariſen to conquer, and is not now to be overcome with the darkneſs. And though ye meet the Woman and her ſeed, with a floud of reproaches and perſecutions, yet that will not ſtop her from coming forth out of the Wilderneſs, to ſhew her beauty and innocency again in the earth. Conſider theſe things, and come out of this hard Spirit into tenderneſs (if it be poſſible) that the ſtill, meek, gentle Spirit of life, may be your leader from under all falſe covers into the truth it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where there is a gentle lying down with all that is of God, and not ſo much as an offence becauſe of any difference (much leſs heart-burnings and perſecutions) but a ſweet waiting on the Lord, for every ones growth, in their ſeveral ranks and ſtations.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Since my waiting on the Lord for the preſence and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his Spirit, in the examining the foregoing Grounds and Conſiderations, there came forth an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to <hi>John Norton's</hi> Book, wherein are laid down ſome further Grounds by way of juſtifying of their proceedings, which for their ſakes, and likewiſe on the behalf of the truth and people of God, I may alſo ſay ſomewhat to.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt, they inſinuate an argument concerning
<hi>the not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of evil, which</hi> (they ſay) <hi>is common to all that fear God, with themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Evil is to be reſiſted, but in Gods way, according to Gods will, and not according to the will of the fleſh. Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al evils are to be reſiſted (by, and in the faith) with ſpiritual weapons, which God hath appointed and ſanctified thereto. Earthly evils, outward evils, tranſgreſſions of the juſt law of the Magiſtrate, are to be reſiſted by the ſword of the Magiſtrate. <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115389:28"/> Here are the bounds which God hath ſet, which he that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth, ſinneth againſt the Lord and his own ſoul. But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is not to ſtep out of Gods way to reſiſt the Magiſtrates evil, nor the Magiſtrate to ſtep out of Gods way to reſiſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual evil, but both are to wait on the Lord, for his bleſſing on the means he hath appointed, and it is better for each of them not to reſiſt evil, but let it grow upon them, till the Lord pleaſe to appear againſt it, than to overcome it by an unrighteous wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. <hi>Woe to them that go down to Egypt for help, and ſtay on horſes, and truſt in Chariots,</hi> Iſa. 31.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond argument is taken from <hi>the ſole cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their tranſplanting, which they ſay was to enjoy liberty, to walk peaceably in the faith of the Goſpel, according to the order of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That there was an honeſt intent in many of them, in tranſplanting into <hi>New-England,</hi> I do not doubt; though whether they had a ſufficient warrant from God to tranſplant, was doubted and objected againſt them, by many of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious fellow ſufferers here in old <hi>England,</hi> who teſtifie them that they did believe it to be their duty not to fly, but ſtay and bear their teſtimony for God and his truth by ſuffering: and this had been a better way of reſiſting that which was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly evil, than of reſiſting by the ſword that for evil, which in due time they themſelves may ſee and acknowledge not to have been ſo. But if they did truly deſire liberly, did not the enemy tempt them to be ſelfiſh, to ſeek it ſo far as might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe themſelves, excluding ſuch as might differ from them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as juſt grounds as they themſelves differed from others? Did not they ſet bounds to the truth, and bounds to the ſpirit of God, that thus far it ſhould appear and no further? Whereas God hath degrees of diſcovering and leading out of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian darkneſs: and he that oppoſeth the next diſcovery of truth, the next ſtep out of <hi>Babylon</hi> is as real an enemy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, as he that oppoſed the fore going. In that they teſtified againſt the Biſhops, they did well: but if they will now ſet up a ſtand, either to themſelves or others, and not follow the leadings of the Lamb, their life may be withered, and they may periſh in the Wilderneſs, while others are following the guide which they left, (when they ſet up their ſtand) towards <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115389:29"/>And as for <hi>walking peaceably:</hi> That they might be free from the fear of outward powers, having liberty to try what ever pretends to be of God; and if it appear error, be out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of having their conſciences forced, this is a great mercy. But if they would live ſo peaceably, as that no diſcovery of God further, ſhould ever ſtart up among them, nor the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be ſuffered to ſend any of his ſervants with any further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of light unto them, this is not a peace which God allowes to any man, nor which his people deſire, but only the carnal part which loves to be at eaſe, and not to be at the pains of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in the fear of the Lord, of what comes forth in his name. And who walk thus, walk not in the faith, nor in the order of the Goſpel, which doth not ſuddenly reject any thing, but firſt throughly tries both doctrines and ſpirits whether they be of God or no. He that rejects that which is of God, cannot thrive or proſper in his ſpirit; and he that tries in the haſtineſs of the fleſh, and not in the patience and meekneſs of the ſpirit, is in great danger of rejecting what ever of God appears,</p>
               <p>But can they not enjoy there own liberty and walk in the order of the Goſpel, and mannage the ſword of the ſpirit againſt errors and ſpiritual enemies (according to the order of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) which is mighty through God to cut down the fleſh, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they get the Magiſtrates ſword to cut down every appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of truth (and every perſon holding forth any truth) but what they themſelves ſhall own? Cannot the ſpirit of God lead into further truth, than they were led into when they went into
<hi>New-England,</hi> and may not the Lord take his own time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it to them, and to lead them into it? So that when firſt it appears, it may be hid from them: and will nothing ſerve them, but the Magiſtrates ſword to cut it down ſo ſoon as ever it appears? Did not the Biſhops of
<hi>England</hi> think theirs to be the Goſpel order, and cryed againſt the non-conformiſts that they could not live peaceably for them, but they diſturbed the order of the Church, and drew mens minds from matters of faith and edification? Surely the deſire of ſuch a kind of peace (as may ſtop the breaking forth of light to the people of God, for their further leading out of <hi>Babylon</hi>) is not good. This is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a fleſhly caſe, than true peace, which the Lord hath not <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115389:29"/> allotted to his people, but they are to wait for the pouring down of his ſpirit, and the opening of the deep myſteries of his life in the latter daies, and to try what comes forth in his name, whether it be of him or no, that they may not loſe the good as it breaks forth, nor be deceived with the evil, as it gets into and appears in the ſhape and likeneſs of the good.</p>
               <p>Now the drift of the argument lies in this, that <hi>this liberty they cannot enjoy, without a non-tolleration of others.</hi> Tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any but themſelves and their own way diſturbs their peace, their faith, their order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The true liberty, the true faith, the true order of the Goſpel was enjoyed formerly, without this power of ſuppreſſing others by carnal weapons, and violent Lawes. Yea this power of ſuppreſſing others, and of compelling to a way of Religion and Worſhip, came up with Antichriſt, and that power which came up with Antichriſt, is not of Chriſt. <hi>The Dragon gave his power to the beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.4. and another beaſt riſeth up with <hi>horns like a Lamb,</hi> ver. 11. and this Beaſt compelleth, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. Mark the beaſt which appeared with horns like a Lamb, as if it had Chriſts power, and maketh fire to come down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on the earth in the ſight of men (and who can deny theſe to be of God, that can do ſuch things) this very beaſt compelleth or cauſeth to worſhip, as, <hi>ver.</hi> 12 So this beaſt which appears like a Lamb, joines with the firſt beaſt whom it had ſet up under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother appearance, and both compel to the worſhipping of an Image of the truth (of ſuch an image of the truth as they think good to advance) and ſo from the truth it ſelf. And he that will not be deceived with their image, with their likeneſs, with that which they call the truth and way of God, or order of the Goſpel, and ſo ſhall refuſe to bow thereto, he ſhall not he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted either to buy or ſell, <hi>ver.</hi>
16, 17. There is no living as men within their bounds, unleſs they will bow to their image. But the true Lamb doth not compel, but calls to wait on the Fathers drawings, till the Father by his ſpirit make willing. And though by the Lamb <hi>Kings Reign, and Princes decree juſtice, (Pro.</hi> 8.15.) yet they never had any commiſſion from him to force men to that way of Religion and worſhip, to which the Spirit of the Lord alone can make them willing, nor to fall upon them becauſe they were unwilling. This is from the Dragon, where ever it is found.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115389:30"/>This then is the great matter of controverſie, you account it your liberty not to tollerate, and here ſtands your peace and Religion (which was a liberty the true Chriſtians never had) and you cannot with patience hear any to teſtifie againſt you: and ſo ye now fall upon any that come to witneſs againſt you, even as ye your ſelves once ſuffered, when ye were witneſſes. But how can ye manifeſt that God ſhall reveal no truth, but what he reveals to you? or if he do, that ye have liberty not to tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate it, or the perſons that hold it forth? Wherefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly, whether this be a right liberty ye have aimed at: for if your aim hath been at a liberty which is not granted of God, at ſuch a liberty as will not ſtand with the liberty of his ſpirit in his people, no marvail though ye have run into indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect means to attain it: and ſo from ſtep to ſtep have been led to the utmoſt degree of violence and perſecution: and being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in it, are now forced to ſeek for arguments to maintain it. This argument is further enforced, by propoſing <hi>the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderableneſs of the Quakers ſuffering of a non-tolleration,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>a manifeſt and greateſt hazard of a tolleration unto the country: Their abſence from hence is no detriment to them, their preſence here threatens no leſs than the ruine of all, to us, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for outward detriment, the <hi>Quakers</hi> do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that in caſes of this nature: but that in them which is born of God, hearing and receiving his command, preſently obeys, waiting for his preſence and power to carry through, and doth not at all mind the hardſhips to be met with. But the inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, ariſing from diſobedience to God is very great, even the loſs of his ſweet preſence, life and power at preſent, beſides the utter hazard of the ſoul: for that which draweth back from obedience to the ſpirit of the Lord, the Lord hath no pleaſure in; &amp; they have known the terrors of the Lord to the diſobedient, therefore they may not pleaſe men in forbearing to go where he ſends them, nor (ſtanding in his counſel and power) do they fear them which can kill the body, but they exceedingly dread the death and loſſe of their Souls, and him who hath the power thereof.</p>
               <p>And as for their <hi>preſence threatning the ruin of all to you,</hi> that's but a miſs apprehenſion. It may indeed be ruine to that part in <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115389:30"/> you, which is wiſe and ſtrong without the preſence of the life of God, but the elect, which is built upon the rock cannot be ruined by any appearance of God, nay nor by any appearance of the powers of darkneſs againſt God, for <hi>the gates of Hell cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt the true Church.</hi> And there is great advantage of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors &amp; hereſies to the true Church, for the life grows and gets ground by a fair tryal &amp; overcoming of them, and the approved are thereby made manifeſt, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. Now what kind of Church is yours, which is in ſuch danger of being ruined by that whereby the true Church was advantaged? So that to plead that either you muſt ſuffer <hi>your Religion, your ſouls, your liberties to be made a prey of,</hi> or take this courſe to defend them, is very inconſequent, and a ſtrong argument againſt you that yours is not the truth, which needs ſuch a defence as the truth hath not been uſed to have, but hath grown up, been preſerved, and thriven not only without it, but againſt the ſtrength and force of it. So likewiſe thoſe conſiderations of the <hi>Shepherds defending the flock from Wolves,</hi> and of the <hi>keeper of the vineyards main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the hedg againſt wild beaſts, &amp;c.</hi> are not proper to the thing in hand: for the ſpiritual ſheep, the ſoul, the liberty of the Church, the true Religion, the true vineyard are not outward, nor to be defended after an outward manner; but the defence is according to the nature of the thing which is to be defended. To truſt, or look after an outward power for defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe, is to betray the faith which is the ſheild. Therefore let them conſider, whether in looking out too much at theſe, they have not loſt the true weapon, and, the ſight of the true thing which is to be defended, which the arme of the Lord alone gathers, and the arme of the Lord alone preſerves.</p>
               <p>This argument is yet further preſſed from the preſent ſtate of your own people, <hi>too many of them being perillouſly diſpoſed</hi> (as ye ſay) <hi>to receive their doctrine, being already too much diſaffected, if not enemies to order, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Alas, alas, have you had your order, your Church government ſo long up, and are the multitude among you yet ſo ready to be ſhaken? Behold what a weak unſtable ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ye have attained to all this time, by your outward force! But ſearch honeſtly, and ſee who they are that are ſo ready to be ſhaken. Are they the <hi>diſcontented and unconſcionable multitude</hi> (as ye ſpeak) or are they the moſt ſimple hearted, moſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115389:31"/> and zealous towards God amongſt you? (for it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced here in Old
<hi>England,</hi> that the ground they gain, is not upon the unconſcionable, but the conſcientious.) If it be theſe that are ſomewhat touched with the ſence of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, it may make you fear that there is more of God therein, than you are aware of. Therefore do not proceed to argue thus violently againſt a thing, before ye have tryed it: but come to a deep, ſerious, inward conſideration of the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and your own ſouls, not in the pride, loftineſs and ſelf willedneſs, but in the honeſty, humility and meekneſs of your Spirits: and then perhaps ye may ſee beauty, and the life of your ſouls in that, which ye now ſo revile and perſecute. And though ye matter not how ye imagine, and ſpeak all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil falſely againſt us, yet do not alſo wrong the beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelves, by tearming them <hi>diſcontented and unconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> becauſe their Spirits are not hardened by your form, but yet retain ſome tenderneſs towards God, his truths and people.</p>
               <p>But why do ye charge following the light within ſo deeply as to be <hi>a giving up of mens ſelves to their own inclinations,</hi> and that it <hi>immediately canonizeth them for Saints, diſchargeth them from ſubjection both Civil and Sacred, and from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as the rule of life, and by vertue of this their Saint-ſhip, intitles them to the eſtates and dignities of all who are not of their minds,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely if ye were guided by the light within, ye would be preſerved from ſuch kind of injuriouſneſs both to perſons and principles. Are your tongues and pens your own, at liberty to ſpeak and write any thing that will make for your advantage, how manifeſtly falſe ſoever? If it were but a natural light, yet being of God, it would not deſerve this deep blame. Have ye ever tryed it, as we have done? if not, why do ye ſpeak ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, before ye have tryed it? We can upon much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teſtifie, that it is againſt our inclinations, that it diſcovers them, calls from them, and is a daily croſs to them; upon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing whereof we feel the bitter dying of the earthly part, and the inclinations thereof pining away. And from true ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to that which truly is of God, it never diſcharges; but leads to obedience to what is lawfully commmanded by authority, &amp; to patient ſuffering under what is unlawfully inflicted. And as <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115389:31"/> for the Scriptures, it opens them in the life which gave them forth, it fulfils them in us, it makes them our own, it makes us able to ſet our ſeal to the truth of them in the ſight of God; and to receive that for the rule, which the Scriptures ſay is the rule, <hi>the living word, Chriſt the living way, the word in the mouth and in the heart,</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>the law in the mind, the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> which is <hi>the word ingrafted</hi> into their hearts, who are created anew in Chriſt. And this is the honour which we give to the Scriptures, namely to receive that which they teſtifie of, to live and walk in that ſpirit; which they call to us to live and walk in; to take heed of painting the old nature, and letting the old ſpirit live upon its imaginations, which it gathers out of the Scriptures, reading them in the old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the letter, and not in the newneſs of the Spirit. And we profeſs nakedly, that we believe the truth of God, not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe the Scripture hath ſaid it (for that which is out of the truth may thus believe) but alſo becauſe in coming to the thing, and receiving the truth as it is in Jeſus, we have found it to be juſt as the Scriptures ſpeak of it. But what do ye ſpeak, as if following the light did intitle men to the eſtates and dignities of all who are not of their mind? Nay, the light teacheth, not to covet, not to deſire earthly dignities or eſtates. Let it be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at over Old <hi>England:</hi> which of us ſo much as mind theſe things? Nay the Lord knows, that the love of theſe things is daily rooted out of our hearts more and more, and we are a people whom the World cannot charge with covetouſneſs or love of the World, wherewith all ſorts of profeſſors hitherto, have been too juſtly chargeable. O Rulers of <hi>New-England,</hi> why do ye thus overturn the cauſe of the innocent? if we were a bad people, yet to lay things ſo notoriouſly falſe to our charge, and to charge that principle in us with it, which powerfully leads us from it, this is not right nor juſtifiable in the ſight of God. Ah take heed of reviling, perſecuting, and ſpeaking all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil againſt us falſely, for his name ſake whom we are called to ſerve, and whom we do ſerve in following and obeying the light of his Spirit in us, which hath led us to the true knowledge of God, and to life and peace with him.</p>
               <p>About the cloſe of this argument, for the further ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, it is ſaid, <hi>Duty is not oppoſite to duty, paſſiveneſs for <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115389:32"/> the truth and activeneſs againſt the enemies of the truth, are both duties in their ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every kind of activeneſs againſt the enemies of the truth, is not duty, for ſome kind is ſinful. There is a lawful fighting, and an unlawful fighting. Such a kind of fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an enemy as may hurt a friend, and cannot hurt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, is unlawful. Now the Magiſtrates ſword may hurt a friend, may affright the tender conſcience from its duty towards Chriſt, but it cannot reach the falſehood which lodgeth in the heart, nor draw the party from that, but rather hardeneth him in it: So that it is not a duty to have the Magiſtrates ſword drawn out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that, for which it is not proper, where it may do hurt and not good. The houſholder would not permit his own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to gather up the tares, leſt they ſhould root up the wheat with them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.29. Did Chriſt deny his Diſciples that liberty, and doth he grant it to the Magiſtrates? Is the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate out of danger of hurting the wheat, while he is ſmiting at the tares: nay is he not in danger of ſmiting and rooting up the wheat inſtead of the tares? Surely this is the Magiſtrates duty, to keep in his place, and not to extend his ſword beyond his commiſſion, and beyond what it is proper for. And let me put this to all the Magiſtrates of the earth, who have been draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their ſword againſt tares (as they might think) <hi>are ye ſure that ye never touched any green thing?</hi> (Revel. 9.4.) <hi>did ye never pluck up any wheat?</hi> ye muſt give an account of this to Chriſt one day. Here in Old <hi>England,</hi> in the Biſhops dayes, the beſt were liable to be excommunicated and weeded out of the Church, and alſo to be ſtruck at by the Magiſtrate: how it hath been in <hi>New-England,</hi> I leave it to your conſciences to conſider of, do not ſlubber it over, but make up a juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. in caſe of blaſphemy, he did by immediate direction from God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. and he was a type of Chriſt, who inwardly and ſpiritually fulfils all his outward ſhadows. And Chriſt doth not ſay that every blaſphemer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel ſhall be put to death, but all blaſphemy or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the ſon of man ſhall be forgiven, but there is a kind of blaſphemy which he will not forgive. And the Church, by his Spirit are to try and deal with blaſphemers, even to the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115389:32"/> of them off by the ſword of the Spirit, that they may repent and <hi>learn not to blaſpheme,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.20. but the Magiſtrace is not now appointed to cut them off in their blaſphemy, and ſo to take away that time of repentance from them, which Chriſt hath allowed them. Chriſts Ordinances and inſtitutions do not claſh one with another, he doth not bid the Church cut off a Perſon from the unity with the ſword of the Spirit, that he might feel the loſs of life, and be made ſenſible of what a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his blaſphemies have brought him to, and ſo come to mourn and repent. I ſay Chriſt doth not do this on the one hand, and on the other other hand bid the Magiſtrate baniſh him, or cut him off with the ſword, and ſo take away his time of repentance from him. Nay this device ſprang from the falſe Church, to make her excommunication outwardly terrible and dreadful, which hath no inward vertue, or cauſe of terror and dread at all in it.</p>
               <p>So as touching <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> he was both extraordinarily ſtirred up by God, and his time was under the law, ſo that the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his example is not valid to them, who have not ſuch a warrant as he had (for he ſaith himſelf, that God had put in his heart what he had to do at
<hi>Jeruſalem, Nehem,</hi> 2.12.) and where the ſtate and miniſtration is changed. The Prieſts did that under the law which is not now to be done, but typified what Chriſt the unchangeable Prieſt was to do: So likewiſe Kings, Judges, and Governors of that People, did that under the law towards them, which is not now to be done outwardly towards any by any King, Ruler, or Magiſtrate, but typified what Chriſt was inwardly to do in the Spirits of his people, and how he would gather, preſerve and defend his Church, and wound and ſubdue his enemies, even by his rod and Scepter, which is the ſword of his Spirit, the word of his mouth.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira's</hi> not ſuffering falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the Woman <hi>Jeſabel;</hi> We do not ſay that any errors, or erronious perſons are to be ſuffered by the Church, but to be dealt with in Chriſts power and authority. But the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of theſe to the ſecular power, we know to have been an invention of Antichriſts, and a great diſhonour to Chriſt (as if his Rod and Scepter were not ſufficient to defend his ſubjects and kingdome, and to beat down his enemies) and alſo a <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115389:33"/> ground of much affliction, perſecution, and bloodſhed of the Saints, yea and of ſuppreſſing the truth of God for a ſeaſon. For the perſecutor having once gotten this cover, then he can do that openly and boldly, which otherwiſe he would bluſh and he aſhamed of. To perſecute Chriſt, to put his people to death, and that for profeſſing and publiſhing his truths, God forbid ſaith the Antichriſtian Spirit (in every form and way of Religion) that we ſhould do this: but in every age calls the witneſſes to the truth (of that age) blaſphemers, wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, perſons that by their tenents overthow the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall truths of the Goſpel, and their Doctrines deſtructive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now what zealous people or Miniſter, or what Chriſtian Magiſtrate can ſuffer ſuch as theſe? By this artifice the ſufferings of the Saints come to abound in every age, and their blood is made havock of: and what is thus done eaſily paſſeth as an act of juſtice againſt offenders, and not, as indeed it is perſecution of the truths and people of God. The after-age can ſee what it is, and cry out againſt it: but ſtill it is the ſubtilty of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Spirit, to hide the perſecutions of the preſent age, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an appearance of zeal for God, and of juſtice againſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the next place it is ſaid on the <hi>Quakers</hi> behalf, that <hi>they are the Lambs of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed this is a conſiderable thing, for if they be Chriſts Lambs then they are innocent, and cannot be the cauſers of their own ſufferings, but that will reſt upon the perſecutors, though they uſe never ſo much art to make the Lambs appear guilty, and themſelves guiltleſs. Their Spirit, Nature, manner of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which is with Lamb-like weapons, which hurt not fleſh and blood) their whole courſe and converſation, and manner of ſuffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> manifeſts them to be Lambs; this is of much more force than a bare ſaying they are Lambs. None of this is mentioned on their behalf, but only that <hi>they ſay they are Lambs.</hi> But let us ſee how fairly that is overthrown.</p>
               <p>Againſt this, that place, <hi>John</hi> 5.31. is alledged,
<hi>If I bear witneſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true:</hi> whereupon it is ſaid thus, <hi>Had not Chriſt been God, the reaſon of the Jews had been good againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doth not the Spirit of God dwell in the Sons of God? <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115389:33"/> and doth not the ſpirit of God bear witneſs in them that they are his Children? and is not this witneſs true? <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>We know that we are of God,</hi> 1 Ioh. 5.19. Was not this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs true in <hi>John,</hi> becauſe <hi>John</hi> was not God. Was not the Prophets teſtimony true (that they were his Prophets, and that God had ſent them, and that it was his meſſage which they brought) becauſe they were not God? Shall the ſpirit of God work wonders in the heart, and ſhall he not teſtifie concerning his own work at his pleaſure? Ah friends, how do ye under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Scriptures, and raiſe inferences from it, thus to condemn the generation of the righteous? Search the Scriptures, do not the Prophets ſtill teſtifie that the Lord ſent them, and that it was his word which they ſpake, though they themſelves were not God: but perſons moved by the ſpirit of God, who ſtirred in his ſervants under the Law, but dwelleth, reſteth, and abideth in his people under the Goſpel, and what he teſtifieth is true, though fleſhly wiſe Iſrael (who ſeem to themſelves very skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Law and letter of the Scriptures) could not receive his teſtimony either then or now. Ah friends, ye had need take heed and conſider, leſt the baſtardly birth in you hath taken up an habitation in the letter, without knowing the mind of the ſpirit, whoſe preſence killeth the carnal part, and ſhutteth out the wiſdome of the fleſh from medling with the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſeem to refer <hi>all to the tryal of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> both <hi>ſtation, doctrine and practiſe:</hi> ſurely if ye had done ſo in truth, ye would have more patiently heard their teſtimony according to the Scriptures. Every man pretendeth Scripture, but none truly honour it, but they who are guided by that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which it teſtifieth of: And they who are not guided by that ſpirit, walk not according to the Scriptures, but according to reaſonings of the fleſhly part, which windeth it ſelf into the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scriptures, that by ſome kind of conformity thereto, it may avoid the dint of the ſpirit. And this is the way of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts revilings, by getting the form, crying up that, winding his own fleſhly ſpirit into that, and ſheltering it ſelf under that. Thus the Jews cryed up the Temple of the Lord, the Sabbath, the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and writings of the Prophets; and under this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, with great zeal perſecuted Chriſt: he was looked upon as a <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115389:34"/> blaſphemer, as one againſt Gods Temple, his Sabbath, his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, &amp;c. And ſince the daies of Chriſt, the Antichriſtian ſpirit ſpeaks great words of Chriſt, his Death, Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, Interceſſion, &amp;c. and of Church-order and diſcipline, that under this cover it may fight againſt the comforter, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, who alone can lead into truth, and which is the proper way of Gods Miniſtration ſince Chriſts aſcention. And this hath been the way of oppoſing truth ever ſince, and ſtill is: and here is the Antichriſt, he that holds theſe in the wrong part, and by theſe fights againſt the true ſpirit.</p>
               <p>But if there be any truth in this, that ye are willing to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Scriptures, let it yet come to a fair tryal this way, and let them have free liberty to manifeſt among you, what they have to ſay from the Scriptures, why your Church, your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, your order and government, your whole way of teaching and worſhip is not of God, nor according to the Scriptures, but an invention and imitation, ſet up in the way of reſemblance of what once was truly ſo. If this cannot be made good againſt you, ye will have much advantage of ſhaming them, and of ſetling your people much firmer than by priſons, whips, cutting off of eares, baniſhment and death, which no mans heart (ſeriouſly conſidering it in true ſoberneſs) can poſſibly believe to be the proper engines of ſetling or preſerving the Goſpel of peace.</p>
               <p>But that the Scripture is the rule of tryal under the Goſpel, I read not in Scripture, but that the things of the ſpirit are to be known in, &amp; by the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of Antichriſts, ſeducers, and erring ſpirits, which were to be tryed, doth not bid them try them by the words which he wrote, or by the other Apoſtles words, or by the Prophets words, but by the anointing, which keeping cloſe to, they need fear no ſeducers, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.26, 27. The word which was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning being received, abode in, and kept cloſe to, tries all words and ſpirits. That which begets to God is the ſpirit; the great gift (which is given to him which is begotten) is the ſpirit; and this (being given) is to become the fountaine of life to the believer, <hi>John</hi>
7.38. And in this ſpring of life he is to live, and receive milk and knowledg, and here he is to walk, and here he is to try all other waters, even by this water. And this is more to a believer, and more enableth him to try, than all the words of <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115389:34"/> truth that ever were written: though he that hath this cannot deſpiſe or undervalue any thing that the ſpirit ever wrote: but yet the ſpirit it ſelf is more to him, and more certain then any words concerning the ſpirit. Men may make falſe gloſſes, and mudd, and make void the Scriptures by their reaſonings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, and traditional apprehenſions: but this water e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver runs freſh &amp; clear, &amp; no foul ſpirit can defile it. <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the Law, which directed to, and ended in Chriſt: Chriſt in the fleſh finiſhed the work which the Father gave him to do, and directed to the comforter to be the leader into all truth, yea the ſpring of life to the believer, and here the believer is ſafe: but the Antichriſtian ſpirit ravening from this, cries up the letter in the ſtead of this, and doth not ſee how the letter points to, and centers in this. <hi>God hath made us able Miniſters of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>not of the letter but of the ſpirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. he overlooked the letter, that was not the thing he was chiefly to miniſter, but the ſpirit, the power, to turn men from darkneſs to light, that they might feel him that is true, and have the life eternal abiding in the heart: But now in the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian darkneſs, the ſpirit being loſt which is the Goſpel-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, now they ſeemingly advance and cry up the letter, putting it into the place of the ſpirit. Yet in truth it is not the Scripture heither, in its naked ſimplicity, which is thus cryed up, but mans wiſe reaſonings about it. The fleſhly will, the fleſhly underſtanding, the fleſhly ſtrength getting a ſeat there, having formed a building out of it, and reared ſtrong holds in that part which can be wiſe and live without the ſpirit; now its life, its intereſt lies in the Scriptures thus believed, thus underſtood, thus practiſed: thus therefore it cries it up, not as it came at firſt out of the hands of the ſpirit, nor as the truth of it is now ſeen in the ſimplicity and nakedneſs of the ſpirit, but as the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from below hath formed meanings and apprehenſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. And here every ſort of men are wiſe in their own eyes, and ſtrong and prudent in their own conceivings and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, but know not the bringing to naught of that underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which precedeth the opening of the eye of the babe, which hath that ſight of the things of God given, which is out of the reach of all the wiſe and ſtrong ones.</p>
               <p>It is true, under the Law, they were to try by the Law and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115389:35"/> teſtimony, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.10. but yet not in an uncertain way, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own gueſſings, imaginations and reaſonings, but according to a certain interpretation and knowledg there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and in caſes of difficulty the Judg was to have recourſe to the Prieſt,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. &amp;c. and the Prieſts in caſes of doubt had an ordinary way of enquiring by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim, Numb.</hi> 27.21. beſides the way of enquiring by Prophets, which was very common with them alſo, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
9.9. and <hi>chap.</hi> 28.6. But now the <hi>Jews</hi> having forfeited theſe, &amp; filling their minds with a gathered knowledge from the Law and Prophets, trying Chriſt and his truths by this, judged amiſs both of him and them. Now the Law was a ſhadow of good things to come, not a ſhadow of another outward Law or rule, but a ſhadow of the inward rule, of the Law of the new Covenant written in the heart, of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit put within,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 8. &amp; by this law is the true believer fully as able to try, as they were by the former: but without this, a Chriſtians tryal of things is not ſo certain, as theirs was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The force of the fourth argument is to this effect,
<hi>that the dictate of conſcience is not a ſucffiient plea in caſe of meer and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ignorance, much leſs in wilful and affected ignorance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The dictate of conſcience is not made a plea by us, but the anſwering and obeying the light of Chriſt in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, is that which keepeth them void of offence both towards God and towards men. Now it is one thing for a man to act evil, and plead it is his conſcience, and it is another thing for a man to be guided by the infallible light of the ſpirit, or if he be not come ſo far, yet to be made tender in his heart towards Chriſt concerning his practiſes in Religion. In this laſt caſe we ſay, that in things whoſe good or evil chiefly depends upon the knowledge and perſwaſion of the mind, which Chriſt alone can do, here Chriſt is the ſole Lord and Judg of the conſcience, <hi>Rom.</hi>
14.4. and not either Miniſter, Church or Magiſtrate. Chriſt giveth knowledge, Chriſt increaſeth knowledge, and Chriſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth obedience according to the knowledge given or increaſed. That is many times required to be left, upon a further degree of knowledge given, which was not required to be left before: and ſo alſo upon the ſame terms may things be required to be performed, which were not required to be done before. <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115389:35"/> And this indeed is the very ſum of the true Religion (ſince the death of Chriſt, and his finiſhing of his work here) either to worſhip in the Spirit, or to wait for the Spirit. He who hath not received the Spirit, he is to wait for the Spirit. He who hath received the Spirit, he is to wait in the Spirit for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and outgoings thereof, and to be obedient thereto. And Chriſtians are to take heed, not only of a wrong Spirit, but alſo of quenching the movings of the true Spirit in themſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If the erring mind hath miſtaken about worſhip, and through its miſtake ſet up a wrong way, the Spirit in the tender plants will be moving againſt it, which the wiſe reaſoning fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part will be knocking down, and ſo the birth which is after the fleſh will be getting advantage of perſecuting and keeping under the immortal ſeed. Now ſuppreſs evil to the utmoſt, but take heed of quenching the good in any; take heed how ye ſtop that in its courſe of diſcovering evil (in your worſhips; or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) which eaſily paſſeth for good, until the Spirit begin to make it manifeſt. Ah friends, if the carnal wiſdome had been crucified in you, and the Spirit of God had had more ſcope in manifeſting evil among you, what might ye have grown to ere this day? but if the Magiſtrate upon every doubt, or diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or ſtartling of the tender conſcience, ſtep in with his ſword, how is the way of the breaking forth of truth ſtopped up? and that which is truly of God, and moſt tender towards him, is moſt liable to ſuffer this way. And this is that which makes the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſuch a ſuffering people, becauſe they have found the benefit of keeping the conſcience tender towards God, and ſo prize it above all things: and this mercy have they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Lord, ſenſibly to diſtinguiſh (in this tenderneſs towards God, and in the fear of his name) between the dictates of conſcience, and the voyce of his Spirit there. Now it is not at all pleaded by us, that under a pretence of conſcience, ye ſhould ſuffer all manner or any manner of evil: but firſt, <hi>Puniſh not good for evil:</hi> do not puniſh the good in others, to defend the evil in your ſelves. Secondly, <hi>That which is manifeſtly evil; puniſh it by ſuch hands and means as God hath appointed,</hi> the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual by ſpiritual, the temporal by temporal, and do not make puniſhing of evil a pretence of perſecuting good in others, and of upholding the evil in your ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115389:36"/>But as touching your diſtinction of meer and ſingle ignorance, or wilful and affected, we can bleſs the Lord who hath delivered us from them both, by the day-ſpring which he hath cauſed to ariſe in our hearts; and we can with a farther meaſure of the ſame Spirit bear this from you, with a meaſure whereof ſome of the non-conformiſts bore this from the conformiſts, who would caſt this upon them, that their ignorance was affected, they were refractory, but might have been better informed, if they would. And we wiſh with all our hearts, that there were not too juſt cauſe of retorting both parts of this diſtinction back upon you: for if ye had not been very groſly ignorant, ye could never have thus put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, caſting ſuch odious reproaches upon the truth, to make it appear what it was not: had ye not been ignorant of the Scriptures, ye would have known the movings of the life and ſpirit of it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but through ignorance of the eternal power, &amp; from your dark reaſonings and conceivings about the letter, ye are ready to call Chriſt <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> not knowing the anointing in the members, no more than the Scribes and Phariſees did in the head. And had not your ignorance alſo been too much affected, ye would have took more pains about the tryal, and not have run into ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes all along, both about them and their Doctrines, as ye have done.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt referred himſelf either to <hi>Pilates,</hi> or the <hi>Jews</hi> try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of him by Scriptures, is a groſs miſtake at beſt. The Jews did try him by Scriptures, and according to their underſtanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, found him a Sabbath breaker, againſt
<hi>Moſes</hi> Law, and that he could not be the <hi>Meſſiah (Joh.</hi>
7.27. and 52. and <hi>chap.</hi> 12.34.) but by their law ought to die,
<hi>John.</hi> 19.7. There is no trying of the things of God by conſidering of Scriptures in the carnal mind, in the wiſe reaſoning part: but in the Spirit which wrote the Scriptures, in the underſtanding which God gives, (1
<hi>John</hi> 5.20.) in the wiſdome which is beſtowed on the babe (who lives in the ſimplicity and pure innocency that is in Chriſt) there the truth it ſelf, and alſo the Scriptures (which teſtifie of it) are clear. Now Chriſt did not refer himſelf to them to be tryed by the Scriptures (for he knew what was in man, and he knew after what manner they would try him thereby:) but he bid them <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> which teſtified of him, that ſo they <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115389:36"/> might come to know and receive him,
<hi>John</hi> 5.39, 40. and none knew him, but thoſe to whom the Father revealed him.</p>
               <p>So the caſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> appealing to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> doth not prove that <hi>Ceſar</hi> was a proper judge in caſes of Conſcience: but he was at that time a proper defence againſt the malice of the Jews, who moſt unconſcionably perſecuted <hi>Paul</hi> under a pretence of zeal for God, and defence of their Church and Ordinances. And were ye not in power, but an equal Heathen Magiſtrate over us both, the
<hi>Quakers</hi> durſt refer their cauſe to tryal, that they have done you no injury, no more than <hi>Paul</hi> did the <hi>Jews.</hi> Indeed
<hi>Paul</hi> preached that, which was the end of the law, and the overturning of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſtate: and if their Prieſts and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers had had him to judge, they would have made him as great an offender, as ye now make the
<hi>Quakers.</hi> Now if your reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſtand upon ſuch a bottome as theirs did, and not upon the rock, in the faith, and by the Spirit, ye may well fear us, it is not without a cauſe: for this we certainly know, that all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of God and of Chriſt, imitations and practiſes from the letter, which ſtand in mans will and wiſdome, will not be able to abide the breath of this ſuffering ſeed, who love the teſtimony of Jeſus and ſervice to his name above their lives.</p>
               <p>And as for an <hi>erring conſcience,</hi> there lies the diſpute, whoſe conſcience errs, yours or theirs. Ye ſay they have erred from the letter, the Order, and Ordinances of the Goſpel: they ſay ye have erred from the Spirit, and therefore muſt needs have erred from the letter alſo (and this they are ready to prove ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, if ye dare ſtand to a fair tryal.) and alſo that ye are in a knowledge, faith, worſhip, wiſdome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſtands in the will and carnal part, and keeps the carnal part alive. This deſerves a meek and ſerious conſideration, in the fear of him who can deſtroy the ſoul, and not ſuch a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and fiery tryal, as your proceedings and writings too much ſavour of.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>That a regular defence of the truth by the Godly Orthodox Magiſtrate and others reſpectively, is not perſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To bring the ſword of the Magiſtrate into the work of Chriſts Spirit and power, this is irregular: and it doth execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion irregularly, cutting down the perſon, and not the ſin; whereas the ſword of the Spirit cuts down the ſin, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115389:37"/> may be ſaved. Chriſt came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave: and if any man receive him not or ſpeak againſt him, he calls not for fire from Heaven, or for a Magiſtrates ſword, but waits to be gratious, and by the power of his Spirit (having once convinced and gathered) doth he defend his truths and people. Let but the Magiſtrate ſtand ſtill with his ſword, the Spirit of Chriſt will ſoon get the victory over error, and a ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better victory than the Magiſtrates ſword can effect. Truth ſprang up without the Magiſtrates ſword, yea againſt it; ſo it grew, ſo it conquered. The Magiſtrates ſword here (though never ſo favourable to truth) doth more hurt than good, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the true ſword out of its place, and keeping down that tenderneſs of Spirit wherein the truth alone can ſpring.</p>
               <p>That coercion was inſtituted for reſtraining of evil, we grant (this is the ſame with the firſt argument) but he that appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two kinds of coercion, ſet each their limits, which they are not to tranſgreſs. See Anſwer to the firſt argument.</p>
               <p>But whereas ye ſay that <hi>tares and ill weeds need no more than being let alone to overrun and ſpoil the corn.</hi> That is directly contrary to Chriſt, who ſaid expreſly, <hi>let both grow together until the harveſt.</hi> Mat. 13.30. Sure he would not have his wheat in danger of being deſtroyed all the time till harveſt: but he judged, that plucking up the tares would more indanger the wheat, than letting them alone,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 29. Man may eaſily mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and pluck up an ear of wheat, inſtead of a tare: and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it were to let many tares alone, than pluck up one ear of wheat. Ye have long been buſied in <hi>New-England</hi> about pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of tares, are ye ſure ye never plucked up any wheat? nay have ye not weeded out the wheat, and left the tares ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Undertaking a work ſo directly contrary to Chriſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (and ſo without the guidance of his Spirit) ye might eaſily thus err. Now what the tares are, is afterwards expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they are ſuch perſons which grow among the wheat, but are not wheat, but are to be gathered from the wheat with Chriſts ſickle, and bound up in bundles for the burning in the day of his harveſt.</p>
               <p>Your compariſons of a <hi>Gangreen</hi> and the like, I wiſh ye knew how to apply, The power of Gods truth in the Spirits of his people is no <hi>Gangreen:</hi> but the form without the power is a <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115389:37"/> Gangreen, &amp; like <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> lean cattle ſoon eats up the fat. And he who hath loſt his own tenderneſs and freſhneſs, ſoon turns perſecutor of ſuch as remain tender, and ſeek to preſerve their freſhneſs.</p>
               <p>In the daies of the Apoſtles there was <hi>a King in Iſrael,</hi> then the Church was well governed, in the meekneſs and ſweet autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power of Chriſts ſpirit, which hurts not creatures, but ſtrikes at Chriſts enemy in creatures. Since that time the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> have had a long day of doing what was right in their eyes, the <hi>Epiſcoparians</hi> a day after them of doing what was right in their eyes, and ſo the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> &amp;c. but it were better for them all to lament after the right King, than to ſet up an uſurped authority in his abſence. Carnal reaſon, the wiſdome of the fleſh hath got his ſeat, giving forth its meanings of Scripture, and ſo (under a colour of them) ruling over his fleſh with force and cruelty, and not with the meek, gentle, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcepter of his ſpirit, which alone is appointed of Chriſt to govern them.</p>
               <p>So then the Magiſtrates puniſhing of the <hi>Quakers</hi> is not regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by any inſtitution of Chriſt, but only by a Law of their own making, as it is further explained. <hi>p.</hi> 95. of this Appendix, the grounds whereof hath been already examined, and found inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to warrant them therein, which I leave to themſelves and to every mans conſcience to conſider of in the dread of God, the Judg of all.</p>
               <p>Upon the reſult of all, it may not be amiſs to ſtate the caſe between the Governours of <hi>New-England</hi> and the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which is briefly thus.</p>
               <p>If the Governours of <hi>New-England</hi> had juſt cauſe to make ſuch a Law againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and had a true rightly derived power ſo to do from God (who is the ſpring of all juſt power:) and if the <hi>Quakers</hi> had liberty from the Lord to chuſe or refuſe obedience to it, then their ſuffering death is juſtly to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to themſelves.</p>
               <p>But if the Governours of <hi>New-England</hi> had not a juſt cauſe of making this law, nor authority and power from God ſo to do: and that the <hi>Quakers</hi> had not liberty to chuſe or refuſe coming thither, but had an indeſpenſible command from Chriſt their Lord; then their ſufferings and blood will reſt on the <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115389:38"/> heads of the Governours of <hi>New-England,</hi> and will ſtick cloſer to them, than to be wiped off by ſuch kind of arguments and reaſonings.</p>
               <p>All depends upon your firſt ſtep of proceeding. If that was without due ground, not in the fear of the Lord, without Chriſts allowance &amp; direction, without having duly weighed the thing in the true unerring ballance, but rather in the haſtineſs and ſtiff reſolvedneſs of the fleſh: then all your proceedings ſince, have been but aggravations of your ſin; and God might juſtly let you go on thus far, to ſhame you evenin the ſight of the very heathen, among whom the ſenſe and abhorrence of this cruel and bloody ſpirit, cannot but make your profeſſion of of the Goſpel of peace become a reproach.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Quakers</hi> came to you in the name of the Lord, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from him to you the evil of your waies, to convince you by his light, of your departing from that ſpirit which was perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in you in the times of your ſufferings in old <hi>England:</hi> but ye would not meekly hear and conſider of what they had to ſay to you from the Lord, but preſently impriſoned and ſent them away, and ſo proceeded further and further againſt them, till at length ye came to drink their blood. So that in truth their teſtimony is the cauſe of their death, and judg in your own hearts whether this be not perſecution of a deep dye. It were better for you to charge it upon your own hearts, then to have the Lord charge it upon you, when ye come to ſtand before him to be eternally judged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>There remains yet an other Paper (printed here in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) <hi>called,</hi> A true Relation of the proceedings againſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Quakers, at the general Courts of the Maſſathuſets, holden at
<hi>Boſton</hi> in New-England, <hi>October 18. 1659.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Arguments therein, whereupon they would have their proceedings paſs for juſt, and not be accounted Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, are theſe, <hi>The authority of this Court; the Laws of the Country, the Law of God, and their gradual proceedings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Perſecutors are very ſeldom (if at any time) without <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115389:38"/> theſe pleas for themſelves. Had not the Biſhops as fair a right to this plea, to cover their perſecutions of the non-conformiſts with? Could not they in their day have alledged the authority of their Courts, the Laws of their Country, (perhaps ſome not made directly to intrap neither, as yours were) and had not they as confident a pretence to the Law of God as theſe? and did they not alſo proceed gradually? He that doubteth let him read <hi>Hookers</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Policy, and other writings of the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and ſee whether their ſpirit was not more mild &amp; Chriſtian like, and their arguments more weighty by far, then thoſe which theſe have uſed againſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi> Nay have the very Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves been without theſe arguments? Did they not proceed gradually in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> daies againſt the Martyrs? yea what pains did they take to convince them of their Hereſies, and to bring them into the unity of the true Church, as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it? But theſe arguments did not juſtifie the Papiſts, or conformiſts in the ſight of God (though they might juſtifie their proceedings in the eyes of their own party) nor will they juſtifie them who have gone one ſtep beyond the conformiſts. But as the ſpirit of perſecution, entring into the Biſhops and conformiſts, was the ſame ſpirit, as well when it was in them, as in the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> ſo the ſame ſpirit entring into the non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, is the ſame ſpirit ſtill in them, as it was in the Biſhops and conformiſts. And the plea of the authority of their Court, the Laws of the country, with ſuch a kind of pretence to the Law of God, and their gradual proceeding, is no more in truth and reality a ſhelter for them, then it was for the other; though they in their day look upon it as a good &amp; ſufficient cover, even as the Biſhops did in their day, &amp; the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> in their day. Had they wanted this cover, the nakedneſs of their zeal &amp; profeſſion would have appeared to every eye: yea their own conſciences could not but have flown in their faces, had they put them to death ſo ſoon as ever they had come over without any foregoing proceedings: but this is the nature of the perſecuting ſpirit, firſt it ſeeks a cover to ſtop the mouth of its own conſcience, and to hide its blood-thirſty actions from the eye of the world, and then its feet are ſwift to ſhed the blood of the innocent. But the ſame Lord God of truth and righteouſneſs who hath unmasked the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and unmasked the Biſhops, will unmask theſe alſo, and their <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115389:39"/> nakedneſs ſhall more appear than the others, who would hide themſelves and their own cruelty with that covering, which they themſelves have judged in others. It is not therefore any of theſe, but the grounds of their proceedings muſt manifeſt them to be juſt, or elſe notwithſtanding the pretence to juſtice, their whole courſe of proceedings will prove in truth (and according to righteous judgment) but perſecution.</p>
               <p>Now the grounds of their proceedings they mention to be theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Their having received intelligence from good hands from</hi> Barbadoes <hi>and</hi> England <hi>of the pernicious opinions and practiſes of the</hi> Quakers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Their profeſſed Tenents</hi> (how well ye have acquitted your ſelves herein, let all that fear God judge.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Their turbulent and contemptuous behaviour to authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Their deſigns to undermine and ruin the order and peace here eſtabliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that is willing to receive, ſhall never want intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence againſt the truths and people of God, even from ſuch hands as he will be ready to call good (it is a remnant only that receive truth, the generality of profeſſors in all ages are ſtill rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy both to ſend and receive intelligence againſt all the living ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of it, and of Gods witneſſes to it.) Nor can he who hath already entertained prejudices, ever want matter againſt their tenents, or behaviour; or to charge them with deſigns. Have not theſe reproaches alwaies been caſt upon every appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God? Are not the veſſels he chuſes to hold forth his truths by, ſtill repreſented as perſons of pernicious opinions and practiſes, and their tenents charged to be wicked, and they looked upon as turbulent and contemptuous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Were not the non-conformiſts themſelves looked upon as perſons that would undermine and ruin the order and peace of the Church, who for ſuch trivial things would make ſuch great rents and breaches, marring the beauty and diſturbing the unity, order and peace of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> (ſure they cannot yet forget this, beſides that common charge againſt them of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy againſt authority.) Theſe are but the old weapons of the old Serpent (only a little new furbiſhed by you for your own uſe) even the weapons which the Biſhops wreſted out of the hands of the Papiſts, and which ye have wreſted out of the <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115389:39"/> hands of the Biſhops, and they are no better in your hands, than they were in theirs. They were good in their hands, ſo long as they had authority to make them forcible; and they have no more vertue in your hands, than what outward autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power adds to them. <hi>England</hi> was once overflown with this floud of reproaches, but now at length (this afflicted people waiting in patience on the Lords will) they have much vaniſhed (the earth helping the woman:) and perſons general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (who are any whit ſober, and come to conſider things in fear and meekneſs) find no ſuch matter againſt them, no ſuch opinions or practiſes, or tenents, but the truths of God recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and held forth in his fear, their carriage and behaviour meek and humble, void of turbulency and contempt towards any, and they freer from deſigns againſt authority and orderly govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than any ſort elſe whatſoever. This is well known in <hi>England,</hi> and it cannot be denyed by the authorities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers therof, how we have ſtill been like lambs, ſuffering from all, not contriving or ſo much as deſiring the hurt of any. The Lord knows the deſire of our ſouls to be after truth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and our expectations for the eſtabliſhing thereof to be fixed on him alone, and not on any perſons whatſoever, but as he pleaſeth to appear in them, and work by them: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever happens in the mean time, is received as from his hand, who ruleth on high over all: ſo that our ſpirits do not ſo much as riſe againſt any authorities or inſtruments that perſecute us, but we wait on the Lord our God to advantage his truth, and bring about good to us thereby; and we pity and pray for all who know not what they do, bleſſing the Lord our God, who accounteth us worthy to ſuffer for his names ſake, in bearing teſtimony at his command to any, though it ſhould be but the leaſt of his truths. Therefore take heed of going on in the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your hearts, but know what a people (in the juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon you) your lot hath been to perſecute, whoſe blood will ſtick the cloſer to you, and lie ſo much the heavier upon you, by how much the dearer they are to God.</p>
               <p>And though ye plead <hi>the ſafety of the People</hi> as being
<hi>the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Law,</hi> yet the Lord God knows whether ye have aimed at the ſafety of the People among you in uprightneſs of heart, or whether ye bring this in alſo as a further cover. There is a <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115389:40"/> double ſafety the People may juſtly challenge from you. Firſt, <hi>the ſafety of their Conſciences in a tender ſearching after truth, and further removing out of Babylon.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the ſafety of their eſtates, perſons, and liberties in this ſearch.</hi> They did not fly from
<hi>England</hi> to be perſecuted by the prevailing part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, but to enjoy freedome of conſcience in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after the Lord, his truth and way of worſhip, and not to be tyed and bound up in a form, exalted and eſtabliſhed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinions and reſult of the reaſonings of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part. Now whether ye have preſerved theſe Liberties for them, and really ſought their ſafety, or whether ye have perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted or made a prey of them for their Conſcience ſake (beyond whatever was done to you here in <hi>England,</hi> or beyond what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they had been like to ſuffer, had they ſtaid here in <hi>England</hi>) the Lord in his day will righteouſly judge. Ye have judged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Cattle and Cattle, the Lord alſo will judge between Cattle and Cattle: and in that day ye will ſee, that as his choice have been your outcaſts, ſo your choice is rejected by him; and that as his ſpirit is the abomination of your eyes, ſo your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal way of worſhip is the loathing of his ſoul. O that ye had eyes to ſee it, that your hearts might not be utterly hardned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, his truths and people, even to your utter and eternal deſtruction. Little do ye ſee, poor deceived hearts, what a narrow ſtep there is between you and the pit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115389:40"/>
            <head>THE Authority and Government which Chriſt excluded out of his Church, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATT. 20.</hi> verſ. <hi>25. to 29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>But Jeſus called them unto him and ſaid, ye know that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great, exerciſe authority upon them. But it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will be great among you; let him be your Miniſter: And whoſoever will be chief among you, let him be your ſervant. Even as the Son of man came not to be miniſtred unto, but to miniſter, and to give his life a ranſome for many. And as they departed from Jericho, a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude followed him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HEre Chriſt cuts off that power and authority, which grows up in the corrupt nature of man, which was ever and anon ſpringing up even in the Diſciples, here he wholly excludes it out of his Church, and ſayes expreſly he would have no ſuch thing among them, no ſuch kind of greatneſs, no ſuch kind of authority. Among the Gentiles there are great ones, there are Princes: and theſe great ones, theſe Princes, they Lord it over the inferiour ones, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing authority and dominion over them,
<hi>but it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gentile-ſtate was a ſhadow, even as the Jews ſtate was a ſhadow. The one of death, the other of life; the one of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the other of light. The one was the Image of Satan the Prince of Wickedneſs, the other of Chriſt the Prince of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Peace. They were both vails, under which the two Kingdoms were hid.</p>
            <p>Now in this Gentile-ſtate there were Nations, Princes, Laws, Governments, Dominions, Authorities, &amp;c. but all in the fall,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115389:41"/> all in the darkneſs, all in the tranſgreſſion from the life. The whole ſtate was corrupt, and there muſt be no imitation from hence, no likeneſs of any ſuch thing in the Kingdome of Chriſt, no ſuch kind of Law, no ſuch kind of Government, no ſuch kind of Authority, no ſuch kind of anger with perſons that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, no ſuch kind of dealing with any, no ſuch kind of detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or hurt to any. <hi>There is nothing to hurt in the Mountain of Gods holineſs;</hi> but there is a righteous Scepter, a ſweet Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a ſpiritual Scepter, which reacheth the Spirit in the power of life, but toucheth not the outward man.</p>
            <p>Two things are here excluded by Chriſt, from whence all the miſchief ariſeth in the Church (all the tyranny and oppreſſion of mens conſciences, and of their perſons, eſtates, and liberties for conſcience ſake) firſt, <hi>greatneſs;</hi> ſecondly, the
<hi>exerciſing do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and authority</hi> by thoſe that would be great therein.</p>
            <p>Such a kind of greatneſs as is in the world, its the deſtruction of the life of Chriſt; and ſuch a kind of dominion and authority as is among the Nations, is the direct overturning of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt. It ſets up another power than Chriſts, another greatneſs than Chriſts, another kind of authority than Chriſts; and ſo it eats out the vertue and life of his Kingdom, and makes it juſt like one of the Kingdoms of this World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> This Spirit muſt be kept out from among you; This aſpiring Spirit, this lofty ruling Spirit, which loves to be great, which loves to have dominion, which would exalt it ſelf, becauſe of the gifts it hath received, and would bring others into ſubjection, this ſpirit muſt be ſubdued, amongſt Chriſts Diſciples, or it will ruin all. The Lord gives grace and knowledge for another end, then for men to take upon them to be great, and rule over others becauſe of it. And he that becauſe of this, thinks himſelf fit to rule over other mens Conſciences, and to make them bow to what he knows or takes to be truth, he loſeth his own life hereby; and ſo far as he prevails upon others, he doth but deſtroy their life too: For it is not ſo much ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true things that doth good, as ſpeaking them from the pure, and conveying them to the pure: for the life runs along from the veſſel of life in one, into the veſſel of life in another; and the words (though never ſo true) cannot convey life to another, but as the living veſſel opens in the one, and is opened in the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115389:41"/>Queſt. <hi>But how ſhall this ſpirit be kept out, or kept down, that it may not hurt the diſciple in whom it ariſeth: or if it do, that the hurt may remain to himſelf, and may not prejudice the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When this ſpirit begins to ariſe up in any, ſo ſoon as ever he perceives it, in that that diſcovers it he is to fight againſt it: laying himſelf ſo much the lower, by how much he finds this evil ſpirit raiſing him up. He is to hearken to that which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the Croſs to it, and ſo to come down and ſubject himſelf in ſerving and miniſtring to thoſe who are little in his eyes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of reigning over them, let him lye beneath them. Let him watch and know the life even in the meaneſt, and ſerve it: for that is his place. That which would rule is to ſerve: that which would be great is to be little: and the little one is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Nation. That which is low, is to riſe, and thou art not fit to riſe with it, further than thou canſt ſerve it, both in thy ſelf and others. Therefore if ever thou beeſt aſpiring, if ever thou have a minde to rule, if ever thou think thy ſelf fit to teach, becauſe of what thou haſt received: ſink down, lye low, take up the Croſs to that proud ſpirit, make it bend and ſerve, let the life in every one riſe over it, and trample upon it: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that in thee may ariſe which is fit to teach, yea and to rule in the Lord: and ſo long as that hath the dominion, thou maiſt be ſerviceable to the Lord and to his truth and people: but if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the other get up again, thou muſt preſently come down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or the wrong ſpirit will get dominion over thee, which with force and cruelty will rule over the life both in thy ſelf and others. Thus if a man be faithful to Chriſt, this evil aſpiring ſpirit at its firſt appearance may be dealt with, and kept down: but if it be cheriſhed, given way to, and once let up, it will be hard bringing of it down afterwards. Therefore the diſciples, or the Church of Chriſt, they are to watch over every ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to beat it down, to teſtifie againſt it, to turn from it, to lay it flat, to put it in its proper place, that is beneath all, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to all, and ſo not to ſuffer it to riſe, ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>Let him be your Miniſter.</hi> This is his place, this is his work, by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt. He that would be great, he that would rule, let him miniſter. Own him there; if he will lye low there, if he will be faithful there, ye may have unity with him. But in that his aſpiring temper, in his ruling, in his teaching by what he <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115389:42"/> hath gained, or what hath been given to him formerly (if out of the preſent life) he is to be denyed and turned from.</p>
            <p>If this rule of Chriſts had been kept to, Antichriſts power could never have got up: nor the poor innocent Lambs ſo often have been worried by the wolves. Ah poor hearts, how ſimply do they come thither, where they once taſted refreſhment to find wholſome advice, not ſuſpecting what is got up there ſince, but give the dominion to a wrong thing, and ſo take directions from a wrong ſpirit, and betray their own ſimplicity.</p>
            <p>Chriſt urgeth this upon his diſciples from his own pattern,
<hi>even as the Son of man came not to be miniſtred unto, but &amp;c.</hi> ver. 28. If any had right to be great, ſurely Chriſt; it any had right to exerciſe authority, ſurely Chriſt. If any was to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced becauſe of any gift received, or becauſe of any preſence of the ſpirit with him, ſurely Chriſt. Yet Chriſt took not upon him this kind of greatneſs, nor did exerciſe this kind of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But he was a ſervant, he made uſe of the gift of the ſpirit, of the power of life wherewith the Father filled him, to miniſter and ſerve with. He did never Lord it over the conſciences of any of his diſciples, but did bear with them, and pitty them in their infirmities (<hi>what can ye not watch with me one hour? The ſpirit</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is willing, but the fleſh is weak</hi>) He did not hold forth to them what ever he knew to be truth, requiring them to believe it: but was content with them in their ſtate, and waited till their capacities were enlarged, being ſtill ſatisfied with the honeſty and integrity of their hearts in their preſent ſtate of weakneſs. Nor did he ſtrive to reign over the world, or call for fire from heaven, when they would not receive him, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs indignation when they deſired him to depart out of their coaſts, or pray for twelve Legions of Angels when they came to betray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, and moſt unrighteouſly ſought his life: but the life he had received of his Father, he gave up as a ranſom for his diſciples, yea and for his enemies. Mark, he did not make uſe of what was given him, to raiſe himſelf up above others, to make his word to ſtand for a Law and be received, but he waited till that was opened in his diſciples and in people which was able to receive his teſtimony; and he made uſe of his power of life, and the fulneſs of the ſpirit to inable him the more abundantly to ſerve, and to wait in patience for the fulfilling of the will of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115389:42"/> the Father. And though Iſrael was not gathered by him, yet was he meek, and patient, and at reſt in the will of him that ſent him, and inſtead of reigning over all, could ſerve all, and give that life (whoſe due it was to reign) <hi>a ranſom for many,</hi> ver. 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His kingdom was not of this world,</hi> nor did he ſeek any great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or authority according to this world, neither over the Jews, nor over the Gentiles, nor over his own diſciples; but he ſerved all, he ſought the good of all: the life in him which was to reign over all, yet here ſerved all, ſuffered for all, and from all, and that was his way to his crown, who having finiſhed his courſe, fulfilled his ſervice, perfected his ſufferings, is ſit down on the right hand of the Majeſty on high, where now he reigns over all, and is made a King by God in righteouſneſs. And this is the pattern, which all his diſciples are to walk by. The more life they receive, the more they are to miniſter, the more they are to ſerve. They muſt not lift up themſelves by their gifts, they muſt not hereupon Lord it over others, or hold forth their knowledge or doctrines, and think to make others bow thereto; but wait in their ſervice, till the Lord make way into mens hearts, and plant his truth there: and upon him alſo muſt they wait for the watering and growth of it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is there to be no greatneſs, no authority among the diſciples of Jeſus, or in the Church of Chriſt? Is every one to do what he will, to be ſubject to his own fancies and imaginations, to the inventions of his own corrupt heart? what a confuſed building will this be? Sure this will not long remain a</hi> Zion, <hi>but ſoon become a</hi> Babylon, <hi>even an heap of diſorder and confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is to be no ſuch kind of greatneſs, no ſuch kind of authority. Yet there is both a greatneſs and authority ſuitable to the ſtate of diſciples, ſuitable to that kind of kingdome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are. There are Laws, there are Governments, there are Governors, there is ruling, and there is ſubjection, but all in the ſpirit, all ſuitable to that which is to bo governed: but no government of or according to the fleſh. As Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this world, ſo the government of his Church and people is not according to this world, but as that which gathers is his ſpirit, and that which is gathered is ſpiritual: ſo that which is governed is the ſpirits of his people, and they are to be governed by his ſpirit and ſpiritually, and not after a fleſhly manner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115389:43"/>Thus Chriſt himſelf, though he miniſtred to his diſciples, yet he alſo was their Lord and Maſter, and in the ſpirit and life of the Father ruled over them; and thus the Apoſtles and other miniſters of Chriſt had likewiſe in the ſpirit, the care of the Churches, and authority in the Lord, by his ſpirit to govern the ſpirits of his people: not to govern after a fleſhly manner, by their own wills, not to preſcribe them in a Lordly way either what they ſhould believe or practiſe, but in the light and in the power of the ſpirit to make their way into every ones conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the ſight of God, miniſtring to every one in the ſpirit according to their capacity and growth, and waiting patiently for God to convey the food and nouriſhment, and to build their ſpirits up in the faith thereby,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spirit of the Prophets is ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> Here is the government, here is the law of rule and ſubjection in the life. Every one feeling a meaſure of the Spirit in himſelf, is thereby taught to own and ſubject to a greater meaſure of the ſame Spirit in another. He that hath no meaſure of the Spirit of God, he is not of God, he is none of Chriſts: and he that hath received a meaſure of the Spirit, in the ſame ſpirit feeleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers meaſure, and owneth it in its place and ſervice, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth its moving, and cannot quench it, but giveth way to it with joy and delight. When the Spirit moves in any one to ſpeak, the ſame ſpirit moves in the other to be ſubject and give way: and ſo every one keeping to his own meaſure in the ſpirit, here can be no diſorder, but true ſubjection of every ſpirit: and where this is wanting, it cannot be ſupplyed by any outward rule, or order ſet up in the Church by common conſent: for that is fleſhly, and lets in the fleſh, and deſtroyes the true order, rule, and ſubjection.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, come from Chriſt with a meſſage of life and ſalvation, with a teſtimony concerning the good will of God and his love to mankind, pointing out the way from death to life, from bondage to liberty, from wrath and deſtruction to peace and ſalvation. What they have ſeen, what they have felt, what they have taſted, what they have handled, what they have found redeem and deliver them, that they declare abroad to others, as they are moved, as they are ſent, as they are guided and aſſiſted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115389:43"/>Now that which they preach to, is mens conſciences in the ſight of God. They open the truth which they know, they give their teſtimony in the moving, leading, and power of the Spirit, and they leave it to the ſame ſpirit, to demonſtrate it to mens conſciences, as it pleaſeth. They are nothing, they can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they cannot convert any man to God; but the power that ſpeaketh by them, the ſame power worketh in other mens conſciences at its pleaſure. And here is the beginning of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſt in the heart, when his truth carries convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with it to the conſcience, and the conſcience is drawn to yeild it ſelf up to him, then he layes his yoak upon it, and takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the guiding of it: he cheriſheth it, he cleanſeth it, he comforteth it, he ordereth it at his pleaſure: and he alone pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth it pure, chaſt, gentle, meek, and plyable to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of his Spirit. And as the conſcience is kept ſingle and tender to Chriſt, ſo his government increaſes therein: but as it becomes hard, or ſubject to mens wills, ſo another ſpirit gets dominion over it.</p>
            <p>Therefore the great work of the Miniſter of Chriſt, is to keep the conſcience open to Chriſt, and to preſerve men from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any truths of Chriſt as from them, further than the ſpirit opens, or to imitate any of their practiſes, further than the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit leads, guides, and perſwades them. For perſons are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding prone to receive things as truths, from thoſe whom they have an high opinion of, and to imitate their practiſes; and ſo hurt their own growth, and indanger their ſouls. For if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a truth, before the Lord by his ſpirit make it manifeſt to me, I looſe my guide, and follow but the counſel of the fleſh, which is exceeding greedy of receiving truths, and running into Religious practiſes without the ſpirit. Therefore the main thing in religion, is to keep the conſcience pure to the Lord, to know the guide, to follow the guide, to receive from him that light whereby I am to walk; and not to take things for truths, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others ſee them to be truths, but to wait till the ſpirit make them manifeſt to me: nor to run into worſhips, duties, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, or practiſes, becauſe others are led thither, but to wait till the ſpirit lead me thither. <hi>He that makes haſt to be rich</hi> (even in religion, running into knowledge, and into worſhips and performances, before he feel a true and clear guidance) <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115389:44"/>
               <hi>ſhall not be innocent:</hi> nor the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs, when he comes to viſit for ſpiritual adultery and idolatry. The Apoſtles were exceeding tender in this point, for though they certainly and infallibly knew what was to be believed, yet they were not Lords over mens faith, but waited till he who is Lord of the faith, would open the way into mens conſciences. They did not take upon them to be able to turn the key, to let in truth and conviction into mens ſpirits (as men in theſe dayes have been too apt to undertake) but directed them to him who had the key, there to wait for the conviction and illumination of their minds, and ſo to receive in, as they found him give forth to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>be fully perſwaded in his own mind;</hi> take heed of receiving things t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoon, take heed of running into practiſes too ſoon, take heed of doing what ye ſee others do, but wait for your own particular guidance, and for a full perſwaſion from God what is his will concerning you. Though I know this to be a truth, yet do not ye receive it, till God make it manifeſt to you; receive truth from his hand, ſtay till he give it you. Indeed the main matter in religion is to keep out the wrong part, the forward part, the baſtardly birth from running into duties, catching of openings, and laying hold of promiſes; and to feel the heir born of the immortal ſeed, to whom all belongs, and that the other birth never afterwards get up above him, but be ſubdued and brought into ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Again, ſaith the Apoſtle, take heed of doing any thing
<hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> be not forward, be not haſty, wait for the leading, wait for the manifeſtation of the Spirit. Be ſure thou receive, what thou receives in the faith, and practiſe what thou practiſes in the faith: for
<hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſin,</hi> being an error from the principle of life, which is to guide: and thereby thou looſeſt ground, and diſhonoureſt Chriſt, and comeſt under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Apoſtle warns believers, to take heed of drawing one another on too faſt, or of judging one another in ſuch things as ſome of them might have light in, others not. He that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, not to judge him that did not eat: and he that did not eat not to judge him that did eat. Yea in matters of worſhip, he <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115389:44"/> that obſerved a day, and kept a Sabbath, not to judge him that obſerved not a day, or kept not a Sabbath, for the Jews which were truly converted, yet were hard to be drawn off from the obſervation of their Sabbath, and could hardly bear with the believing Gentiles, who were never taught to keep their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath with them, but were taught to eſteem every day and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie it to the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi>
14.5. And theſe who eſteemed every day, and dedicated it to the Lord (ceaſing from ſin, and reſting to him: for under the Goſpel we are not to ſet up a new type, but to enter by faith into the true reſt, which is the ſubſtance of what the other ſignified) could hardly bear with them who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a day. Even in the Apoſtles dayes, Chriſtians were too apt to ſtrive after a wrong unity, and uniformity in outward practiſes and obſervations, and to judge one another unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in theſe things. And mark, it is not the different practiſe from one another, that breaks the peace and the unity, but the judging of one another becauſe of different practiſes. He that keeps not a day, may unite in the ſame ſpirit, in the ſame life, in the ſame love with him that keeps a day, and he who keeps a day, may unite in heart and ſoul, with the ſame ſpirit and life in him who keeps not a day; but he that judgeth the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of either of theſe, errs from the ſpirit, from the love, from the life, and ſo breaks the bond of unity. And he that draws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to any practiſe, before the life in his own particular lead him, doth as much as in him lies to deſtroy the ſoul of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. This was the Apoſtles rule, for every one to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſingly to the Lord what he did, and not for one to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the light or conſcience of another (undervaluing his brother, or judging him becauſe his light and practiſes differed from his,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 10. of that 14. <hi>chap.</hi>) but every one to keep cloſe to their own meaſure of light, even to that proportion of faith and knowledge, which God of his mercy hath beſtowed on them. And here is the true unity in the Spirit, in the inward life, and not in an outward uniformity. That was not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Apoſtles dayes, nor is it neceſſary now: and that eye which ſo dotes upon it, overlooks the one thing which is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Men keeping cloſe to God, the Lord will lead them on faſt enough, and give them light faſt enough, for he taketh care of ſuch, and knoweth what light, and what practiſes are moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115389:45"/> for them:) but for men to walk on faſter than the Lord holds forth light to them, this overturns them, raiſing up a wrong thing in them, and the true birth hereby comes to ſuffer, to ſhrink, and be driven back. And O how ſweet and pleaſant is it to the truly ſpiritual eye, to ſee ſeveral ſorts of believers, ſeveral forms of Chriſtians in the School of Chriſt, every one learning their own leſſon, performing their own peculiar ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and knowing, owning, and loving one another in their ſeveral places, and different performances to their maſter, to whom they are to give an account, and not to quarrel with one another about their different practiſes! <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. For this is the true ground of love and unity, Not that ſuch a man walks and does juſt as I do, but becauſe I feel the ſame ſpirit of life in him, and in that he walks in his rank, in his own order, in his proper way and place of ſubjection to that. And this is far more pleaſing to me, than if he walked juſt in that track where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I walk: nay (ſo far as I am ſpiritual) I cannot ſo much as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he ſhould do ſo, until he be particularly led thereto, by the ſame ſpirit which led me. And he that knows what it is to receive any truths from the ſpirit, and to be led into practiſes by the ſpirit, and how prone the fleſhly part is to make haſt, and how dangerous that haſt is, will not be forward to preſs his knowledge or practiſes upon others, but rather wait patiently till the Lord fit them for the receiving thereof, and fear leaſt they ſhould receive and practiſe too ſoon, even in that part which cannot ſerve the Lord. And this I can truly ſay concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ſelf, I never found my Spirit forward to draw any, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to any thing I believed to be true, or to any practiſe or way of worſhip I obſerved or walked in, but deſired that the power and leadings of life might go before them, and was afraid leſt men ſhould receive things from my hand, and not from the Lords. Yea and this I very well remember, that when I walked in the way of Independency (as it hath been commonly called) I had more unity with, more love towards ſuch as were ſingle hearted in other wayes and practiſes of worſhip (whoſe ſpirits I had ſome feeling of in the true ſimplicity, and in the life) than with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of ſuch, who were very knowing and zealous in that way of Independency, in whom a wrong thing in the mean time had got up, which had cauſed them to ſwerve from the life and from the ſimplicity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115389:45"/>So that the true Church Government being in the ſpirit, and over the conſcience as in the ſight of God, the great care muſt be to keep it within its bounds, that nothing elſe govern but the Spirit, and that the government be extended only unto that which is to be governed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, care muſt be had that nothing govern in the Church of Chriſt, but the Spirit of Chriſt: that nothing elſe teach, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe exhort, nothing elſe admoniſh and reprove, nothing elſe cut off and caſt out. Every Miniſter in the Church is to watch over his own Spirit, that it intrude not into the work of God, that it take not upon it to be the teacher, the exhorter, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And every member is to wait in that meaſure of the Spirit which he hath received, to feel the goings forth of the Spirit in him that teacheth and governeth; and ſo to ſubject not to man, but to the Lord; to receive from the Lord, to obey the Lord. Not to know any Miniſter according to the fleſh, but to receive, and ſubmit to what comes from the Spirit, in the Spirit. Not to know <hi>Paul,</hi> or
<hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> but the Spirit miniſtring in them.
<hi>Paul</hi> may erre, <hi>Apollo</hi> may erre, <hi>Peter</hi> may erre (and did erre, when he compelled the Gentiles to live as the Jews, <hi>Gal.</hi>
2.14. for which <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to the face, <hi>verſ.</hi>
11.) and <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo did erre, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. but the Spirit cannot erre: and he that keeps to the meaſure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in himſelf, cannot let in any of their errors, if they ſhould erre, but is preſerved. For the leaſt meaſure of the Spirit is true, and gives true judgment: but he that receiveth never ſo great a meaſure of the Spirit, yet if he keep not low therein, but lifteth up himſelf becauſe thereof above his brethren, may eaſily erre himſelf, and draw aſide others into his error.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Care muſt be had that the conſcience be kept ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that nothing be received but according to the light in the conſcience. The conſcience is the ſeat of faith; and if it be not kept cloſe to the light which God lighteth there, faith is ſoon made ſhipwrack of. Chriſtianity is begun in the Spirit, which keepeth out the fleſhly part, with all its fleſhly wiſdome and reaſonings about ſpiritual things: and as the beginning is in the anointing, ſo muſt the progreſs be. As the Spirit begins in the conſcience by convincing that, by perſwading that, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up his light there, and leading the ſoul by that light: ſo that <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115389:46"/> light muſt ſtill be eyed, and according to its growth and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation in the conſcience, ſo muſt the ſoul ſtand ſtill, or go on.</p>
            <p>The great error of the ages of the Apoſtaſie hath been, to ſet up an outward order and uniformity, and to make mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences bend thereto, either by arguments of wiſdom, or by force; but the property of the true Church Government is, to leave the conſcience to its full liberty in the Lord, to preſerve it ſingle and entire for the Lord to exerciſe, and to ſeek unity in the light and in the ſpirit, walking ſweetly and harmoniouſly together in the midſt of different practiſes. Yea and he that hath faith, and can ſee beyond another, yet can have it to himſelf, and not diſturb his brother with it, but can deſcend and walk with him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his meaſure: and if his brother have any heavy burthen upon him, he can lend him his ſhoulder, and bear part of his burthen with him. O how ſweet and lovely is it to ſee brethren dwell together in unity, to ſee the true image of God raiſed in perſons, and they knowing and loving one another in that i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and bearing with one another through love, and helping one another under their temptations and diſtreſſes of ſpirit, which every one muſt expect to meet with.</p>
            <p>If thou art a Chriſtian indeed and in truth, preſerve thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pure and tender towards God, do not defile it with ſuch religious practiſes, duties, ordinances, &amp;c. as thou doſt not feel the Spirit leading thee into: for all ſuch are Idols, and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly pollute thee. And be tender alſo of thy brothers conſcience, and be not an inſtrument to draw him unto any thing, which the Lord leads him not into, but rejoyce if thou find him in ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heart ſtartling at any thing: for if he abide here faithful, his guide will in due ſeaſon appear to him, and clear up his way before him: but if he be too haſty, he may follow a wrong guid, and that guid will never lead him aright towards the Kingdom, but intangle him further and further from it.</p>
            <p>O how many have run a whoring from the Lord! how many have firſt loſt the guidance of his Spirit, and then drowned their life in religious performances! how many have drunk of the cup of fornication from the life, at the hands of the fleſhly wiſdome! how many have filled their ſpirits with New-Teſtament Idols and Images! how many have even hardened their hearts and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, by following the doctrines of men, their imaginary mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115389:46"/> of Scriptures, and the imaginations and dreams of their own hearts! Is it not time for men at length to turn back towards the Lord, to wait for the viſitation and light of his ſpirit, from whom they have gone a whoring, and whom in all theſe things they have grieved? And if ever any feel and enjoy the guidance of Gods ſpirit, their conſcience muſt be kept tender to it, and ready to hear and follow his voyce, who ſpeaks in ſpirit to that which is born of him, which inſallibly knows his voyce, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept clear) cannot doubt concerning it. <hi>My Sheep hear my voyce,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, they know it, and the voyce of the ſtrange ſpirit they know not, ſo as to follow it, but turn from it both in themſelves and others. But that which is not the Sheep, but hath only got the Sheeps cloathing, cries out, how ſhall we know the voyce of the ſpirit? We may be deceived. Nay that which is born of God, that which is the elect of God, cannot be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Wait therefore for the birth of the Spirit, to which the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is given for a guide, who infallibly guides it out of deceit. All deceivers are out of this birth, out of this ſpirit, perhaps in ſome birth or other framed from the Letter, and living in the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome practiſes and Ordinances from the Letter (under which cover they lie in wait to deceive) but ſtrangers to the life and power, and to that wiſdome which begets and bears to God. Thus the Jews erred, and deceived their proſelytes before the coming of Chriſt: Thus the Chriſtians (in name) have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally erred all along the Apoſtaſie, and indeed (for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity) have not been true Chriſtians, but only a perſecuted remnant amongſt them; whoſe life hath been nouriſhed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, not by doctrines and obſervations which they have been taught by the precepts of men, nor by the knowledge which they themſelves have gathered, but by a little bread dayly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them from the Father of mercies out of the Wilderneſs: that was the thing which nouriſhed their ſouls up to God, though many of them knew not diſtinctly what it was that nouriſhed them, nor how they came by it.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But is not uniformity lovely, and doth not the Apoſtle exhort Chriſtians to be of one mind, and were it not a ſweet thing if we were all of one heart and one way?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, uniformity is very lovely, and to be deſired and waited for, as the ſpirit, of the Lord which is one, leads
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115389:47"/> and drawes into one. But for the fleſhly part (the wiſe reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning part of man) by fleſhly waies and means to ſtrive to bring about a fleſhly uniformity, which inſnares and overbears the tender conſcience, this is not lovely, nor ſpiritual, nor Chriſtian. And the Apoſtle who exhorts Chriſtians to one mind, yet doth not bid them force one another into one mind, but walke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſweetly ſo far as they had attained, and wherein they were otherwiſe minded, God in his due time would reveal more to them, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.15, 16. He that hath, to him ſhall be given. And the intent and work of the Miniſtry (with the ſeveral mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of it) is to bring into the unity (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.) as perſons are able to follow, and not to force all men into one practiſe or way; that's the way to deſtroy the faith, and the true unity, and at beſt can introduce but a fleſhly appearance of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in ſuch a form of worſhip and godlineſs, as eats out the power. And for being of one heart and one way, bleſſed be the Lord, this is in meaſure known and witneſſed. The way is one, Chriſt the truth of God, and he that is in the faith, and in the obedience to that light which ſhines from his ſpirit into the heart of every believer, hath a taſt of the one heart, and of the one way; and knoweth that no variety of practiſes (which is of God) can make a breach in the true unity. This is the one way, for every one to be ſubject to that light of Chriſts ſpirit, which he hath received from Chriſt, and every one keeping here, there is alſo one heart kept in the midſt of all the variety, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of practiſes. And the unity being thus kept, all will come into one outwardly alſo at length, as the light growes in every one, and as every own growes into the light: but this muſt be patiently waited for from the hand of God (who hath the right way of effecting it, and who alone can do it) and not harſhly and cruelly attempted by the rough hand of man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115389:47"/>
            <head>Some Conſiderations concerning the State of Things, relating to what hath been, now is, and ſhortly is to come to paſs, warning all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to look about them, and to wait on the Lord for the unerring light of his Spirit, that they may know the times and ſeaſons, and the work which God is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the world, which is great and wonderful, and ſo may not be found fighters againſt God, his Truths, and the Witneſſes of this Age and Generation, more particularly lamenting over and exhorting
<hi>England.</hi> With a faithful Teſtimony concerning the
<hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THat the Spouſe of Chriſt, the true Church which God built in the Apoſtles daies by his Spirit, the Church againſt which the gates of hell could not prevail, the Church which was the Temple of the living God, the pillar and ground of truth, the Woman which was cloathed with the Sun, who had the Moon under her feet, and was crowned with a crown of twelve Stars, &amp;c. This Church (at the cloſe of the fight between <hi>Michael</hi> with his Angels, and the Dragon with his Angels) fled into the Wilderneſs, into the place prepared of God for her, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.6. having two wings of a great Eagle given her that ſhe might fly thither to her place, where ſhe was to abide, and be hid from the face of the Serpent, and to be fed with the living nouriſhment from the hand of the Father all the time of Antichriſts reign, which is ſaid to be a time, times, and half a time, <hi>verſ.</hi>
14. or one thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. or forty two months, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.2. And ſhe was accordingly gone out of ſight, inſomuch as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent could find her no more, but <hi>went to make war with the remnant of her ſeed, which keep the commandments of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Revel. 11.17.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115389:48"/>2. That the true Church cannot come out of the Wilderneſs, till the time of her abobe there (the ſet time appointed by God) be ended, nor then neither but by the outſtretched arm of the Lord,
<hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.13. She may mourn over her deſolate Wilderneſs ſtate, but ſhe cannot fly out of it, without the help of the wings of the ſame Eagle which were given her to fly into it. The Lord muſt pitty the duſt of
<hi>Sion,</hi> and by his everlaſting ſtrength and compaſſion raiſe up the tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> which is fallen down, or it can be reſtored no more, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the ſtate of the people of God, all this time of the true Churches abſence, hath been a ſtate of captivity. The ſeed hath been in bondage in <hi>Egypt</hi> the dark Land, in <hi>Babylon</hi> the Land of confuſion (for ſuch all the Church buildings, order and government have been in compare with the true order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church by the Spirit, which was known and enjoyed by the people of God before this her flight) where they have been mourning under their chains of darkneſs, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over their mother: for Zion hath been laid waſt and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem (the holy City) hath been troden under foot by the Gentiles, to whom the outward Court was given, when God took down his building, and ſecured his Temple, Altar, and the worſhippers therein, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. And in this ſtate God finds his people, when he comes to overthrow her (to bring death, and mourning, and famine, and fire, upon her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8.) and to redeem them: for then the voice goes forth from the ſpirit of the Lord, to the ſpirits of his people, <hi>Come out of her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 4. Why, were the people of God in her till now? yea, till the very hour of her judgment, and are many of them in great danger of ſtaying there, even till they feel her plagues. They that ſit down in any Church-building, taking it for <hi>Sion,</hi> before Gods ſeaſon of building his <hi>Sion,</hi> ſit down but in <hi>Babylon,</hi> it is no other, though they who have drunk of the falſe womans cup (new mixed for them, and ſo are inchanted a freſh into ſome new fine-painted bed of her fornication) cannot believe it to be ſo.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That when God redeems his people out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> he brings them not immediately unto <hi>Sion</hi> (not immediately into a built City) but into the wilderneſs where the Church lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115389:48"/> where they are prepared and fitted for the holy Land, and circumciſed in ſpirit before their entrance. There is a long tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel from
<hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Zion,</hi> wherein the haſty ſpirit, the rough ſpirit, the exalted ſpirit, the murmuring ſpirit, the ſelf-will, ſelf-worſhip, ſelf-wiſdom, knowledge, and righteouſneſs, (all which are of great price in <hi>Babylon</hi>) is cut down, and the ſpirit broken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> emptyed, made poor, deeply humbled, and ſo prepared for Gods holy Hill. When a Babyloniſh building or way of worſhip is diſcovered, man would fain have another ready, to put in the place of it ſo ſoon as it is pulled down. Thus mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would order it, but the Lord will not have it ſo, but there muſt be a ſeaſon of deſolation, of ſtripping, of nakedneſs, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncloathed of all the purple and ſcarlet dye of
<hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 17.4. a pulling off the ornaments of all the knowledge, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ordinances, duties, experiences, &amp;c. which are held and practiſed out of the pure life. And in this ſtate of miſery and fore diſtreſs, the Lord laies the foundation of the new heavens, and of the new earth in the ſpirits of his people, which when it is finiſhed, then at length he ſaith to <hi>Zion, Thou my people,</hi> Iſa. 51.16.</p>
            <p>Obſerve therefore the error of the reformations ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy. They have been ſtill building too faſt, and not waiting on God to be hewn and ſquared, and fitted for his building. The reformed Churches have ſtill been built of ſtones, before they were made ready for the building. They have not waited their time of preparation in the wilderneſs, nor have they wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Gods building them up into a Temple, nor for the time and ſeaſon wherein it is Gods pleaſure to build. So that though they did well in ſeperating from that which was corrupt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly evil, yet they did not well in making haſt into another way of their own forming, but ſhould have waited for Gods manifeſtation of the good, and for his leading of them by his ſpirit into it. And by this means it hath come to paſſe, that though there hath been a pure thing often ſtirring towards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, yet by an over forward haſtening to build, the good hath been quenched, and the evil hath again (under a new cover or form of worſhip) overgrown it, and then hath been ready to revile and perſecute the good in others: but this the eye, which is overtaken with the appearing beauty of its building
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115389:49"/> (having concluded it to be according to the will of God revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Scriptures) cannot diſcern.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That when <hi>Zion</hi> is rebuilt, when the Church its heaven is again ſtretched forth (wherein ſhe was ſeated before ſhe fled into the Wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. thoſe that are Gods faithful witneſſes (into whom his ſpirit of life hath entred, and whom he hath cauſed to ſtand upon their feet) ſhall aſcend up to heaven in a cloud, which their very enemies ſhall behold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12. And this was done in the time of a great Earth-quake, wherein the tenth part of the City fell,
<hi>ver.</hi> 13. The ſhaking at this time is very great in this Nation, let men mark what will be the iſſue, and obſerve whether (notwithſtanding all the ſeeming contrarieties) the Lord God do not ſo order it, as to bring a conſiderable part of <hi>Babylon</hi> down, and of the powers that uphold her.</p>
            <p>The people of God, all this time of Antichriſts reign, have been a ſuffering people. The tender-hearted every where (whoſe ſouls could only bow to the Lord, who could not receive do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines from men, or fall into worſhips and practiſes at the will of man) have lain open to Church-cenſures (as they call them) and to the Magiſtrates indignation under the names of Hereticks, Blaſphemers, Seducers, and diſturbers of the peace both of Church and ſtate: and indeed ſo far as any have taſted of the true light and power of Chriſt, and have been called forth by him to be his witneſſes, they could not but be diſturbers of the carnal peace and ſecurity of the Antichriſtian congregations, againſt whom they witneſſed. When the true Church fled into the Wilderneſs, the Serpent caſt a flood after her: ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached and blaſphemed for an Harlot, a Strumpet, one that was not the Lambs wife, as ſhe pretended, <hi>Rev.</hi>
12.15. For the Dragon which perſecuted her (having now gained her ground) had ſet up another woman fot the true Church, and had decked her richly,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. inſomuch as ſhe was admired for her beauty by all the Kings and inhabiters of the earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. but ſhe which was indeed the true woman, was trampled upon and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed even by all the outward worſhippers, in the outward court all over the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. And if thoſe of the Synnagogue of Satan, could contend to be the true Jews and the true Church, even while the true Church was ſtanding, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.9. no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115389:49"/> though they carry it clear in their ſeveral forms and diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, all the time of her flight and abſence, eſpecially they appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring both in the place where ſhe once was, and in her very dreſs: and here is the eye of Gods ſpirit, and of the wiſdom he gives to his babes tryed, even to diſcern and fly from her here. Let her paint never ſo often, change her dreſſes in every hour of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, come nearer and nearer into the likeneſs of the true Church: yet that which is born of the truth eſpieth her, and the young man whoſe care is kept open to the voice of wiſdom, (which uttereth it ſelf in the immortal ſeed) eſcapeth her bed, and is not defiled with the great Whore, nor with any of her women or daughters, who are borne of her after her ſpirit, though they deny her, and ſeem much to differ from her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. Enter into the miſtery of life (from out of the reach of the ſpirit of witchcraft) and read me here, that in the true eternal light of all the living, thou maiſt perceive the miſtery of deceit, and eſcape as a bird from the ſnare, and live. Now the true Church being thus fled, what becomes of her ſeed? they muſt needs be ſcattered, they can no more be found in a body as before, there is now but a remnant left which <hi>keep the commandments of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe the Dragon applies himſelf ſtill to manage the war againſt,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17. And the Beaſt (to whom the Dragon gave his power,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. and upon whom the falſe Church was found ſitting even to the very laſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3.) did not only make war with the Saints, but alſo overcome them: and this power was given him over all kindreds, and tongues and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. of <hi>chap.</hi> 13. So that the holy City was to be kept down and trampled under foot by the falſe worſhippers, under one form or appearance of Church-worſhip or other, all the time of the Beaſts reign, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. And as the Beaſt did kill them: ſo the woman that ſat upon the Beaſt drunk their blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6. For mark, the Dragon, the firſt Beaſt, the ſecond Beaſt with the falſe Church are all in unity together, &amp; drive on their war and deſign under diſguiſes and appearances of truths &amp; Church-worſhip and diſcipline againſt the Lamb &amp; his followers, againſt every appearance of Chriſt in his truth &amp; people. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, where he can get into any form without the power, there he manageth his war by the form againſt the power. Thus <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115389:50"/> in <hi>Popery</hi> by crying up holy Church, holy Church, he knocks down al the ſpringings up of truth there: ſo in
<hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> by cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up that form, how did he knock down the buildings up of the true life and power there alſo. And if he be driven out there, then he ſtands ready to enter into the next form, either of
<hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> or <hi>Independency,</hi> that he may not want the advantage of a cover to keep his war on foot ſtill againſt the Saints and the truths of Chriſt: and here lies his ſtrength; and the liker his form is to that which once was true, the better it ſerves to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, and he has better advantage of fighting under it againſt Chriſt, his truths and people, than under another which is not ſo like. But Antichriſts reign, (who hath taken the name upon him without the nature, and ſo perſecuted the true nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covered with the name) is to have an end, yea (bleſſed be the Lord) it is in part ended, and the Lambs day is already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, the outſtretched arme of the Lords everlaſting power is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and revealing more and more: yea <hi>Babylon</hi> is already diſcovered, her waters are dryed up, her nakedneſs under all her coverings is ſeen, her very life and ſpirit is ſtruck at, her kingdom totters dayly; the ſtakes alſo of Zions tabernacle are ſtrengthening daily, and the Lord is ſtretching out her curtains, and inlarging her territories; and the wrath iſſues out more and more from the Throne, and dreadful woes and plagues are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, who are either upholding any old likeneſſes of what once was true, or ſetting up any new ones in this day of Gods power, wherein he is redeeming and bringing forth the life it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Is it not plain that the Beaſt (or Antichriſt who ſat in the Tem-of God, ruling there as a Beaſt by outward force, without the inward life and power, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.) had power given him to continue his war againſt the Saints, till the very expiration of the forty two months?
<hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5. and was not this power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him over all kindreds and Tongues and Nations, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. Did not the falſe Church or falſe woman, till the very end of this time (in one appearance or other, under ſome form of worſhip or other; ſometimes in a groſſer and more loathſome, ſometimes in a finer and more taking dreſs) ſtill goe for the true Church, being upheld by the Kings and inhabiters of the earth, who all drank of her cup of fornication? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2, 4. Was not the holy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115389:50"/> City (or true Church) trod under foot all this while in every kindred, nation, &amp;c. by the heatheniſh ſpirit of the Antichriſtian Chriſtians therein, who made a great ſhew of zeal and worſhip in the outward court? <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. For while the holy City is to remain unbuilt, he that will worſhip in it, muſt ſink into its ruins, and lye deſolate with it: but he that will be building before Gods time, rejects the corner ſtone, which lies hid in the ruins of this City, and ſo builds up a <hi>Babylon,</hi> to which though he gives the name of
<hi>Zion,</hi> yet it is not ſo in truth; but <hi>Zion</hi> lies underneath, in the duſt, trampled upon and ſet at nought by him and his building. Now ſhall the forty two months ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have an end and ſhall the holy City never riſe again from under the feet of the Antichriſtian profeſſors and worſhippers in the outward Court? ſhall the walls of <hi>Zion</hi> never be built more? or is it to be expected, when the Lord begins to build her up and bring her forth, that ever any of the falſe Churches ſhould own her? O fear therefore before the Lord, every one entring into that in his own heart, which (being hearkened unto) teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the fear, and breaketh the pride, loftineſs, and conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the high imagining mind, which firſt builds up with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions about Church, Religion, and worſhip without the ſpirit, and then is offended with that which cannot bow to thoſe images. But be it known unto you, O Nations and Powers of the Earth, that the Lord hath raiſed up a people, whoſe knees can alone bow at the name of Jeſus, and whoſe tongues can alone confeſs to him. And if <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> ſpirit ſhould heat a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of affliction ſeven times hotter, then it hath yet been heated all this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the cruel ſufferings of Gods dear people, and threaten all with it, that will not bow to the image or form of worſhip which he ſets up, yet this we know aſſuredly, that the Lord hath begotten a ſeed which he can deliver, and which we do not doubt but he will deliver, let Antichriſts Sea &amp; Waves roare never ſo loud againſt them. But however, bow to any image they cannot: for they have taſted of the living truth it ſelf, which hath made them free from ſuch images and idols wherein they were before intangled; and the ſpirit of the Lord calleth aloud to them to ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath ſet them free, and not to receive any more the yoke of <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115389:51"/> bondage upon their necks, but to draw under the ſweet gentle yoak of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>O <hi>England, England,</hi> how ſad is thy ſtate! how great &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things hath the Lord done in thee, but thou ſtill overlookeſt his hand, and art offended with the work of his Spirit, becauſe it ſutes not with thy fleſhly deſires and intereſts! O <hi>England, England,</hi> what will become of thee! the Lord hath kindled his ſire, and thou addeſt fewel daily. The Lord is ariſen to make inquiſition for the ſufferings and blood of his people, and thou inſtead of repenting of what thou haſt done, art greedy of more. Thou haſt deeply drunk of the whores cup of fornication, and that makes thee thus thirſty after the Saints blood. Thou cryeſt out againſt thoſe that put the Martyrs to death, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Jews did againſt thoſe that put the Prophets to death; and yet perſecuteſt their Spirit wherever it appears in further proſecution of the work of reformation at this day, even as the Jews did perſecute the Spirit of the Prophets in Chriſt and his Apoſtles. O mourn to the Lord to open thine eyes, that thou maiſt not thus ſtand any longer in his way. Let him bring forth his Church, let him ſet up his truth, let him advance his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and do not thou go about to limit the ſpirit of the holy one in them. There's none of theſe will harm thee, but bring bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon thee. Let thy Governors keep within their bounds, and be a defence upon all people in their juſt rights and liberties, and ſee if from that day he do not bleſs thee. But if there be one thing in the Lords heart concerning his people, and another thing in thine; if he reſolve to bring them forth to his praiſe, and to give them their liberty in their obedience to his Spirit, &amp; thou reſolve they ſhall come under thy yoaks and bonds, how can ye agree? your wrath by this means muſt needs be kindled againſt each other, and he that hath moſt ſtrength will carry it. For as the day of your wrath is come, to ſee the people of God ſo increaſe, and grow bold in his truth and power: ſo the day of his wrath is come, to ſee his people ſo reproached, hated, hunted, and perſecuted for his names ſake,
<hi>Revel.</hi> 11.18. And take heed leſt upon that ſpirit, which in this generation ſtill continues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, the ſufferings, perſecutions, and blood of all the Saints and Martyrs (ſhed all the time of Antichriſts raign), be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. The blood of all the Prophets from <hi>Abel</hi> to
<hi>Zacharias,</hi> 
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115389:51"/> was required of that great profeſſing generation of the Jews, who ſpake ſuch great words of
<hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, but perſecuted Chriſt and his Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35. And the blood of all the ſouls that lie under the Altar, crying, <hi>how long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> They were bid to reſt a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then the blood of all that ever was ſlain ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles dayes, is to be required on that generation of profeſſors, who are found even to the very laſt in the perſecuting ſpirit, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.10, 11.</p>
            <p>I do not write this to reproach any ſort of profeſſors, but in true love and bowels of compaſſion, that ſuch among them as ever had any taſt of God, and of his ſweet meek ſpirit, but are now grown hard, and found ſmiting their fellow ſervants, may (if it be poſſible) hear the Lords voyce, which yet tenderly calls after them, that they may not be cut in pieces, and receive their portion of wrath with <hi>Babylon, Mat.</hi>
24.49, 50, 51. <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. As for me, I am poor and weak (a worm, and no man) one who hath been a mourner and wanderer in a ſtrange land all my dayes, yea I have been that fool, who though I have often been very neer, yet ſtill knew not the way to the city of my God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.15. and at preſent, I am very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and unfit to be an inſtrument in the Lords hand, for the reclaiming of any man from his wanderings. Yet this I can in truth and uprightneſs ſay concerning the Lords gracious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with me, that in the bowels of his mercy he hath viſited me and turned my face towards his <hi>Zion:</hi> and in his life and Spirit (as he pleaſeth to keep me freſh and open) I know both my way and my leader, and alſo that which is mine enemy, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually endeavoureth to betray and devour me. And, I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, I lie not, I know alſo what I have felt wrath and miſery upon, and that what the Lord hath ſo long and ſo ſeverely ſmitten in me, he will not ſpare in others. O that men could hear, and avoid my bed of torment, where I ſuffered a moſt dreadful and terrible hell for many years (bear with me, for I cannot call it leſs) though without either guilt upon my Spirit, or fear of wrath, being juſtified before God in my own conſcience (till afterwards under long continuance of miſery and thick darkneſs, ſome guilt was contracted) and having a <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115389:52"/> ſecret root of hope concerning good from God, if once I might appear in his preſence to plead my cauſe there. Who can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly believe the miſery I endured (if it were related) and yet it had not the leaſt mixture of either of theſe in it for a long time. But after this, through the ignorance and thick darkneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I had been long overwhelmed, not knowing what had been and ſtill was preſent with me, the tempter by his ſubtilty got in, and led out my mind from what had viſited and ſought after me all my dayes, to wait and hope for ſome great appearance to ſet me to rights: and here my loſs was very great, my ſoul being hereby removed far away from the preſent feeling of the ſpring of my life, and drawn to neglect the little dawnings of that light, which ſhineth more and more to the perfect day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving concluded in my ſelf that no leſs would ſuffice to heal me, than its breaking forth in its full ſtrength, even as at noon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me. Thus I deſpiſed the day of ſmall things, and was ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into a gaping after, and a waiting for that, which is never ſo to be received: but the little ſeed of light being received, and finding good and honeſt earth, groweth up therein even to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and then knoweth and receiveth the light of the day in its full ſtrength. And although there was ſuch a ſavour of God laſt in me, that upon the firſt converſe with this People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I could own the voyce of God in them, and ſet to my ſeal (as in the preſence of God) that it was the true life and power of the moſt high whereof they were born, yet I could not but deſpiſe it as a weak and low appearance thereof, yea and ſtarted back from it, as being ſuch a kind of diſpenſation of life and power as was to paſs away, and the paſſing away whereof from me had made me ſo miſerable. And now I am as one born out of due time, and come lagging behind, feeling my ſelf alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unworthy to be numbred amongſt them, or to bear a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to that truth and power of life wherein they flouriſh, and by which they are redeemed and bought out of the earth with the price of the living immortal blood of Jeſus, by which (together with the word of his teſtimony) they cannot but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome all the powers of darkneſs (with all the Powers of the earth which ſtand in the darkneſs, and fight under the darkneſs) being taught thereby not to love their lives unto the death. But the ſcoffing conceited Profeſſor will be ready to ſay, <hi>What are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115389:52"/> thoſe the only People? Others beſides them, are as dear to God as they. There are many in forms equal to them, and many out of forms, far beyond them.</hi> Whereto I anſwer thus, Yea, there are ſo in the ſcale of mans judgment, but not ſo in the meaſure of the Sanctuary. Theſe are the only redeemed People that my ſoul knows of. There is a ſeed beſides them, not yet gathered, but in <hi>Babylon,</hi> whom the Lord (in his due ſeaſon) will gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame light, life and power: but there is no other Saviour, but that light eternal which hath given them life, and dwels in them; who is riſen in them, come to them, and hath taken them into himſelf, in whom they are, even in him that is true, who is the Son of God, the true God, and the life eternal, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. who hath poured forth his ſpirit upon them, in which they Miniſter and gather up to God, thoſe who have an ear to hear the voyce of his Spirit. Beware therefore, O ye Nations and Powers of the earth, what ye do againſt this People: for ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail by any inchantment, againſt theſe whom the Lord hath bleſſed: but the more ye ſtrive to villifie and ſuppreſs them, the more will the Lord magnifie and exalt them. And the life which God hath raiſed up in them muſt reign, do what ye can againſt it. O abaſe your ſelves, and kiſs the Son, O Profeſſors and Powers of the earth, that ye be not cut off; for the Lords hand is lifted up, and in his jealouſie he will ſmite home for the ſake of <hi>Zion,</hi> for his ear hath heard the cry of the poor and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whom no man regardeth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.10, 11.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
